<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The present state of Hungary. Or, A geographical and historical description of that kingdom giving an account of the nature of the country, and of its inhabitants, of its government and policy; its religion and laws; of its division into counties and provinces; of its towns, castles, forts, rivers lakes, mountains, product, mines, minerals, and other rarities. Together, with the memorable battles and sieges that have happened there since the time of the Romans; but more particularly since the Turkish invasions. To which is added, a short account of Transilvania, and the lofty titles taken by those Turkish emperours, who have made war in those countries.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1687</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 204 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 90 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A55718</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P3266</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R218986</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99830528</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99830528</idno>
            <idno type="VID">34980</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A55718)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 34980)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2109:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The present state of Hungary. Or, A geographical and historical description of that kingdom giving an account of the nature of the country, and of its inhabitants, of its government and policy; its religion and laws; of its division into counties and provinces; of its towns, castles, forts, rivers lakes, mountains, product, mines, minerals, and other rarities. Together, with the memorable battles and sieges that have happened there since the time of the Romans; but more particularly since the Turkish invasions. To which is added, a short account of Transilvania, and the lofty titles taken by those Turkish emperours, who have made war in those countries.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 168, [8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for H. Rhodes next door to the Swan-Tavern, near Brides-Lane in Fleet-Street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Lond. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1687.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With a table of contents, index, and two final advertisment leaves.</note>
                  <note>With an license to print on verso of title page, signed and dated: Licensed, August 12. R.L.S.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original at the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hungary --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Hungary --  Politics and government --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Hungary --  Description and travel --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Transylvania (Romania) --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:34980:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:34980:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE <hi>Preſent State</hi> OF HUNGARY.</p>
            <p>OR, A Geographical and Hiſtorical De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of that Kingdom, giving an account of the Nature of the Country, and of its In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants, of its Government and Policy; its Religion and Laws; of its Diviſion into Counties and Provinces; of its Towns, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, Forts, Rivers Lakes, Mountains, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct, Mines, Minerals, and other Rarities.</p>
            <p>TOGETHER, With the Memorable Battles and Sieg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es that have happened there ſince the time of the <hi>Romans;</hi> but more particularly ſince the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Invaſions.</p>
            <p>To which is added, A ſhort Account of <hi>Tranſilvania,</hi> and the lofty Titles taken by thoſe <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours, who have made War in thoſe Countries.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lond.</hi> Printed for <hi>H. Rhodes</hi> next door to the <hi>Swan-Tavern,</hi> near <hi>Brides-Lane</hi> in <hi>Fleet-Street,</hi> 1687.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:34980:2"/>
            <p>Licenſed, <hi>Auguſt</hi> 12. <hi>R. L. S.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:34980:2"/>
            <head>A TABLE OF THE CHAPTERS.</head>
            <list>
               <label>CHAP. I.</label>
               <item>OF the Names of <hi>Hungary,</hi> its Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits, Diviſion, Rivers, Lakes and Mountains. <hi>Page 1</hi>
               </item>
               <label>CHAP. II.</label>
               <item>Of the Country of <hi>Hungary</hi> and it's In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants. <hi>Page 3</hi>
               </item>
               <label>CHAP. III.</label>
               <item>Of the Princes and Nations, that have made Progreſs in <hi>Hungary. Page 5</hi>
               </item>
               <label>CHAP. IV.</label>
               <item>Of a Chronological Succeſſion of the Kings of <hi>Hungary. Page 8</hi>
               </item>
               <label>CHAP. V.</label>
               <item>Of the Authors who treat of <hi>Hungary. Page 11</hi>
               </item>
               <label>CHAP. VI.</label>
               <item>Of the Towns of Upper <hi>Hungary</hi> and their Deſcription. <hi>Page 12</hi>
               </item>
               <label>CHAP. VII.</label>
               <item>Of the Towns of the Lower Hungary. <hi>Page 38</hi>
               </item>
               <label>CHAP. VIII.</label>
               <item>Of the Rivers, of <hi>Hungary,</hi> and their Deſcription. <hi>Page 73</hi>
               </item>
               <label>CHAP. IX.</label>
               <item>Of the Diviſion of the Kingdom of <hi>Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> into Counties, and their Names. <hi>Page 81</hi>
               </item>
               <label>
                  <pb facs="tcp:34980:3"/>
                  <hi>CHAP. X.</hi>
               </label>
               <item>Of the Eſtates of <hi>Hungary. Page 84</hi>
               </item>
               <label>CHAP. XI.</label>
               <item>Of the chief Palat. Nobility of <hi>Hung. Page 68</hi>
               </item>
               <label>CHAP. XII.</label>
               <item>Of the State of the Palatin of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Hungary,</hi> his Quality, Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and Preheminence, with a Liſt of thoſe who in this laſt Age have been Elected to that Office. <hi>Page 89</hi>
               </item>
               <label>CHAP. XIII.</label>
               <item>Of the Arms of the Kingdom of <hi>Hunga<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry,</hi> and in what manner the Kings have given them. <hi>Page 92</hi>
               </item>
               <label>CHAP. XIV.</label>
               <item>Of the memorable Battles that have been fought in <hi>Hungary. Page 97</hi>
               </item>
               <label>CHAP. XV.</label>
               <item>Of the Ceremon. obſerved in the Coron. of the Kings and Queens of <hi>Hungary. Page 133</hi>
               </item>
               <label>CHAP. XVI.</label>
               <item>Of the Deſcription of <hi>Tranſilvania,</hi> anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently united to <hi>Hungary</hi> and the Princes who have Reigned in it, ſince the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of this Age, to the preſent time. <hi>Page 142</hi>
               </item>
               <label>CHAP. XVII.</label>
               <item>Of the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Emperors, who in Progreſs of time have invaded, ſubdued, and uſurped the greateſt part of <hi>Hungary Page 146</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:34980:3"/>
            <head>THE Preſent State OF HUNGARY: OR An Hiſtorical, and Geographical Deſcription of that Kingdom.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p> Of its Names, Bounds, Diviſion, Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, Lakes and Mountains.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE Kingdom of <hi>Hungary,</hi> belonging by Right to the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> but, in a great part, invaded and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:34980:4"/> uſurped by the <hi>Turks,</hi> lies betwixt the 39. and 47. degree of Longitude, and from the 45. to the 49. of North Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, or thereabouts: It is part of the Ancient <hi>Pannonia,</hi> called <hi>Magiar</hi> by the <hi>Turks; Wegierska,</hi> by the <hi>Sclavoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans; Hungerland,</hi> by the <hi>Germans; On<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garia,</hi> by the <hi>Italians</hi> and <hi>Spaniards; Hongrie,</hi> by the <hi>French;</hi> and <hi>Hungary</hi> by the <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Bounds of it are <hi>Tranſilvania</hi> to the Eaſt; <hi>Poland</hi> and <hi>Ruſſia</hi> to the North; <hi>Moravia, Auſtria</hi> and <hi>Styria</hi> to the Weſt; and <hi>Servia</hi> and <hi>Boſnia</hi> to the South.</p>
               <p>The Figure of this Kingdom is ſquare, its Corners looking to the four parts of the World.</p>
               <p>It is divided into the Upper and Lower <hi>Hungary;</hi> the Upper is on the ſide of the <hi>Danube,</hi> towards <hi>Poland</hi> and <hi>Tranſilvania;</hi> and the Lower on the other ſide of the ſame River.</p>
               <p>Heretofore it contained above Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venty Counties, but at preſent it has only about fifty; whereof before this laſt War Twenty ſix were ſubject to the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Tyranny. It may be alſo divided into the part held by the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:34980:4"/> and that which is under the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Dominion.</p>
               <p>Its chief Rivers are, the <hi>Raab,</hi> the <hi>Wag,</hi> the <hi>Gran,</hi> the <hi>Teiſſe,</hi> the <hi>Sarviliſe,</hi> which comes out of the lake <hi>Balathon,</hi> and the <hi>Donau.</hi> The leſs conſiderable are the <hi>Newſidl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r, Reckzkerle,</hi> and ſome others.</p>
               <p>The higheſt Mountains of <hi>Hungary</hi> are the <hi>Carpathian</hi> Mountains, towards <hi>Poland</hi> and <hi>Tranſilvania.</hi> The richeſt are betwixt <hi>Buda</hi> and <hi>Strigonium,</hi> which have Mines affording excellent Mettals, and eſpecially Quick-ſilver.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p> Of the Country of <hi>Hungary,</hi> and its Inhabitants.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE Air of this Country is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wholeſom, and eſpecially to Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers; and it is obſerved to engender a great deal of Vermine. The Waters, excepting that of the <hi>Danube,</hi> are not good, and the Author <hi>de Mirabilibus Hungariae</hi> obſerves, that there are Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:34980:5"/> in <hi>Hungary,</hi> whoſe Waters are Poyſonous, which increaſe and dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh with the Moon, and are quite dried up when that Luminary is in the Full. There are other Fountains in it alſo, that turn into Stone any thing that is caſt into them; others which are hot in Winter, and freeze in Sum<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mer; and others whoſe Waters are ſowriſh, ſalt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> There are in i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> alſo ſeveral Mines of Salt, Gold, Sil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ver, Copper, Steel and Iron. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Soil is very fruitful, in ſo much, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſome have thought, that <hi>Hungary</hi> alone was ſufficient to furniſh all <hi>Europe</hi> with Corn. Its Paſturages are wonderful and ſo great is the plenty of Wild Beaſts and Fowl, of Fiſh and Cattle that the Country People live for moſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> part on the Fleſh of Wild Boars an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Veniſon. An hundred Carps hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> been ſold there for a <hi>Noble;</hi> and i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hath been obſerved, that in one yea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> above Fourſcore thouſand Oxen hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> been brought from thence into <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny.</hi> The <hi>Hungarians</hi> are Warlike, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cruel, proud, revengeful, and ſo i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> united together, that it is no wonde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they have been a Prey to the <hi>Barbar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ans.</hi>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:34980:5"/> They ſpeak ſeveral Languages, and eſpecially <hi>Latin,</hi> which is very familiar to them; the Gentry are magnificent, and all great Lovers of Horſes, Hunting and good Chear. The <hi>Hungarians</hi> love not the <hi>Germans;</hi> yet the Nobility adhere to the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> to ſecure themſelves from the Oppreſſion of the <hi>Turks,</hi> who va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue a Peaſant as much as a Gentleman. The ſtrength of the Country conſiſts in light Horſe-Men. The Troopers there are called <hi>Huſſars,</hi> and the Foot <hi>Heydukes.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p> Of the Princes and Nations, who have made any Progreſs in <hi>Hungary.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE firſt of the <hi>Romans</hi> that made any Progreſs in <hi>Hungary</hi> was <hi>Julius Coeſar,</hi> other Captains con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued them after him, untill the time of <hi>Tiberius,</hi> who entirely ſubjected that Kingdom. Afterwards upon the Fall of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, the <hi>Goths</hi>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:34980:6"/> ſeiz'd it, and that Kingdom became Prey to the <hi>Huns</hi> and <hi>Lombards,</hi> who were driven out by the former in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> eighth Century. For certain crue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> People of <hi>Scythia,</hi> called <hi>Hongres,</hi> tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lived only on Blood, poſſeſſed them ſelves of all that Country, which a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> preſent we call <hi>Hungary.</hi> They who treat of <hi>Hungary,</hi> reckon <hi>Balamir</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Balamber</hi> amongſt the Kings of tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Countrey; he reigned fifty ſix years and had a Son <hi>Mundſur</hi> or <hi>Mundiaque</hi> who died before his Father. <hi>Aptar</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> alſo reckoned amongſt thoſe Kings and the two Brothers, <hi>Bleda,</hi> killed in the Year, 444. and <hi>Attila,</hi> called the Scourge of God, who died in the year 453. His Children made a cruel Wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> againſt one another, and loſt the Con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>queſts of their Father. The <hi>Huns</hi> made another Irruption into <hi>Pannonia,</hi> about the Year 744. under the Conduct o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> one named <hi>Amie,</hi> who had <hi>Arphad</hi> for his Succeſſor. Theſe gave the name to <hi>Hungary. Sultan,</hi> one of the iſſue of that <hi>Arphad,</hi> was, as it is ſaid, the Father of <hi>Toxa</hi> or <hi>Toxis,</hi> and this Man begot <hi>Geiza,</hi> the Father of St. <hi>Stephen,</hi> with whom I ſhall begin the Chrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logical
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:34980:6"/> Succeſſion of the Kings of <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary.</hi> He was Crowned in the year, 1000. or 1020. according to others. Since that time the <hi>Hungarians</hi> had Kings, who governed them peaceably<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> enough, until after the Death of <hi>Loüis,</hi> called the Great, whoſe Daughter and Heireſs <hi>Marie</hi> was Married to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour <hi>Sigiſmond</hi> of <hi>Luxemburg;</hi> but his Government diſpleaſing them, they called in <hi>Charles de Duras</hi> King of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,</hi> and <hi>Stephen,</hi> Vaivod of <hi>Tranſilva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,</hi> who had his recourſe to <hi>Bajazet</hi> the Firſt, Emperour of the <hi>Turks;</hi> from thence began the Miſeries of that Kingdom, which ſince the year 1394. hath been always almoſt the ſeat of War, and became a Prey to the <hi>Turks;</hi> and eſpecially under <hi>Amurath, Solyman,</hi> and others. The Kingdom of <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary</hi> is partly poſſeſſed by the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> and partly by the <hi>Infidels.</hi> The former rendred it Hereditary af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Death of <hi>Loüis</hi> the Young, who periſhed at the Battle of <hi>Mohacs,</hi> in the year 1526. <hi>John de Zapol,</hi> Count of <hi>Scepua,</hi> was ſaluted King by part of the <hi>Hungarians,</hi> and <hi>Ferdinand</hi> of <hi>Auſtria</hi> by the reſt, who carried it
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:34980:7"/> from his Competitor. The Eſtates of this Kingdom are divided into four Bodies. 1. The Clergy. 2. The Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons. 3. The Nobles. 4. The Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al and Free Towns. The Religion of it is divided, and the Manners of the People odd. The <hi>Hungarians</hi> were converted to the Faith by <hi>Giſle</hi> Siſter to St. <hi>Henry,</hi> who married their King St. <hi>Stephen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p> A Chronological Succeſſion of the Kings of <hi>Hungary.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>IN the year 1000. or 1020. St. <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen,</hi> died in 1038.</p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell role="label"> </cell>
                        <cell role="label">years</cell>
                        <cell role="label">months</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1038. </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Peter</hi> the <hi>German</hi> reigned</cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1042. </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Ovon</hi> or <hi>Aban</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1044. </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Peter</hi> the <hi>German</hi> reſtor'd</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1046. </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Andrew</hi> I.</cell>
                        <cell>15</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1061. </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Bela</hi> I.</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1063. </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Salomon</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>11</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1074. </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Geiza</hi> or <hi>Gezcza</hi> I.</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1077. </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Ladiſlaus</hi> I.</cell>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1095 </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Coloman</hi> or <hi>Colan</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>19</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:34980:7"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1114. </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Stephen</hi> II.</cell>
                        <cell>18</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1132. </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Bela</hi> II.</cell>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1141. </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Geiza</hi> II.</cell>
                        <cell>20</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1161. </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Stephen</hi> III.</cell>
                        <cell>11</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1172. </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Ladiſlaus</hi> the Uſurper</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1172. </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Stephen</hi> IV.</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1173. </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Bela</hi> III.</cell>
                        <cell>23</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1193. </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Emeri</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1204. </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Ladiſlaus</hi> II.</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1205. </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Andrew</hi> II. called of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſhalem.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>30</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1235. </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Bela</hi> IV.</cell>
                        <cell>25</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1260. </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Stephen</hi> V.</cell>
                        <cell>12</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1272. </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Ladiſlaus</hi> III.</cell>
                        <cell>18</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1290. </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Andrew</hi> III. called the <hi>Venetian</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>11</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Charles</hi> I. called <hi>Martel.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1301. </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Wenceſlaus</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1305. </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Otho.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1310. </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Charles Robert</hi> or <hi>Charo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>32</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1342. </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Loüis</hi> I.</cell>
                        <cell>40</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1382. </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Marie</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1383. </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Charles</hi> III. called the Little</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1387. </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Sigiſmond</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>51</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1438. </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Albert</hi> of <hi>Auſtria</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1440. </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Ladiſlaus</hi> IV.</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:34980:8"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1445. </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>John Corvin,</hi> called <hi>Huniades</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1452. </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Ladiſlaus</hi> V.</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1458. </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Matthias Corvin</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1490. </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Ladiſlaus</hi> VI.</cell>
                        <cell>25</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1516. </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Loüis</hi> II. called the Young</cell>
                        <cell>11</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1526. </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>John de Zapol</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1540. </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>John Stephen,</hi> or <hi>Sigiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1527. </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Ferdinand</hi> I.</cell>
                        <cell>37</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1564. </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Maximilian</hi> I.</cell>
                        <cell>12</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1576. </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Rodolph</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>36</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1612. </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Matthias.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1619. </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Ferdinand</hi> II.</cell>
                        <cell>18</cell>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1637. </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Ferdinand</hi> III. called Earneſt.</cell>
                        <cell>20</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ferdinand Francis</hi> Elected, 1647.</p>
               <p>1657. <hi>Leopold Ignatius</hi> choſen in the Life of his Father <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the III. in the year, 1655.</p>
               <p>The Author has not here obſerved the preciſe year of the Election of theſe Princes, but the year their Reign began.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:34980:8"/>
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p> Of the Authors that ſpeak of <hi>Hungary.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE chief are: <hi>Bonfinius, Eneas Sylvius, Bizar, Philippus Calli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>machus, Experieus, Cellarius, Dillichi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, Poretius, Eſtuanfus, Sambuch, Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del, Peter Ranzan, Melchior Soiter, Cia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conius, Stuarth, Roger,</hi> who hath Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed a Volume of <hi>Hungarian</hi> Writers, <hi>Tharoſius,</hi> the Authors of the Hiſtorys of <hi>Germany, Poland</hi> and <hi>Naples, Thevet</hi> and <hi>Paulus Jovius</hi> on <hi>Matthias, Corvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> and <hi>Huniades,</hi> St. <hi>Antonin, Blondus, Daviti,</hi> the Fables of the Kings of <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary, Mercator, Ortelius, Maginus Cluve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius, Brietius, Samſon, Du Val, Boiſſard, Volateran, Du May</hi>'s Deſcription of the War of <hi>Hungary, Szenkely, Chron: Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarii,</hi> St. <hi>Baudrand Lexic. Geog.</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:34980:9"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p> Of the Towns of <hi>Upper Hungary</hi> and their Deſcription.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE Kingdom of <hi>Hungary,</hi> as we have ſaid, is divided into the <hi>Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per</hi> and <hi>Lower Hungary,</hi> the Towns of the <hi>Upper Hungary,</hi> are theſe that follow.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>PRESBOURG.</head>
                  <p>This Town lies upon the <hi>Danube,</hi> and is the Capital City of the <hi>Upper Hungary,</hi> and of all that belongs to the Emperor within that Kingdom. It gives it's Name to a County, which is a Province of <hi>Hungary,</hi> betwixt <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ravia, Auſtria,</hi> and the <hi>Danube;</hi> the Latin Authors call it <hi>Poſonium</hi> and <hi>Flex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi> and thoſe of the Country, <hi>Poſon.</hi> This place is eight Leagues from <hi>Vien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> in <hi>Auſtria,</hi> and as far from <hi>Newheu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel</hi> and <hi>Comorra;</hi> it is Fortified with a conſiderable Caſtle againſt the Incur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:34980:9"/> of the <hi>Turks,</hi> which is mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Author of the <hi>German</hi> Itine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rary in this manner. <hi>Lib.</hi> 5.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Hic ubi Poſonium conſurgit turribus altis,</l>
                     <l>Limes Teutonicis, Hungariiſque viris.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>The Authors of the <hi>Hungarian</hi> Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, which are bound up in one Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume, ſpeak of <hi>Preſbourg,</hi> as well as <hi>Cluverius, Ortelius</hi> and <hi>Samſon;</hi> it hath the Title of an Arch-Biſhoprick, and in the Cathedral-Church, which is partly poſſeſſed by the Fathers Jeſuits, the Body of St. <hi>John</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andra</hi> is held in great Veneration.</p>
                  <p>Pope <hi>Clement</hi> the Fifth being inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that the <hi>Hungarians</hi> were in Arms, and would not ſubmit to <hi>Charles Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel,</hi> Son to <hi>Charles</hi> II. King of <hi>Naples,</hi> thought himſelf obliged to ſend a Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat thither, either for compoſing theſe Diſorders, or ſtrengthening the Party of the Lawful Soveraign. For that effect he pitched upon <hi>Gentil de Monteffiore,</hi> whoſe Merit had raiſed him from a Franciſcan Frier to the Dignity of a Cardinal, and who ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitted
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:34980:10"/> himſelf extraordinarily well in his Commiſſion. At firſt he uſed all ways of Mildneſs; but finding them to be unprofitable, he employed Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Cenſures, and reclaimed the <hi>Hungarians</hi> to their Duty. He ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated a Council at <hi>Preſbourg,</hi> in the year 1309. Where ſound Cannons were made; which were afterwards approved by the Pope. In this Town there are a great many Houſes built after the <hi>Italian</hi> manner, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute much to the Beauty thereof.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>NITRIA.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Nitria</hi> or <hi>Nitracht,</hi> a Town in the <hi>Upper Hungary,</hi> is the Seat of a Biſhop, Suffragan to the Arch-biſhop of <hi>Gran,</hi> and has it's Name from the River it lyes upon, which it gives to a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, whereof it is the Capital: It is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Juriſdiction of <hi>Newheuſel,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing five Leagues diſtant from it, and ten from <hi>Preſbourg,</hi> and continued al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ſubject to the Emperour.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:34980:10"/>
                  <head>NEWHEUSEL.</head>
                  <p>The people of the Country call it <hi>Owar,</hi> and the Latin Authors <hi>Neoſeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um;</hi> it lyes upon the River of <hi>Nitria,</hi> or <hi>Nitrach,</hi> two Leagues from <hi>Comor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra</hi> upon the <hi>Danube:</hi> It is but a ſmall Town, but very well ſeated, and the chief Town of a large Country; the <hi>Turks</hi> took it in the year 1663. And the Emperours Army having inveſted it the ſeventh of <hi>July,</hi> 1685. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took it the nineteenth of <hi>Auguſt</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>NOVIGRAD.</head>
                  <p>A little Town with a Caſtle upon a Hill, the Capital of the County of the ſame name, lying on the <hi>Danube,</hi> betwixt <hi>Gran</hi> and <hi>Vachia.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>VACHIA.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Vatzen</hi> or <hi>Veitzen,</hi> and in Latin <hi>Vac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia,</hi> is a Town lying upon the <hi>Danube,</hi> betwixt <hi>Novigrad</hi> and <hi>Peſt,</hi> and the Seat of a Biſhop, Suffragan to <hi>Gran.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:34980:11"/>
                  <head>CASSOVIA.</head>
                  <p>This Town by the <hi>Hungarians</hi> is called <hi>Caſchow,</hi> the Capital of the County of <hi>Abauwiver.</hi> It is very well fortified, and lyes upon the River of <hi>Kunnert,</hi> which falls into the <hi>Teiſs</hi> five or ſix Leagues from the Carpatian or Crapat Mountains, betwixt <hi>Eſperies</hi> and <hi>Borſanick.</hi> And though it be a free Town, and have conſiderable Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges, yet it hath always acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged the Emperor as King of <hi>Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> till of late, being engaged in the Rebellion of <hi>Teckely,</hi> it was forced to return to the Emperor it's Lawful So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign in the year, 1685.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>FILLECK.</head>
                  <p>Was formerly a ſtrong Town of the Imperial <hi>Hungary,</hi> lying five Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues to the North of <hi>Agria,</hi> and as far to the Weſt of <hi>Caſſovia,</hi> upon the River <hi>Gayenne,</hi> in the County of <hi>Zabel;</hi> it was reduced under the power of <hi>Teckely,</hi> and it's Fortifications demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:34980:11"/>
                  <head>ESPERIES.</head>
                  <p>In Latin <hi>Eperiae</hi> is a very well forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied Town in the County of <hi>Sarax</hi> in <hi>Hungary,</hi> lying upon the River of <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bez,</hi> towards the Mountains and upon the Frontiers of <hi>Poland:</hi> It always be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed to the Emperor as King of <hi>Hungary,</hi> till it was involved in the Rebellion of <hi>Teckely,</hi> from whom it was retaken by the Imperial Arms in the year, 1685.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>AGRIA.</head>
                  <p>This Town by the <hi>Germans</hi> is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>Eger,</hi> and by the <hi>Hungarians, Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>law,</hi> lying upon a River of the ſame Name: It is but a ſmall place, hut ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarily well fortified, and hath always been the Seat of a Biſhop, Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fragan to the Arch-biſhop of <hi>Strigoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi> and the Bulwark of Chriſtendom, and therefore it was Beſieged, but in vain, by the Army of <hi>Solyman:</hi> But at length, <hi>Mahomet</hi> the Third carried it the 12. of <hi>October,</hi> 1596. Since that time it hath been in the hands of the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:34980:12"/> 
                     <hi>Turks,</hi> who keep a ſtrong Gariſon in it. Three Leagues from this Town the River of <hi>Agria</hi> falls into the <hi>Tyſſa</hi> or <hi>Teiſſe,</hi> which is the <hi>Tibiſcus</hi> of the Latins. In the year 1552. the <hi>Turks</hi> firſt beſieged <hi>Agria,</hi> with an Army of Threeſcore and ten thouſand Men. It was then no ſtrong place, neither by Nature nor Art; and yet the Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage of the Gariſon ſupplied the Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the place. There were within it Two thouſand <hi>Hungarians,</hi> and Three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore of the chief Gentlemen of the Country, who brought thither their Wives, Children, and all their Goods. They all took an Oath, that they would ſuffer the utmoſt Extremity, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than render the place; they put all their Proviſion into publick ſtores, and when the <hi>Turks</hi> ſummoned them to render the place, they put out a Cof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin upon the Battlements of the Walls, to ſhew that they had reſolved to die, rather than to yield. The Town was for Forty days time inceſſantly Batter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Fifty pieces of Cannon; but all that daunted not the Beſieged. Nay the <hi>Turks</hi> having made three Aſſaults in one day, were ſtill beaten off, and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:34980:12"/> loſt Eight thouſand men. Above all things the Valour of the Women was conſpicious in ſo bloody an Action. One of them was fighting in preſence of her Mother and Husband, who was killed hard by her, and her Mother bidding her carry off the Body and Bury it: God forbid, anſwered ſhe, that I ſhould Bury my Husband be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I revenge his death: and with that ſnatching up the Buckler and Sword of her dead Husband, ſhe threw her ſelf into the midſt of the Enemy's, and left not off Fighting till ſhe had revenged the death of her Husband by the ſlaughter of three <hi>Turks.</hi> Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Woman carrying a great ſtone to caſt down upon the Enemy, was ſhot with a Canon Bullet, that carried off her head. Her Daughter who fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed her, without ſtanding to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wail her loſs, took up the ſtone, and all bloody as it was with her Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Blood, threw it down upon a croud of the Enemy, who endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to mount the Wall. The <hi>Turks</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Witneſſes of ſuch obſtinate Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, raiſed the Siege the Nineteenth of <hi>October;</hi> and the Beſieged ſallying
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:34980:13"/> out after them, cut to pieces a great number of the Infidels, and took moſt of their Baggage.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>TOKAY.</head>
                  <p>A very ſtrong Town with a Cita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del upon the River <hi>Bodroch,</hi> that falls in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Teiſſe.</hi> This Town lying in form of an Iſland, was taken by the <hi>Turks,</hi> and afterwards regained by the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors Army; but falling into the hands of the Rebel <hi>Teckely,</hi> his Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Majeſty retook it in the year, 1685. to whom it belongs at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. This Town is Subject to Inun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations, and yet the Land about it is very Fertile, and bears excellent Wine called by that name. Below it the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of <hi>Bodroch,</hi> running by <hi>Eſperies,</hi> joyns the <hi>Teiſſe.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>UNGWAR.</head>
                  <p>A little Town, Capital of the County of <hi>Ung,</hi> lying at the Foot of the <hi>Carpat</hi> Mountain, near the River <hi>Ung,</hi> the Boundary of <hi>Red Ruſſia,</hi> thirty Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues to the Eaſt of <hi>Caſſovia,</hi> and five
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:34980:13"/> and twenty to the North of the <hi>Teiſſe;</hi> it fell likewiſe into the hands of <hi>Teckely,</hi> and was retaken by the Arms of the Emperor in the year, 1685.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>COLOCZA.</head>
                  <p>An Ancient Town lying near the <hi>Danube</hi> lower than <hi>Peſt,</hi> was here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore an Arch-biſhops See; it is encompaſſed with very Fertil Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>ONOTH.</head>
                  <p>A Town lying upon the ſide of the River of <hi>Schaia,</hi> between <hi>Agria</hi> and <hi>Tokay.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>DEBRECHIM.</head>
                  <p>A City lying in the County of <hi>Zo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel,</hi> betwixt <hi>Tokay</hi> and great <hi>Waradin;</hi> it is Rich, Populous, and of great Commerce and Traffick; upon the humble deſire of the Inhabitants, it was received into the Protection of his Imperial Majeſty, after the Reduction of <hi>Zolnock,</hi> and <hi>Caſſovia:</hi> It continued
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:34980:14"/> Neuter during the late Revolutions in <hi>Hungary,</hi> and ſided not with the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, allowing always Liberty, as well to the Judges there eſtabliſhed by the Emperour, as to the Commiſſioner of the Port, to Exerciſe their Authority in it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>GIULA.</head>
                  <p>This Town lies betwixt the Rivers of <hi>Sebeskeres</hi> and <hi>Feyerkeres,</hi> upon the Lake of <hi>Zarkad,</hi> a few Leagues be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low great <hi>Waradin,</hi> upon the Frontier of <hi>Tranſilvania;</hi> as yet it belongs to the <hi>Turk.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>ZOLNOCK.</head>
                  <p>This Town lyes upon the River of <hi>Teiſſe,</hi> where the River of <hi>Zagiwa</hi> joins it: It is the chief Town of the ſame name, and ſtrongly fortified, having long groaned under the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Yoke; it lyes fourty Leagues to the Weſt of <hi>Waradin,</hi> and ſixty from <hi>Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da.</hi> This Fortreſs was taken by the <hi>Baron de Mercy,</hi> Lieutenant-Marſhal <hi>de</hi> Camp, and by the Sr. <hi>Heuſler</hi> one of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:34980:14"/> the Emperor's Generals, in the Month of <hi>October,</hi> 1685.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>ZATMAR.</head>
                  <p>A ſmall Town lying upon the River of <hi>Samos,</hi> on the Frontiers of <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilvania,</hi> and the Capital of the County of the ſame Name; it belongs to the Emperour, and is ten Leagues North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of <hi>Waradin,</hi> and fourteen Eaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of <hi>Tokay.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>ZARAVAS.</head>
                  <p>This is a Modern Fortreſs built by the <hi>Turks,</hi> ſince the breaking out of the Rebellion, which <hi>Emerſi</hi> Count of <hi>Teckely</hi> raiſed in this Kingdom: It lyes upon the River of <hi>Kiros,</hi> which falls into the <hi>Teyſſe,</hi> five <hi>German</hi> Leagues from <hi>Zolnock,</hi> and twelve from <hi>Giula;</hi> but the ſituation of it is not as yet de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed in the Maps: By the Conqueſt of this place, two Counties that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend on it have been gained, which before the Rebellion held not of his Imperial Majeſty; the one is called the County of the <hi>Tarantali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi>
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:34980:15"/> and the other of the <hi>Czongradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>MONGATZ.</head>
                  <p>A Fort with a very ſtrong Caſtle ſeated on the River <hi>Torza,</hi> betwixt <hi>Ungwar</hi> and <hi>Zatmar</hi> near the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains; it hath been a place of Retreat to the Rebel Count <hi>Teckely,</hi> as it was before to Prince <hi>Ragotzi.</hi> The Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs of <hi>Teckely, Aurora Veronica</hi> Daugh-to the late Count <hi>Peter Serine,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Widdow of the ſaid Prince, ſtill delays to render it to the Emperor, as being uncertain what will become of her Husband. In the mean time it is ſtraitly blocked up by the Imperial Forces.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>TEMESWAR.</head>
                  <p>A great and ſtrong Town upon the River of <hi>Temes,</hi> towards the Fron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers of <hi>Tranſilvania;</hi> it is the chief Town of a P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ovince of that Name, which has the Title of a County. The <hi>Turk</hi> hath ſubdued both the Town and Country.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:34980:15"/>
                  <head>WARADIN.</head>
                  <p>This Town which is called <hi>Great Waradin,</hi> lying on the <hi>Drave,</hi> was of the Ancient <hi>Dacia,</hi> and is at preſent in <hi>Tranſilvania.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is ſituated to the South of the lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle River of <hi>Keuvres,</hi> which others call <hi>Sobeskeres,</hi> and the Ancients <hi>Chriſus,</hi> that has its Source in one of the Branches of the <hi>Carpathian</hi> Mountains, from whence it ſeems to waſh away, and bring along with its Sand little Spangles of Gold.</p>
                  <p>In the year 1242. the <hi>Tartars</hi> made themſelves Maſters of that Town, and uſed great Cruelties i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t, putting moſt of the Inhabitants to the Sword, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſtinction of Age or Sex.</p>
                  <p>In the year 1290. <hi>Ladiſlaus</hi> King of <hi>Hungary,</hi> built in it the fair Church of our Lady, which is the Seat of a Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fragan Biſhop.</p>
                  <p>This Town having a ſtrong Cita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del, is fortified with five Baſtions; and the <hi>Turks</hi> looking upon it as a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable Poſt, for enlarging their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts on the ſide of <hi>Tranſilvania,</hi> ſent
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:34980:16"/> firſt in the year, 1598. a powerful Army under the command of <hi>Omar,</hi> who beſieged it in the month of <hi>Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember;</hi> but after may Cruel and Bloody Attacks on both ſides, the <hi>Turks</hi> were forced to raiſe the Siege on the third of <hi>November:</hi> How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever in 1660. they took it, and made it a place of Arms againſt Chriſtendom.</p>
                  <p>This place is the uſual Reſidence of a <hi>Sangiack,</hi> who depends on the <hi>Beglerbey</hi> of <hi>Themeſwar:</hi> And here it was, that Count <hi>Emery of Teckely,</hi> was ſurpriſed and ſeized by the Baſſa of the place, and ſent to the Grand Viſier at <hi>Adria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople</hi> in Chains. This was a great Transformation of him, who put in his Standard that was taken in the month of <hi>September,</hi> 1684. by General <hi>Schultz</hi> at the Battle near <hi>Eſperies;</hi> his own Arms beſet with two Lions <hi>Or,</hi> and two <hi>Argent</hi> holding in their claws a Shable, cleaving the Imperial Eagle in two, and over-head a Ducal Coronet, with a device in Latin and Sclavonick, of, Protector in <hi>Hungary:</hi> But alas!</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Quem veniens ſuperbum</l>
                     <l>dies vidit</l>
                     <l>Hunc fugiens jacentem</l>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:34980:16"/>
                  <head>GUTTA.</head>
                  <p>This Town is very well Fortified at that place, where the River of <hi>Waag</hi> diſcharges it ſelf into the <hi>Danube;</hi> it was Built ſince the laſt Wars, in a Fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny place betwixt a branch of the <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nube,</hi> the <hi>Waag</hi> and the <hi>Swatrz.</hi> It is a Mile diſtant from <hi>Newheuſel,</hi> and from the top of the Church of <hi>Gutta,</hi> one may ſee the Town of <hi>Newheu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel,</hi> and even diſtinguiſh the ſeveral Houſes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>SCHINTA.</head>
                  <p>Eſteemed a very ſtrong place, long ſince Built to command the River, and all the Country about; it hath a Tower in the middle, with four Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, and ſeveral great Guns.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>TIRNAW.</head>
                  <p>Is a Town lying in an open Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, and may be ſeen at a great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance; within theſe ſeven years it was reduced to Aſhes, and is now almoſt intirely Re-built.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:34980:17"/>
                  <head>TOPOLCHAN.</head>
                  <p>This Town lyes upon the Banks of the River of <hi>Nitra,</hi> and was burnt down with its Church during the late Wars, and could never be Built again ſince.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>LEOPOLD.</head>
                  <p>This Town was Built after the loſs of <hi>Newheuſel,</hi> and much in the ſame Figure; it hath ſix very Regular Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, and well covered, lying Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of the River of <hi>Waag,</hi> and exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly oppoſite to <hi>Freiſtadt:</hi> It is not ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry far from the place, through which the <hi>Tartars</hi> went in the late War, when they ravaged a great part of that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and made many Slaves, as they did alſo in <hi>Moravia.</hi> It was begun to be fortified in the year, 1665.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>FREISTADT.</head>
                  <p>Is a very pretty Town, but the <hi>Turks</hi> not long ſince burnt it: The Count of <hi>Forchatz,</hi> has a lovely Caſtle and a
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:34980:17"/> ſtately Houſe in it, and the <hi>Capucins</hi> a Convent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>TRENSCHEIN.</head>
                  <p>Is a very fair Town lying upon the ſide of the River of <hi>Waag,</hi> over which it hath a Wooden Bridge: The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket place of it is very pretty, the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits Church lovely, and the Caſtle very high; it is ſeen at a great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and belongs to Count <hi>Illeſhazi.</hi> There are a great many Springs of Mineral Waters, in all the Country a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>SERNOWITZ.</head>
                  <p>Is a Town lying upon the River of <hi>Gran,</hi> having a Caſtle built upon a Rock.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>NEWSOL.</head>
                  <p>Is a pretty neat Town, lying upon the River of <hi>Gran;</hi> at the end of it there is a very lovely Tower, and the Caſtle well deſerves to be ſeen; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is a Church within it co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:34980:18"/> with Copper, wherein are a great many fair Wooden Statues, and ſome Relicks. It hath a Bridge over the River, with a handſome pile of Building, made to ſtop the Timber that is thrown into the River, ten Miles above the Town in the Country, that is all covered with Wood. By that means Wood is conveyed to <hi>Newſol</hi> without much trouble and cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ges, which is made uſe of for Working in the Copper Mines that are in the Town: It was taken by <hi>Bethlem Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor</hi> Prince of <hi>Tranſilvania,</hi> who making uſe of the Occaſion of the Revolt of the <hi>Bohemians,</hi> and of his Alliance which they demanded, fell into <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary</hi> and took many places in it. Before this Town of <hi>Newſol,</hi> the brave Count <hi>Charles of Bucquoy,</hi> Knight of the Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Fleece, being General of the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial Army, found his Bed of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor; for having retaken the Towns of <hi>Preſbourg, Tirnaw, Altenbourg,</hi> and others, and encamping before <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſol,</hi> where he Valliantly carried on the Siege in the year, 1621. he was kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in a Sally in the Month of <hi>July</hi> that year, after he had received Six<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:34980:18"/> Mortal Wounds. The following Inſcription was made to his Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory.</p>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div type="epitaph">
                              <lg>
                                 <l>Belli fulmen,</l>
                                 <l>Hoſtium terror,</l>
                                 <l>Suorum militum Pater,</l>
                                 <l>Regum Praeſidium, Equitum Aurei Velleris decus.</l>
                              </lg>
                              <lg>
                                 <l>CAROLUS BUCQUOIUS.</l>
                              </lg>
                              <lg>
                                 <l>Quem ad Ambianum Henricus <hi>IV.</hi>
                                 </l>
                                 <l>Galliae Rex</l>
                                 <l>Timendo laudaverat.</l>
                                 <l>Novis hic laudibus atque victoriis ſe probavit,</l>
                                 <l>Supremus Tormentorum conſtitutus Praefectus,</l>
                                 <l>Ipſo ſole illuſtrior famâ</l>
                                 <l>Gaborem Imperii jugulo imminentem</l>
                                 <l>Viennâ repulit, Auſtriâque totâ exegit:</l>
                                 <l>Turrianum, Anhaltinum &amp; Mans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feldium,</l>
                                 <l>Perduellium Duces, contudit.</l>
                                 <l>Dejecit affectato Regno Palatinum.</l>
                                 <l>Pragam recepit,</l>
                                 <pb n="32" facs="tcp:34980:19"/>
                                 <l>Subegit Bohemiam,</l>
                                 <l>Moraviam pacavit:</l>
                                 <l>In Hungaria Poſonium, Tirnaviam,</l>
                                 <l>aliaque oppida,</l>
                                 <l>Regi ſuo aſſeruit:</l>
                                 <l>Denique dum ad Neoſolium</l>
                                 <l>Infeſtam obſeſſorum eruptionem fortiter</l>
                                 <l>ſuſtinens</l>
                                 <l>Equo, quem in hoſtem admiſerat longius,</l>
                                 <l>trucidato,</l>
                                 <l>Ipſe, ſedecim vulneribus ſaucius,</l>
                                 <l>Lanceâque ad extremum confoſſus</l>
                                 <l>Non finem vitae ſuae,</l>
                                 <l>Sed melius &amp; auctius quam apud</l>
                                 <l>Mantinaeam,</l>
                                 <l>Epaminondas,</l>
                                 <l>Initium reperit.</l>
                              </lg>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>ALTSOL.</head>
                  <p>Is a Town lying upon the ſame River of <hi>Gran,</hi> lower than <hi>Newſol,</hi> betwixt it and the Town of <hi>Crem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitz.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>HERN-GRUNDT.</head>
                  <p>Is a little Town ſtanding on a pretty high Ground, though it be betwixt two
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:34980:19"/> Hills. The place it ſtands on goes by the ſame Name, and is but a mile from <hi>Newſol.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>SCHEMNITZ.</head>
                  <p>The biggeſt of all the Towns in <hi>Hungary,</hi> where there are Mines, and in it there is a great deal of Silver found daily. The Town is very well built, hath three fair Churches, and moſt part of the Inhabitants are <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therans.</hi> It hath alſo three Caſtles; the firſt is the old Caſtle, that ſtands in the Town; where one may hear pretty pleaſant Muſick, at ſix of the Clock in the morning, and ſix at night, which is performed by means of an Engine that they have found out. The ſecond is the new Caſtle, built by a Lady, who cauſed the Gibbet that ſtood upon a Hill to be removed, and a ſtately Fabrick to be erected in place of it. The third is upon the top of a very high Hill, where there is always a Sentinel to diſcover the approach of the <hi>Turks,</hi> and to give notice of it by firing a great Gun. The Streets lye upwards and downwards upon the ſide
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:34980:20"/> of the Hill, and all the Country is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry uneven.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>CREMNITZ.</head>
                  <p>This is but a very little Town, but hath large Suburbs, and ſtands on ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry high Ground. It is thought that St. <hi>John</hi>'s Church, which is pretty near it, is built on the higheſt Ground of all <hi>Hungary:</hi> It is the ancienteſt of all the Towns where Mines are, and is alſo the richeſt of all the ſeven, which are called <hi>Schemnitz, Cremnitz, New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſol, Koninsbergs, Bochantz, Libeten,</hi> and <hi>Tiln.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>VIROVICHITZ.</head>
                  <p>Lying before the Iſle of St. <hi>Andrew,</hi> is a place in high Eſteem, for the love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Vines and good Grapes that grow there. Near it there is a demoliſhed Stone Building, upon the ſide of the Iſle of St. <hi>Andrew,</hi> where it is ſaid, that heretofore there was a Stone Bridge.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:34980:20"/>
                  <head>MAROS.</head>
                  <p>Is on the other ſide of <hi>Vicegrad,</hi> near the Iſle of St. <hi>Andrew.</hi> It hath a very lovely Church, and being a place that heretofore yielded voluntarily to the <hi>Turks,</hi> the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> are not much tormented there; but only pay a yearly Tribute of very ſmall Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>PEST.</head>
                  <p>On the other ſide of the <hi>Danube</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Eaſt, is the Town of <hi>Peſt,</hi> that is ſquare and ſeated in a very lovely Plain: it looks very pretty from <hi>Buda,</hi> becauſe of its Walls and the Towers of its <hi>Moſques.</hi> It gives the Name to all the Countrey about, which therefore is called, <hi>Comitatus Peſthienſis,</hi> the County of <hi>Peſt;</hi> for <hi>Hungary</hi> is divided into Counties as well as <hi>England.</hi> Betwixt this place and <hi>Buda</hi> there is a fair Bridge of <hi>Boats,</hi> at leaſt half a mile over; it hath been taken and re-taken, whereby it is much ruined, and the Town of <hi>Buda</hi> which
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:34980:21"/> is over againſt it ſtanding on an Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence, whereas this lies in a Plain, ſo commands it, that it can batter it down with great Guns; unleſs on the ſide of the Gate of <hi>Agria,</hi> which is covered by the Town. The <hi>Imperial</hi> Forces took it in the year 1684. when they inveſted <hi>Buda;</hi> but quitting that Siege they alſo abandoned <hi>Peſt;</hi> though now in this preſent year 1686. they have again made themſelves Maſters of it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>HADWAN.</head>
                  <p>Lies upon the <hi>Zagywe</hi> to the North of <hi>Peſt,</hi> and fortifyed with Earth, but not ſo as that the <hi>Turks</hi> repoſe great aſſurance on it: It was taken by the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> in the year 1596. but after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards abandoned to the <hi>Turks</hi> in the year 1603. and is not above ſix Leagues from <hi>Peſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To cloſe up the Deſcription of the Towns of Upper <hi>Hungary,</hi> I ſhall ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>join the <hi>Latin Epigram,</hi> made upon the Revolt of the Towns that eſpouſed the Party of <hi>Teckely.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:34980:21"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>EPIGRAMMA.</hi> In ſeptem Superioris Hungariae For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talitia Duce Teckelio Caeſari Rebellantia.</head>
                  <l>CAſtrorum ſeptem crudelis &amp; impia tellus</l>
                  <l>Quid Dominum contra perfida colla levas?</l>
                  <l>Oblita es famulam, ſaltem te agnoſce pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentem:</l>
                  <l>Hic tibi, ni Princeps eſſet, alumnus erat.</l>
                  <l>Divitiiſnè tumes? cecidit Campania dives.</l>
                  <l>An populo? Marathon millia quanta premit.</l>
                  <l>Sed tibi fortè animos perjurus proditor auget,</l>
                  <l>Aſpice quàm ſtultum ſtulta ſequare Ducem.</l>
                  <l>Sit licet ille ferox, &amp; ſit bellare peritus,</l>
                  <l>Sit licet ille potens, improba cauſa ſua eſt.</l>
                  <l>Vincitur ut cauſâ, pariter vincetur &amp; Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis,</l>
                  <l>Bella placent juſto non niſi juſta Deo.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:34980:22"/>
               <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p> Of the Towns of Lower <hi>Hungary.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>BUDA.</head>
                  <p>BEfore the <hi>Turks</hi> invaded <hi>Hungary,</hi> the City of <hi>Buda</hi> was the <hi>Metro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polis</hi> of the Kingdom; the Ancients called it <hi>Curta,</hi> and the <hi>Germans Offen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is divided into the Upper and Lower Town, lying upon the ſide of a Hill, the Foot whereof is waſhed by the <hi>Danube,</hi> which at that place is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove half a mile over: It hath a Bridge of Boats over it, that joins the City of <hi>Buda,</hi> to the little Town of <hi>Peſt,</hi> ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the oppoſite ſide. In <hi>Buda</hi> are to be ſeen the Ruines of ſeveral ſtately Palaces, built heretofore by <hi>Matthias Corvinus</hi> King of <hi>Hungary,</hi> and his Predeceſſours; which the <hi>Turks</hi> neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, and let fall into decay.</p>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:34980:22"/>
                  <p>This is a large, fair, and well built Town, but ill peopled, and hath hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly any Inhabitants, but the <hi>Spahies</hi> and <hi>Janiſaries</hi> of the Garriſon, which is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways very numerous.</p>
                  <p>After the Death of <hi>John Zapol,</hi> Count of <hi>Scepus</hi> and <hi>Elba</hi> King of <hi>Hungary,</hi> his Widow <hi>Eliſabeth</hi> of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and his Son <hi>Stephen,</hi> called in the <hi>Turks</hi> to their Aſſiſtance, againſt <hi>Ferdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nand</hi> of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> who was elected King. The <hi>Germans</hi> beſieged <hi>Buda,</hi> and the <hi>Turks</hi> having defeated them, made themſelves Maſters of the Town under pretext of Friendſhip, ſending the Queen, her Son, and <hi>George Martiniſius,</hi> who had been chief Miniſter to the late King, into <hi>Tranſilvania.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This Town is the Reſidence of a <hi>Beglerbey,</hi> whoſe Authority extends o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver twenty <hi>Sangiacks.</hi> The <hi>Baſſa</hi> of <hi>Buda</hi> hath more Authority than the others have, and the Garriſon conſiſts commonly of eight or ten Thouſand Men. Some take it to be the <hi>Curta</hi> of <hi>Ptolomy,</hi> and others for the <hi>Aguincum</hi> of the Itinerary of <hi>Antonine.</hi> It is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry hard to be poſitive as to that, and all that can be ſaid are but Conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures.
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:34980:23"/> But it is a Fable, that the Brother of <hi>Attila</hi> built it, and called it by his Name <hi>Budaeus:</hi> For that Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>Attila</hi> was named <hi>Bleda,</hi> and not <hi>Budaeus,</hi> as the Fabulous pretend.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Solyman</hi> rendered himſelf Maſter of <hi>Buda</hi> the 20eth. of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1526. and in the year 1527. <hi>Ferdinand</hi> I. King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> Brother to the Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> V. after the overthrow of <hi>Loüis</hi> the Young, in the Plain of <hi>Mohacz,</hi> was proclaimed King of <hi>Hungary,</hi> by <hi>Stephen Bathori</hi> Palatin of the Kingdom, and by the ſounder part of the Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity; <hi>John Zapoliha,</hi> Vaivod of <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilvania,</hi> having been before tumultua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily elected by the reſt.</p>
                  <p>The ſame year, <hi>Ferdinand</hi> made himſelt Maſter of the greateſt part of the Kingdom, and of <hi>Buda</hi> the Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal City, of which he made <hi>Thomas Nadaſti</hi> Governour; until the year 1529. that <hi>Solyman</hi> took it by the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery of the Garriſon, and ſhortly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter laid ſiege to <hi>Vienna,</hi> which he was forced ſhamefully to raiſe, after he had made many B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oody Aſſaults.</p>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:34980:23"/>
                  <p>From whence, retreating to <hi>Buda,</hi> he re-eſtabliſhed <hi>John</hi> Vaivod of <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilvania</hi> in the Kingdom; having left in <hi>Buda, Gritti,</hi> a Renegado, with three Thouſand <hi>Janiſaries,</hi> to defend it in Name of the Vaivod.</p>
                  <p>Afterwards <hi>Ferdinand</hi> King of <hi>Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia,</hi> made General <hi>Rogendorf</hi> beſiege it, in the year 1530. but in vain.</p>
                  <p>In the year 1540. he commanded his General <hi>Leonard Feſſius</hi> to Beſiege it a ſecond time, having firſt poſſeſt himſelf of the Forts of <hi>Vicegrad, Vac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia,</hi> and <hi>Peſt;</hi> and <hi>John Zapoliha</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dead the year before, who left for his Succeſſor <hi>John Sigiſmond,</hi> a Pupil under the tuition of the Princeſs <hi>Iſabel</hi> his Mother, and <hi>George Monck;</hi> but <hi>Feſſius</hi> having there endured the fati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues of a long and troubleſom Siege, was again obliged to draw off.</p>
                  <p>In the year, 1541. General <hi>Rogen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorf</hi> renewed the Siege again a Third time; but upon the coming of <hi>Soly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> he thought it beſt to retreat. In the mean time that <hi>Ottoman</hi> Prince ſurpriſed the Town by Cunning, drove the young Prince and his Mother out of it, and ſent them to Reign in <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilvania,</hi>
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:34980:24"/> publiſhing that he would keep it until <hi>John Sigiſmond,</hi> the Son of <hi>John Zapoliha</hi> the Uſurper, were of Age.</p>
                  <p>In the year, 1542. the Marqueſs of <hi>Brandebourgh,</hi> made as if he intended to Beſiege <hi>Buda,</hi> and in that deſign marched towards it. He attacked <hi>Peſt,</hi> on his march, but in vain, and retreated without any ſucceſs.</p>
                  <p>The Count of <hi>Swartzenbourgh</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Month of <hi>March</hi> 1598. by a Wonderful Stratagem retaken <hi>Java<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rin,</hi> or <hi>Raab,</hi> from the <hi>Turks,</hi> marched the ſame year in the Month of <hi>Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> under the Auſpices of the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duke <hi>Matthias,</hi> and laid Siege to <hi>Buda,</hi> which after thirty days Attack he was forced to raiſe, becauſe of the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual Rains: And it is remarkable, that the <hi>Turks,</hi> who at the ſame time Beſieged the Town of <hi>Waradin</hi> in <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilvania,</hi> were likewiſe obliged to quit their Enterpriſe for the ſame Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
                  <p>The Chriſtians again attacked that Town in the year 1602 under General <hi>Roſwurm,</hi> but having ruined the Bridge ever the <hi>Danube,</hi> and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:34980:24"/> the Town of <hi>Peſt,</hi> the Rigour of the Seaſon obliged them to deſiſt from their Deſign.</p>
                  <p>The Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> Generaliſſimo of the Imperial Armies, attempted the Siege of the ſame place, having firſt made himſelf Maſter of the Caſtle of <hi>Vicegrad, Vaccia</hi> and <hi>Peſt,</hi> and thrice defeated the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Army; but the Seaſon being too far advanced, that he might not endanger the Army, he thought it convenient to raiſe the Siege in the Month of <hi>October,</hi> 1684.</p>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>The Council of <hi>Buda.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Philip</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Fermo,</hi> of the holy See, being ſent by <hi>Nicholas</hi> III. for treating ſome important Affairs with <hi>Ladiſlaus</hi> III. King of <hi>Hungary,</hi> in the year 1279. celebrated a Council at <hi>Buda;</hi> the Conſtitutions whereof to the Number of Thirty ſix, <hi>Oldericus Rainaldus</hi> hath put at the end of the 14. Tome of the Eccleſiaſtical An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals.</p>
                     <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                        <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="46" facs="tcp:34980:25"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Churches</hi> or <hi>Funf-Kerken,</hi> and ſome other places, burnt <hi>Siget,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged <hi>Caniſa,</hi> which he would have infallibly taken, had the Succours that were promiſed him been ſent to him. The Grand <hi>Viſier</hi> having Intelligence of that ſiege, advanced with a great Army, made him raiſe it, and then took <hi>Fort Serini,</hi> which was afterwards demoliſhed, little <hi>Gomora,</hi> and other Places.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>VICEGRAD.</head>
                  <p>The <hi>Latins</hi> call it, <hi>Viſſegradia,</hi> and the <hi>Germans, Plindenburg.</hi> It is a ſtrong Town, built upon a very high Rock, the <hi>Danube</hi> running by the Foot of it, and lies above <hi>Buda,</hi> and below <hi>Stri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonium.</hi> In this place there is a Caſtle, upon a little Hill, where the <hi>Abbey</hi> of <hi>Pily</hi> ſtands alſo. Heretofore the Crown of <hi>Hungary</hi> was kept there, that Town in former times having been the place of Reſidence of the Kings of <hi>Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry;</hi> and the Remains of the Ruines of a very ſtately Building of Free Stone, are ſtill to be ſeen there. The Forces of the Arch-Duke <hi>Matthias,</hi> re-took
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:34980:25"/> that place in the Reign of <hi>Mahomet</hi> III. But the <hi>Heydukes</hi> committed a piece of the greateſt Treachery ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable, and delivered it up into the hands of the <hi>Turks,</hi> in the time of <hi>Sultan Achmet. Charles</hi> King of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,</hi> who was alſo proclaimed King of <hi>Hungary,</hi> having been wounded in the Head by <hi>Forchatz,</hi> was carried into that Caſtle, where under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text of applying a Plaiſter to his Head, they ſtrangled him. The Crown of <hi>Hungary</hi> was heretofore kept at <hi>Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grad,</hi> but the <hi>Turks</hi> having advanced ſo far, it was thought ſafer to put it into the Caſtle of <hi>Presbourg.</hi> This Crown is of a pretty ſingular ſhape; for it is very low, and hath a Croſs on the top with four leaves that go compleatly round it, of which one is as big as the other three, or at leaſt, as two of them. It is infinitely eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the <hi>Hungarians,</hi> becauſe they believe that an Angel brought it to their King St. <hi>Stephen:</hi> and the moſt <hi>Auguſt</hi> Emperour <hi>Leopold,</hi> who reigns at preſent, is the two and fourtieth King that hath been crowned with that Crown.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:34980:26"/>
                  <head>S. MARTINSBERG.</head>
                  <p>Is a pretty handſom Town, and a very ſtrong place, ſeated on the Top of a very high Hill, from whence all the Countrey about may be diſcovered. It lies betwixt the Fort of <hi>Raab,</hi> and the Town of <hi>Dotis.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>DOTIS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Dotis, Tata,</hi> or <hi>Theodata,</hi> is but four Leagues from <hi>Comora;</hi> it hath a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle with Ditches round it, and not far from thence, there are ſome natural Baths. It lies betwixt <hi>S. Martinsberg</hi> and the <hi>Danube,</hi> hath been often ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and re-taken, and belongs to his <hi>Imperial</hi> Majeſty. The Count of <hi>Salms,</hi> General of the <hi>Imperial</hi> Army, took it in the year 1565. with the Town of <hi>Veſprim.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>VESPRIM.</head>
                  <p>In <hi>Latin Veſprinium,</hi> and in <hi>High-Dutch Weisbrun,</hi> is a little pretty ſtrong Town, lying near the head of the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:34980:26"/> 
                     <hi>Sarwis,</hi> and the Lake <hi>Balaton</hi> ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Leagues from <hi>Strigonium,</hi> and five from <hi>Alba Regalis,</hi> being the Seat of a Biſhop Suffragan to <hi>Strigonium;</hi> it is the capital of the County of its Name, and hath a ſtrong Caſtle upon the top of a little Hill, belonging to his <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial</hi> Majeſty. The Count of <hi>Salms</hi> took it in the year 1565. with the Town of <hi>Dotis.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>PAPA.</head>
                  <p>A little Town, but ſtrong, defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by a Caſtle, and lying in the County of <hi>Veſprim,</hi> upon the River of <hi>Malchaltz;</hi> it belongs to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>SARWAR.</head>
                  <p>This place lyes upon the <hi>Raab,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>Papa,</hi> and <hi>Sabaria,</hi> under Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Emperour, having been re-taken in the year, 1567.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>SABARIA.</head>
                  <p>Is an Ancient Town in the County
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:34980:27"/> of <hi>Iron Caſtle</hi> lying at the concourſe of the two Rivers of <hi>Guntz,</hi> and <hi>Regnitz,</hi> before they fall into the <hi>Raab.</hi> This Town is affirmed to be the Native Town of St. <hi>Martin;</hi> and there are ſome who report, and others that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that the Famous Poet <hi>Ovid</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and was Buried in this Town of <hi>Sabaria.</hi> They write, that having been Seven years Baniſhed at <hi>Tomos,</hi> near the <hi>Euxin</hi> Sea, he was afterwards recalled, and died at <hi>Sabaria,</hi> upon his return to <hi>Italy;</hi> where they ſay his Tomb was found in the year 1508. with this E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitaph, made by himſelf, and cut on the outſide of a ſtately Vault.</p>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div type="epitaph">
                              <q>
                                 <lg>
                                    <head>Fatum neceſſitatis lex.</head>
                                    <l>Hic ſitus eſt Vates, quem Divi Caeſaris ira</l>
                                    <l>Auguſti, Patriâ cedere juſſit humo.</l>
                                    <l>Soepe miſer voluit Patriis occumbere terris;</l>
                                    <l>Sed fruſtra, hunc illi fata dedêre locum.</l>
                                 </lg>
                              </q>
                              <p>That's to ſay.</p>
                              <q>
                                 <pb n="51" facs="tcp:34980:27"/>
                                 <lg>
                                    <head>Fate <hi>is a Law of neceſſity.</hi>
                                    </head>
                                    <l>Here lyes the Poet, whom the Anger of Divine <hi>Caeſar,</hi> obliged to leave his Country; often did he wiſh in his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery that he might dye in his own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, but in vain; for the Fates have given him this for a Burying place.</l>
                                 </lg>
                              </q>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <p>And about the year 1540. <hi>Iſabel</hi> Queen of <hi>Hungary</hi> ſhewed <hi>Peter Angelo Bargeo,</hi> a Silver Pen that <hi>Ovid</hi> made uſe of to write with; which not long before had been found amongſt the Ancient Ruins of <hi>Tearunum,</hi> at preſent called <hi>Belgrade,</hi> at the mouth of the <hi>Save,</hi> that falls into the <hi>Danube,</hi> with theſe words Engraven round it: <hi>Ovidii Naſonis Calamus,</hi> which that Queen highly priſed, and kept it as a Sacred thing.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>GRAN.</head>
                  <p>This Town which is called <hi>Gran, Strigonium,</hi> or <hi>Oſtrogon,</hi> lyes on the South-ſide of the River of <hi>Gran,</hi> where it falls into the <hi>Danube.</hi> It is divid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into the Upperr and Lower, Town both which are conſiderably ſtrong
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:34980:28"/> and have good Walls. The lower Town commands the <hi>Danube,</hi> and St. <hi>Thomas</hi> his Hill is alſo very well fortified, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe being cloſe by the Town it might command it. In this Town there are excellent Natural Baths, that are not too hot. Heretofore it was the Metropolitan City of <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary,</hi> and St. <hi>Stephen</hi> their firſt King was born in it; as <hi>Stephen</hi> III. died there. The chief Ornaments of it are the great Church of St. <hi>Stephen,</hi> who lyes buried in it, the Arch-Biſhop's Palace, and the Houſes of other Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons: This Arch-Biſhop formerly put the Crown upon the Kings Head the day of his Coronation. In the Upper Town there is a Rock, on which a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſtrong Caſtle is built. The Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boring Hills abound in Vines, and the Country about with Springs of hot water, ſo that by reaſon of the Fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of the Country, and the ſtrength of the Town, the Kings of <hi>Hungary,</hi> in former times had their Palace and kept their Reſidence there: Hardly any place hath maintained ſo many Bloody Sieges. For <hi>John</hi> King of <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> Beſieged it, but in vain; and he
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:34980:28"/> could not ſucceed in his Attempt. <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyman</hi> took it in the year, 1542. but the Count of <hi>Mansfield</hi> re-took it, for the Arch-duke <hi>Matthias.</hi> It was once more Beſieged in vain; but in Succeſſion of time <hi>Sultan Achmet</hi> took it, by means of an infamous piece of Baſeneſs, that the Chriſtians who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended it committed; for having kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Count of <hi>Dampierre</hi> the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, they ſurrendered the place to <hi>Alybeg</hi> General of the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Army. The Town of <hi>Barckan,</hi> is exactly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſit to <hi>Gran,</hi> and there is a Bridge of Boats betwixt thoſe two places. It was before that Fort, that the Armies of the Emperor and <hi>Poland</hi> gained the Battle againſt the <hi>Turks</hi> in the Month of <hi>October,</hi> 1683. when they Beſieged and took the ſaid Fort, and the Town of <hi>Gran</hi> alſo the 23. of the ſame Month, after they had gloriouſly raiſed the Siege of <hi>Vienna;</hi> which the Grand Vizier <hi>Kara Muſtapha</hi> had laid to it, with the chief Forces of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Empire, who were cut to pieces, and put to the rout there; and after that the City of <hi>Gran,</hi> for the ſpace of 80. years had groaned under the yoke
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:34980:29"/> of the <hi>Turks.</hi> But the <hi>Barbarians,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing impatient that ſuch an important place ſhould remain longer in the Hands of the Chriſtians, endeavoured to regain it with an extraordinary ſtrong Army, and laid Siege to it the 30th. of <hi>July,</hi> 1685. which they were forced to raiſe, with the loſs of the Battle that followed after the 16th. of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> the ſame year.</p>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>The Iſle of Schut.</head>
                     <p>This Iſle, which the <hi>Latins</hi> call <hi>Inſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la Cituorum,</hi> called commonly <hi>Schut,</hi> and <hi>Comora,</hi> or rather <hi>Comara,</hi> from its moſt important place lying on the North-Eaſt point of the Iſland, that has that name, is Twelve <hi>Hungarian</hi> Leagues in length, and Five in breadth, Sixteen <hi>Hungarian</hi> making Twenty <hi>German</hi> Leagues. It contains about Three Hundred Villages, or Bourgs, and Fifteen Thouſand Inhabitants. Its next beſt place to <hi>Comora,</hi> is <hi>Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria</hi> or <hi>Samareyn,</hi> for which cauſe <hi>Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterus</hi> ſays, that the Iſland is called <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maria,</hi> as well as <hi>Schythia</hi> and <hi>Camaron,</hi> meaning <hi>Schut</hi> and <hi>Comara.</hi> This
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:34980:29"/> Iſle is made by the <hi>Danube,</hi> which dividing it ſelf into four Branches be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low <hi>Preſbourg,</hi> makes many lovely Iſles, full of tall Trees, of which this is the chief; at the end whereof and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low <hi>Comara</hi> the <hi>Danube</hi> unites all its Branches, of which that which comes from the Upper <hi>Hungary,</hi> is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Waag;</hi> and the River coming from the North falls into the <hi>Danube</hi> at this Iſland.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>RAAB or JAVARIN.</head>
                  <p>A very ſtrong Town ſituated where the Rivers of <hi>Raab</hi> and <hi>Rabuits,</hi> fall into the <hi>Danube,</hi> is the Seat of a Biſhop Suffragan to <hi>Gran,</hi> or <hi>Strigoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um.</hi> The <hi>Germans</hi> call it <hi>Raab,</hi> the <hi>French Javarin,</hi> the <hi>Hungarians Gever,</hi> the <hi>Italians Giavarin,</hi> and the Latin Authors, <hi>Javarinum, Arabo</hi> and <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabo.</hi> The Fort was made by <hi>Ferdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nand</hi> of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> King of <hi>Hungary,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he came to be Emperor in the year, 1550. and is one of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleateſt Strengths in <hi>Europe.</hi> It hath two Bridges, one on the ſide of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria,</hi> and the other on the ſide of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba Regalis,</hi> or <hi>Stael-Weiſſenbourgh,</hi> it is
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:34980:30"/> fortified with Seven Baſtions, and hath Four high Mounts, from whence all the Country about may be diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered. The Firſt is the Baſtion, on which the Caſtle or Governours Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace is built. The Second is upon the brink of the River of <hi>Danube.</hi> The Third ſtands upon the Holy Hill; and when the <hi>Turks</hi> blew it up, there was a Man upon it on Horſe back, who was carried by the force of the Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powder into the <hi>Danube,</hi> without the leaſt hurt either to Man or Horſe. The Fourth is that in the middle, which looks Eaſt-ward into the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey. The Fifth is that which is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the New Baſtion. The Sixth the Imperial Baſtion. And the Seventh is that of <hi>Hungary,</hi> on the brink of the River of <hi>Raab.</hi> Here it was that the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Governour was killed, when the Chriſtians ſurpriſed the Town, in the night time. It is very near the Iſle of <hi>Schut</hi> in a Plain that reaches out of ſight, environed by a Branch of the <hi>Danube,</hi> and the River of <hi>Raab,</hi> which makes many to give it that name: And it would ſeem that nothing can be able to hurt it; unleſs it be a little Hill
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:34980:30"/> which is at a pretty good diſtance from it too, and might be blown up when they pleaſed, if there were occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for it. Beyond it there is alſo a little Tower, in the middle of the Plain, from whence the approach of an Enemy, may eaſily be diſcovered. This Town may be near Three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred paces in Circuit, and at each Angle of the Figure, there is a Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier which commands the Fortification faced with brick. <hi>Sinam Baſſa</hi> beſieg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it in the Reign of Sultan <hi>Amurath</hi> III. He loſt a great many men there, and Twelve thouſand were killed in one Attack; but at length it rendred in the year 1591. by the Treachery of the Count of <hi>Hardeck,</hi> who was Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of the place, for which baſe Action he had his Head ſtruck off at <hi>Vienna.</hi> Some years after it was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken by the Count of <hi>Swartſzenbourg,</hi> and the Count of <hi>Palfy</hi> who ſurpriſed it in the night time, in the year 1606. under the Emperor <hi>Rodolph,</hi> and made a great ſlaughter of all the <hi>Turks</hi> that were in it: A piece of the Gate, which was broken down by a Petard, is ſtill kept in the Cathedral Church, as the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:34980:31"/> Inſtrument of the Victory; in memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry whereof, the Town fires yearly all their Guns, and make a Solemn Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion. Whilſt the <hi>Turks</hi> were Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of that Town, they made a Dungeon for the Chriſtian Priſoners, into which there enters no Light but through a Grate that looks to the Market-place. But at preſent there are commonly <hi>Turks</hi> ſhut up in it, who beg the Charity of thoſe that paſs that way, and ſell a kind of Whips, which they make in their wretched Confine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. <hi>George Draſcovitz</hi> Biſhop of that Town held a Synod there in the year 1579.</p>
                  <p>The Emperor finding himſelf in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commoded by the great number of <hi>Chiaus</hi> or Ordinary Envoys who came often to <hi>Vienna,</hi> from the Vizier of <hi>Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da,</hi> and never went back again with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome Preſent, ordered for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that they ſhould advance no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than <hi>Raab,</hi> unleſs they had a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, and that they ſhould receive their diſpatches there. In conſequence whereof there was in <hi>December,</hi> 1685. a <hi>Turkiſh Aga</hi> there named <hi>Aga Scelebi,</hi> waiting for the Emperours Anſwer,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:34980:31"/> from whom he came to beg a Peace.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>COMORA.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Gomora, Crumenum,</hi> or <hi>Comaronium,</hi> is a very large fair Town, lying at the Eaſt-end of the Iſle of <hi>Schut;</hi> it looks to the <hi>Danube,</hi> and <hi>Waag,</hi> and is very well fortifyed and peopled. The Fortifications of it have alſo been late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enlarged, and a great deal of ground taken in, by means of a Line drawn from the <hi>Waag</hi> to the <hi>Danube,</hi> and is fortified by four Baſtions more.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>TORTOISE.</head>
                  <p>Is reckoned a ſtrong place, and has its Name from its Figure, which in ſome manner reſembles a <hi>Tortoiſe. Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nan Baſha</hi> having taken the Town of <hi>Raab,</hi> beſieged this place with Three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore Veſſels, and a vaſt number of <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Tartars;</hi> but it was without ſucceſs, and moſt part of the <hi>Tartars</hi> were kill'd there.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:34980:32"/>
                  <head>PETRONEL.</head>
                  <p>Betwixt <hi>Vienna</hi> and <hi>Presbourg,</hi> where the River of <hi>Mark</hi> falls into the <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nube,</hi> lyes the Town of <hi>Petronel,</hi> near the Hill, and Caſtle of <hi>Haimbourg. Petronel</hi> is thought to be the place that was anciently called <hi>Carnuntum,</hi> which was one of the ſtrongeſt places of the <hi>Panonians,</hi> and in vain beſieged by the <hi>Romans</hi> 170. years, before the Incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of our Saviour; who never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the leſs, in Progres of time made them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Maſters of it under <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> that ſent thither a <hi>Roman</hi> Colony, with the Forces which were called <hi>Legio decima Gemina,</hi> and <hi>Claſſis Iſtrica.</hi> It was enlarged ſo much afterward, that it became the chief City of the Upper <hi>Panonia,</hi> and contained all that lay on the South ſide of the <hi>Danube,</hi> where at preſent we ſee <hi>Haimbourg, Altenbourg,</hi> and <hi>St. Petronel.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>ALTENBOURG.</head>
                  <p>Is a Town environned by the little River of <hi>Leytha,</hi> and near that ſmall
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:34980:32"/> Branch of the <hi>Danube,</hi> which runs to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Lower <hi>Hungary,</hi> eight Leagues from <hi>Presbourg.</hi> It was form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erly an open Village; but it hath ſince been walled in by the <hi>Hungarians,</hi> who call it <hi>Ovar,</hi> that's to ſay, old <hi>Caſtle,</hi> which ſutes with the German name <hi>Altenbourg,</hi> that ſignifies an old Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough. It is near to the Weſt end of the Iſle of <hi>Schut,</hi> and in the Hands of the Emperour, who in the year 1646. gave that Lordſhip to <hi>Nicholas Drasko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witch,</hi> Count of <hi>Trukoſtian,</hi> at that time choſen Palatin of <hi>Hungary,</hi> that he might qualifie him by that Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>SIGET.</head>
                  <p>A ſtrong Town lying on this ſide of the <hi>Drave,</hi> in the Waſh of the River <hi>Alm,</hi> with a Citadel fortifyed by a tripple Wall, and a tripple Ditch: It is the chief Town of the County of that Name, and was taken by the <hi>Turks</hi> the ſeventh of <hi>September,</hi> 1566. after a brave defence made by <hi>Nicho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las Eſdrin</hi> Count of <hi>Serini,</hi> Great-Grandfather to <hi>Nicholas</hi> II, Knight of
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:34980:33"/> the Golden Fleece, who died in the year, 1664. and three days after, <hi>Soly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> who beſieged it departed this Life in the Town of <hi>Five-Churches,</hi> whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, falling ſick in the Camp, he was carried. This <hi>Nicholas</hi> I. was that Great and Valiant Warriour, who af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the taking of ſo many Towns, and gaining ſo many Battles, defended that great and important Place of <hi>Ziget,</hi> againſt the <hi>Turks</hi> with an undaunted Courage to the laſt; ſo that being no longer able to reſiſt the formidable Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts of that Barbarous Enemy, he made the laſt Sally with Prodigious Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, and amongſt many Musket-ſhot which he received at the firſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge, one in the Head, laid him Dead on the Ground. The Barbari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans having cut off his Head, ſent it to <hi>Selim</hi> the Son of <hi>Solyman,</hi> who ſent it to <hi>Mahomet Baſſa,</hi> and he to the <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſha</hi> of <hi>Buda,</hi> who preſently wrapt it up in a Cloth of Silk, and by two Boors ſent it to the Emperor <hi>Maximi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> in the Camp of <hi>Turn</hi> or <hi>Bregeto,</hi> and from thence it was carried by <hi>Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaſar Butſchano</hi> to <hi>Tſcacaturno,</hi> and there buried in St. <hi>Helens</hi> Church,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:34980:33"/> where <hi>Catharine de Frangipani</hi> his firſt Wife lay; this is the <hi>Epitaph</hi> upon his Tomb.</p>
                  <q>
                     <p>Illuſtriſſimo Comiti <hi>Nicolao Zeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio</hi> Torquati ex ſorore nepoti, à <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolo</hi> V. poſt Viennam obſidione ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutam, quòd in ea Adoleſcens adhuc &amp; Tyro multa praeclara confeciſſet, equo, auroque donato: Ad Budam &amp; Peſchtum pulchra per facinora ſummâ cum laude probato: Croa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia, Dalmatiae, &amp; Sclavoniae Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nato, Bavernicorumque Regalium in Pannonia Magiſterio ſingulari cum prudentiâ functo: Copiis Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaris ad dextrum Danubij latus à <hi>Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinando</hi> I. &amp; <hi>Maximiliano</hi> II. Impera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toribus Praefecto: Victis ſaepiſſimè, fugatis, captis, caeciſque hoſtibus: Infauſtiſſimâ poſtremùm, funeſtiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mâque Sigethi expugnatione, cujus arcem contra innumerabilem <hi>Soly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manni</hi> Turcarum Principis exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, factâ eorum ingenti &amp; memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabili ſtrage, diutìus qum viribus par fuerat, defendit, defuncto ibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem <hi>Solymanno,</hi> totiùs Orbis flagello, pulcherrimè abſumpto, bellicae gloriae
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:34980:34"/> fortiſſimo, invictiſſimoque Duci, de ſe publièque B. M. P. P.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>Vixit annos quadraginta octo: occubu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it ſeptimo Septembris, anno Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginei partus 1566.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>ALIUD.</head>
                  <q>
                     <l>"Hoſtibus ut vidit diris &amp; caedere fatis</l>
                     <l>"Credita virtuti maenia celſa ſuae:</l>
                     <l>"Servatae à me olim, nunc me ſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitis, "inquit,</l>
                     <l>"Arces &amp; pugnans <hi>Zrinius</hi> occubuit.</l>
                     <l>"Imodo, te jacta quantum vis, Roma "Lyburnis</l>
                     <l>"Et ſunt quae mortem pectora deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciunt.</l>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>FIVE CHURCHES.</head>
                  <p>This Town hath a Biſhoprick Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fragan to <hi>Gran,</hi> or <hi>Strigonium;</hi> the <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> call it <hi>Funf-Kircken,</hi> the <hi>Hungari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans Otegiazack,</hi> and the <hi>Latin</hi> Authors <hi>Quinque Eccleſiae.</hi> It lyes upon the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulet called <hi>Kevirz</hi> cloſe by the <hi>Drave,</hi> which five or ſix Leagues from that, falls into the <hi>Danube. Five Churches</hi> is
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:34980:34"/> a ſtrong place Four Leagues from <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get,</hi> and in the hands of the <hi>Turks. Solyman</hi> II. took it in the year 1543, and afterward died in that Town, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Siege of <hi>Siget</hi> in the year, 1566. which being ſo near, they had reaſon to ſay that he died in his Camp. The Valiant Count <hi>Nicholas Serini</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond of that Name, burnt this Town, and the Bridge of <hi>Eſſeck,</hi> in the year 1664. and ſhortly after ſignalized him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in a particular manner at the Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of <hi>Raab,</hi> the <hi>Turks</hi> having ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly confeſſed, that the Terror of his Name was the cauſe of the gaining of that Battle. Not long after that brave Count ended his Life, in a very Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical manner, for being ſeparated from his Attendance, and engaged in the Thickets of a Wood, a Wild Boar enraged by the Wounds which it had received, fell upon him, and having hurt him in the Knee, threw him down. The Count had not the leiſure to come to him again; for the violent Beaſt ſtruck one of its Tusks into his Head, and gave him that Mortal wound, whereof he ſhortly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter died in his Page's Arms. Such
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:34980:35"/> was the end of that Illuſtrious Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, whom Death ſeemed to have reſpected amidſt the greateſt Dangers to which he daily expoſed himſelf, and yet became a prey to an inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Beaſt. He was a ſworn Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to the <hi>Mahometans,</hi> and had for them as implacable a Hatred as ever <hi>Hanibal</hi> had for the <hi>Romans.</hi> He was undaunted in Dangers, brave in Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, indefategable in Labour, Mild in Peace, and moderate in his Pleaſures. He was very ſober and took greateſt pleaſure in Hunting in the Woods, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was an Exerciſe that reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled the Labours of War. He was a man of a profound and ſolid Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and in a Word, one of the moſt zealous Defenders of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Religion, whoſe Courage, Valour, and brave Actions, ought in Hiſtory to procure him a place amongſt the greateſt <hi>Hero</hi>'s. He died the 18th. of <hi>November,</hi> 1664. about the four and fortieth year of his Age, and his Body was Buried near to <hi>Sacathurne,</hi> the place of his Reſidence in <hi>Croatia,</hi> in the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that hath been built in the ſame place of the Wood where he was killed,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:34980:35"/> and all round the Chappel theſe words are to be read: <hi>Neque diem, neque horum ſcimus.</hi> The Chappel is full of all ſorts of Trophies, Standards, and Colours, which that Noble Warriour took from the <hi>Turks.</hi> His Epitaph is in Leonin Verſe.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Fata, Leonini verſus, deflete <hi>Serini,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Magnus bellator fuit &amp; Virtutis a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mator,</l>
                     <l>Turcas proſternit, mortemque &amp; vulnera ſpernit,</l>
                     <l>Hic vitâ exemptus, crudeli eſt morte peremptus,</l>
                     <l>Inter Apri ardentes, invenit funera dentes,</l>
                     <l>Atque hoc auguſtum meruit ſub mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more buſtum</l>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>
                     <hi>ESSECK</hi> and its <hi>BRIDGE.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>The Town of <hi>Eſſeck</hi> or <hi>Oſſeck,</hi> is thought to be the Ancient <hi>Murſa,</hi> or at leaſt it is not far from it. Hiſtory will have it to be in this place, that <hi>Conſtantus</hi> Son to the Emperor <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine</hi> defeated the Tyrant <hi>Magnen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> in the year 359. This Town lies very low, and there are Trees grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in all the Streets. On one ſide of
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:34980:36"/> the Gate there is part of a <hi>Roman</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription, which begins thus: <hi>M. Aeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> &amp;c. And on the other, the Head of a Maid on a Stone. There is a very pret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Dial there alſo, brought thither from <hi>Serinwar;</hi> and one of the fineſt pieces of Cannon that ever was ſeen in thoſe parts: It is not upon a Carriage, as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers are, but upon great beam of Wood. This is a great and populous Town, there being in it at leaſt five hundred ſhops, many Moſques and <hi>Haccars,</hi> which are large Inns for Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellers.</p>
                  <p>But that which is moſt conſiderable, is the lovely Wooden Bridge, (not to be matched in the World) which was built by <hi>Solyman,</hi> in the year 1521. immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately after he took <hi>Belgrade,</hi> partly over the <hi>Drave,</hi> and partly over the River of <hi>Fenues</hi> cloſe by, both which do often o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verflow. On this ſide the <hi>Drave</hi> it is about Eleven Hundred paces long, and on the other ſide almoſt Eight Thouſand, all of good Oak. It is about Twelve yards broad, ſo that three <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Wag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons, that are bigger than ours, can go a Breaſt upon it. The River of <hi>Drave</hi> is not broad at that place, and there are
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:34980:36"/> but ſixteen Boats that ſupport the Bridge with great Trees that make the Arches. All who well conſider that Bridge, and the ſeveral Wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en Towers which are built upon it, with the vaſt number of Beams that were needful to uphold ſo great a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick, cannot ſufficiently admire, how they could find Timber enough to build or to ſupport it. The Brave Count <hi>Nicholas</hi> of <hi>Serini,</hi> Second of that Name, burnt the part of the Bridge that is over the <hi>Drave</hi> in the year 1664. but in ſix Weeks time they made ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Bridge of Boats, a little lower than the firſt. The <hi>Turks</hi> would not re-build it in the ſame place, becauſe the Piles that ſupported it, and that were under Water when the Fire was out, ſtuck ſo faſt in the ground, that it would have coſt them too much Trouble to get them out. Over this Bridge march all the Armies that come into <hi>Hungary,</hi> and here it was that the unfortunate King <hi>Loüis</hi> thought to have put a ſtop to the <hi>Turks,</hi> that were co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming againſt him, under the Conduct of <hi>Solyman,</hi> in the year 1526. and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, if that Paſs had been well defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:34980:37"/> at that time, it is probable <hi>Soly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> might not ſo eaſily have marched forwards to <hi>Buda.</hi> Count <hi>Serini</hi> burnt the part of the Bridge that was built o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the <hi>Drave,</hi> to hinder the <hi>Grand Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier</hi> from receiving Succours from the other Counties of <hi>Turky;</hi> and upon his return, he alſo burnt <hi>Five-Churches,</hi> that lyes Weſt-ward from <hi>Eſſeck. Count Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlie,</hi> General of the Imperial Army, ſet fire again to the Bridge of <hi>Eſſeck,</hi> which for twelve hundred Paces length was immediately in a flame; at the ſame time he took the Town of <hi>Eſſeck,</hi> put all he met to the Sword, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving plundred it, and blown up the Magazin and Arſenal, that were full of Ammunition and Proviſions, he put Fire to it, and reduced it to A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>WALPO.</head>
                  <p>Is a Town lying upon a River of the ſame Name, which abounds in Fiſh. It was taken by the <hi>Turks</hi> in the year 1642. and re-taken and ſacked by Count <hi>Leſlie,</hi> in the Month of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt</hi> 1685.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:34980:37"/>
                  <head>METRONIZA.</head>
                  <p>Is a pretty neat Town, and big e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to be the place of a Fair. It lyes upon the ſide of a Lake.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>CIRMIUM.</head>
                  <p>This Town lying upon the River <hi>Boſneth,</hi> near the <hi>Save,</hi> into which it falls, is the chief Town of the Province of that Name, which is alſo called <hi>Schremnia,</hi> in the South part of <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary,</hi> having been formerly a Biſhops Seat; it hath its Name from <hi>Sirmus</hi> King of the <hi>Tribals:</hi> This is the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent <hi>Sirmium</hi> heretofore ſo Famous, which is at preſent ſo little eſteemed. However, there grows excellent Wine about it, and in this Province, it is ſaid, that the Emperour <hi>Probus</hi> planted Vines with his own hand, upon <hi>Mount-Almos</hi> or <hi>Arpataro.</hi> That Emperor was killed there by his own Soldiers, who were vexed that he kept them in ſo ſtrict Diſcipline, and feared that they might be thought uſeleſs when that Prince had quell'd all the Enemies of
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:34980:38"/> the Empire; but afterwards repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what they had done, they made him this <hi>Epitaph.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Hic probus Imperator</l>
                     <l>Et verè probus ſitus eſt.</l>
                     <l>Victor omnium gentium Barbarorum,</l>
                     <l>Victor etiam Tyrannorum.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>That Emperour named <hi>Marcus Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relius Probus,</hi> was the Son of a Peaſant in <hi>Dalmatia,</hi> and was killed in the year 282. Many <hi>Roman</hi> Emperours have been in theſe parts, who were born, died, or ſignalized themſelves by great Actions there. For not to ſpeak of <hi>Trajan, Caracalla, Gallien, Conſtantius,</hi> and ſeveral others; the Emperours <hi>Aurelian, Probus,</hi> and <hi>Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian,</hi> were born at <hi>Sirmium,</hi> and <hi>Clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius Gothicus</hi> died there, or very near to that place. <hi>Jovian</hi> and <hi>Valentinian,</hi> were born in <hi>Pannonia,</hi> and in the time of <hi>Photinus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Sirmium,</hi> there was a general Council held in that Town.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:34980:38"/>
               <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p> Of the Rivers of <hi>Hungary,</hi> and their Deſcription.</p>
               </argument>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>THE <hi>DANUBE.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THE <hi>Don</hi> or <hi>Donaw,</hi> by the Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents called <hi>Danube,</hi> is the ſecond River of <hi>Europe,</hi> both for Greatneſs and Force; its ſource is in <hi>Swabia,</hi> in the County of <hi>Fuſtemberg,</hi> where the <hi>Schwartz-wald</hi> is, and the black For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt. It paſſes by <hi>Ulm,</hi> over againſt which it receives the <hi>Iler,</hi> which runs by <hi>Kempten,</hi> and near to <hi>Memminguen,</hi> it paſſes by <hi>Donawert,</hi> near which and on the other ſide of it, it receives the <hi>Lech,</hi> which runs by <hi>Ausbourg,</hi> and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parates <hi>Swabia</hi> from <hi>Bavaria;</hi> near to <hi>Donawert,</hi> the <hi>Danube</hi> enters into <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varia,</hi> where it leaves <hi>Newbourg</hi> to the right hand, <hi>Ingolſtadt</hi> to the left; di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vides <hi>Bavaria</hi> from the Palatinat, from whence it receives the <hi>Nabe;</hi> paſſes under the Bridges of <hi>Ratisbonne</hi> and
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:34980:39"/> 
                     <hi>Siraubing,</hi> which are to the right; on the ſame ſide receives the <hi>Iler,</hi> which watereth <hi>Munick</hi> and <hi>Landſhout,</hi> the Capitals of the upper and lower Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chies of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> receives at <hi>Paſſaw</hi> the <hi>Inn,</hi> which comes from the <hi>Enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dines</hi> amongſt the <hi>Griſons,</hi> and croſſes the County of <hi>Tirol,</hi> and there wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes <hi>Inſpruck,</hi> that has the firſt Bridge upon the <hi>Inn,</hi> then <hi>Halle,</hi> in <hi>Tirol,</hi> and <hi>Kufſtain,</hi> &amp;c. and gives to a part of the Town of <hi>Paſſaw</hi> the Name of <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtat,</hi> the firſt Town of <hi>Inn.</hi> A little below <hi>Paſſaw</hi> the <hi>Danube</hi> enters <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria,</hi> and there watereth <hi>Lintz</hi> the Capital City of <hi>Auſtria;</hi> above <hi>Ens</hi> it receives the River of <hi>Ens,</hi> where the Town of <hi>Ens</hi> is, waſhes <hi>Crems</hi> in the middle <hi>Auſtria,</hi> and <hi>Vienna</hi> in the lower; <hi>Vienna</hi> and <hi>Lintz</hi> are on the right ſide Bank, and <hi>Crems</hi> on the left of the <hi>Danube.</hi> The <hi>Murau,</hi> which deſcends from <hi>Moravia,</hi> falls into the <hi>Danube</hi> between <hi>Auſtria</hi> and <hi>Hungary,</hi> where the <hi>Danube</hi> continuing its courſe, on the left hand waſhes <hi>Presbourg,</hi> the Capital City of the Upper <hi>Hungary,</hi> embraces the Iſle of <hi>Schut,</hi> on the Bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders whereof are <hi>Owar</hi> or <hi>Walkenbourg,</hi>
                     <pb n="75" facs="tcp:34980:39"/> and <hi>Gever</hi> or <hi>Javarin;</hi> and at the point of the Iſle, <hi>Comora,</hi> all ſtrong places, which for many years have ſtood it out againſt the <hi>Turks.</hi> The <hi>Danube</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving at <hi>Comora</hi> rejoined all its Branch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, paſſes by <hi>Gran</hi> or <hi>Strigonium,</hi> runs betwixt <hi>Buda</hi> the ancient place of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidence of the Kings of <hi>Hungary,</hi> and <hi>Peſt,</hi> embraces the Iſſe of <hi>Ratzenimarck;</hi> waters <hi>Colocz</hi> on the left, receives the <hi>Drave</hi> on the right, and over againſt the Iſle of <hi>Erdewdy,</hi> the <hi>Teiſſe</hi> on the left, over againſt <hi>Salonkemen,</hi> the <hi>Save</hi> on the right, and below the confluence of the <hi>Save</hi> and <hi>Danube</hi> lyes <hi>Belgrade,</hi> in a Situation that ought to be eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, ſeeing of the four Rivers that are near to it, the leaſt runs above an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Leagues: Beyond <hi>Belgrade</hi> we have but little knowledge of the <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nube,</hi> and from this place forwards the Ancients began to call it the <hi>Iſter:</hi> On the right hand it receives all the Riv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, which deſcend from <hi>Servia</hi> and <hi>Bulgaria,</hi> and on the left thoſe of <hi>Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lachia</hi> and <hi>Moldavia,</hi> by ſeven Mouths it diſcharges it ſelf into the greater or black Sea. The whole Length of its Courſe may be ſix hundred Leagues,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:34980:40"/> to wit, two hundred in <hi>Germany,</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what leſs in <hi>Hungary,</hi> and ſomewhat more from <hi>Hungary</hi> to the Black Sea.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The <hi>TIBISQUE,</hi> and the <hi>BEDRACK.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>That great River towards the Eaſt called <hi>Tibiſcus,</hi> or otherwiſe the <hi>Teiſſe,</hi> which hath its ſource in the Country of <hi>Maromorus,</hi> at the Foot of the <hi>Carpati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> Hills, having received the <hi>Mariſcus</hi> or <hi>Mariſa</hi> with ſeveral other Rivers, diſcharges it ſelf into the <hi>Danube,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>Waradin, St. Peter,</hi> and <hi>Belgrade.</hi> There are brought down this River great quantities of Salt Stones, dug out of ſeveral Mines in <hi>Hungary</hi> and <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilvania,</hi> which are alſo ſent up the <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nube</hi> as far as <hi>Presbourg.</hi> This River is reckoned the beſt in all <hi>Europe;</hi> nay, I may ſay, in all the World, for Fiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; ſo that the People of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try ſay commonly, that there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in that River but Water and Fiſh.</p>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:34980:40"/>
                  <p>The River of <hi>Bedrack,</hi> which falls in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Tibiſcus</hi> not far from <hi>Tockay,</hi> is alſo ſo full of Fiſh, that in the Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer time when the water is low, the People ſay that the Fiſh make the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to ſwell: It is none of the ſmalleſt Rivers; for according to the Relation of thoſe who have ſeen it, it is Thirty fathom broad, and Eighty eight and a half deep. But there is no good fiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in it with Nets, becauſe the Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel of it is triangular. This great Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tili<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y is attributed to the Communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that its Water hath with the ſalt Mines under Ground, which impreg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nates it with a Principle of Fecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The <hi>RAAB.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>The River <hi>Arabo</hi> or <hi>Raab</hi> is to the Weſt, which hath its ſource in <hi>Stiria,</hi> and falls alſo into the <hi>Danube.</hi> It is a River in much eſteem, becauſe it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives the <hi>Lauffnitz,</hi> the <hi>Pica,</hi> the <hi>Guntz,</hi> and many other Rivers; but it is become more Famous by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feat of the <hi>Turks,</hi> under the conduct of <hi>Achmet,</hi> who at that time was <hi>Grand
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:34980:41"/> Viſie-,</hi> by the <hi>Imperial</hi> Army at <hi>St. Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard</hi> near to that River.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The <hi>DRAVE.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>There is a very lovely River to the South, called the <hi>Drave,</hi> or the <hi>Drau,</hi> which having its head in the Country of <hi>Saltzburland,</hi> that is a part of the ancient <hi>Noricum,</hi> and running through the middle of <hi>Carinthia,</hi> falls at length into the <hi>Danube</hi> near to <hi>Erdoed,</hi> or the ancient <hi>Teutoburgium,</hi> after it hath run about an hundred Leagues. The River of <hi>Mure</hi> falls into it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The <hi>SAVE.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>On the ſame ſide alſo is the River of <hi>Sava</hi> or <hi>Sau,</hi> which is very broad, and having its ſource in <hi>Carinthia,</hi> falls into the <hi>Danube</hi> at <hi>Belgrade,</hi> after it hath run near an hundred Leagues, and been augmented by ſeveral conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Rivers that fall into it. It ſeems to be a very pretty River at <hi>Carnodunum</hi> or <hi>Crainbourg,</hi> which is a neat Town near the head of it; but it is much en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged in its Courſe: It makes ſome
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:34980:41"/> pretty Iſlands, as <hi>Metubaris</hi> to the Weſt of the ancient <hi>Sirmium,</hi> and <hi>Sigeſtica</hi> or <hi>Siſſex</hi> near <hi>Zagrabia,</hi> wherein there was heretofore a very ſtrong and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Town. The Water of the <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nube</hi> ſeems to be whiter and more mud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy than the <hi>Sau,</hi> and the Water of the <hi>Sau,</hi> blacker and clearer than the <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nube.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The <hi>GRAN</hi> and the <hi>WAAG.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>In the North of <hi>Hungary</hi> there are ſome Rivers alſo, which having their ſources in the <hi>Carpathian</hi> Mountains, divide it from <hi>Poland;</hi> amongſt others the River of <hi>Gran,</hi> which falls into the <hi>Danube,</hi> cloſe by <hi>Strigonium</hi> or <hi>Gran;</hi> and the <hi>Waag</hi> or <hi>Vagus,</hi> which diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges it ſelf into the ſame River, above <hi>Comara. Stuckius</hi> who is an Eye Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſays, that that River is no leſs than the <hi>Po</hi> in <hi>Italy:</hi> It is certain that at <hi>Frey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtadt,</hi> which is a Town about ſeven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen Leagues from the place, where it falls into the <hi>Danube,</hi> it is very broad, and has a fair Bridge there, the greateſt part whereof was carried away by the Ice, in the year 1669. A great way above this
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:34980:42"/> Place, and nearer its ſource, there is another very fair Bridge at <hi>Trenſchin.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The <hi>SARVIZZA, WALPO,</hi> and <hi>BOSNETH.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Beſides all theſe great Rivers there are ſome others mentioned by <hi>Pliny</hi> which he calls <hi>Fluvii non ignobiles,</hi> no inconſiderable Rivers. By <hi>Jeni</hi> or <hi>Nova Palenka,</hi> runs the River of <hi>Sarviz za</hi> otherwiſe called <hi>Vrpanus<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> which hath its ſource cloſe by <hi>Weſprin,</hi> and having run by <hi>Alba Regalis,</hi> makes a Trian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle with <hi>Buda</hi> and <hi>Gran,</hi> and then falls into the <hi>Danube.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By <hi>Walcover</hi> alſo runs the River of <hi>Walpo</hi> or <hi>Vulpanus,</hi> which hath its head above the Town of <hi>Walpo,</hi> that was taken by <hi>Solyman</hi> upon his March to <hi>Alba Regalis</hi> or <hi>Stoel-Weiſſenbourg.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As to the River <hi>Boſneth</hi> or <hi>Bacuntus,</hi> it hath its ſource near Mount <hi>Arpataro</hi> or <hi>Almus,</hi> and falls into the River of <hi>Sau,</hi> near to the Ancient <hi>Sirmium</hi> that ſtands upon its bank.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:34980:42"/>
               <head>CHAP. IX.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p> Of the Diviſion of the Kingdom of <hi>Hungary,</hi> into Counties, and their Names.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>WE have ſaid before, that the Kingdom of <hi>Hungary</hi> is divid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into Counties as well as <hi>England</hi> is. Theſe Counties are the parts of the Kingdom, which are called Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and by the <hi>Greeks</hi> Monarchies, and the Lords who are Counts of them, have the juriſdiction therein; it having been for the more eaſie and exact Adminiſtration thereof, that the <hi>Hungarians</hi> thought fit to make that diviſion. The Soveraignty of part of theſe Counties is at preſent lodged in his Imperial Majeſty, as King of <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary;</hi> and the other is uſurped by the <hi>Turks:</hi> The Counties ſubject to the King of <hi>Hungary,</hi> are theſe that follow.</p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <pb n="82" facs="tcp:34980:43"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>Counties.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">Comitatus.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Abanviver,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Abanvivarienſis.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Avra,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Arvenſis.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Barzod,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Barzodienſis.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Kalo,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Bihorienſis.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Biſtricz,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Biſtricenſis.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Sarwar,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Caſtriferrenſis.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Czepufs,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Cepuzienſis.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Comara,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Comarienſis.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Gewynar,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Geuinarienſis.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Gewer,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Javarenſis.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Gran,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Strigonienſis.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Lypzce,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Liptovienſis.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Marmarue,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Marmarovienſis.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Mauzon,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Muſovienſis.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Neytracht,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Nitrienſis.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Novigrad,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Novigradenſis.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Peretzaz,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Peregienſis.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Poſon,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Poſonienſis.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Kreiſs,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Riſienſis.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Sellia,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Saronienſis.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Saroz,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Sarienſis.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Semlyn,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Selminienſis.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Sopron,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Sopronienſis.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Torna,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Tornenſis.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Tranſchyn,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Tranchinienſis.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Ovar,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Turocenſis.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>aſdin,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Varaſdienſis.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <pb n="83" facs="tcp:34980:43"/>Veſprim,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Veſprimienſis.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Ugoza,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Ugoghenſis.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Ungwar,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Ungenſis.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Zagrabia,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Zagrabienſis.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Zalawar,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Zaladienſis.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Zatmar,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Zalmarienſis.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Zolnock,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Zolnocenſis.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label" cols="2">The Counties ſubdued by the <hi>Turks.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Ekekes Feierwar,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Albenſis.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Barananyvar,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Baranienſis.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Bars,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Barſenſis.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Bath,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Bathienſis.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Bodrogh,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Bodrogenſis.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Chanad,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Chanadicenſis.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Chege,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Zabolienſis.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Hewecz,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Heweſenſis.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Sag,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Hontenſis.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Czongrad,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Orodienſis.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Peloycz,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Pelyſienſis.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Peſth,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Peſthenſis.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Poſega,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Poſegienſis.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Szygeth,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Sigetenſis.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Zegzard,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Simigienſis.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Szerem,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Sirmienſis.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Temeſwar,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Temeſvenſis.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Tolna,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Tolnenſis.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Thurtur,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Torantalienſis.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Valpon.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Valkonienſis.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:34980:44"/>
               <head>CHAP. X.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p> The Eſtates of <hi>Hungary.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE Eſtates of <hi>Hungary</hi> conſiſts of four Orders. 1. The Biſhops and Clergy. 2. The Barons and Lords, amongſt whom are comprehended the Palatin of <hi>Hungary,</hi> the Ban of <hi>Scla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vonia,</hi> and the Hereditary Counts of Provinces. 3. The Gentry, whether they have Inheritances or not, and thoſe newly enobled by the Prince, for which the Patents ought to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented in ſome of the Counties when they have their particular Meetings, for the holding of the Convention of the Eſtates. 4. The free and Royal Towns.</p>
               <list>
                  <head>In the Eſtate of the Clergy, which makes the firſt, are rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned,</head>
                  <item ana="#role_LABEL">The Arch-biſhop of <hi>Gran,</hi> and his Suffragans, who are,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:34980:44"/>
                     <list>
                        <item>The Biſhop of <hi>Agria,</hi> Chancellor of <hi>Hungary.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>The Biſhop of <hi>Nitra.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>The Biſhop of <hi>Raab.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>The Biſhop of <hi>Vaccia.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>The Biſhop of <hi>Five-Churches.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>The Biſhop of <hi>Veſprim,</hi> Chancellor to the Queen.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item ana="#role_LABEL"> The Arch-biſhop of <hi>Colocza;</hi> whoſe Suffragans are:
<list>
                        <item>The Biſhop of <hi>Zagrabia</hi> or <hi>Agram.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>The Biſhop of <hi>Waradin.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>The Biſhop of <hi>Szerem.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>The Biſhop of <hi>Alba Julia</hi> in <hi>Tranſilva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vania.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>The Biſhop of <hi>Chenad.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>The Biſhop of <hi>Boſne.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>The Biſhop of <hi>Poſega</hi> in <hi>Sclavonia.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:34980:45"/>
               <head>CHAP. XI.</head>
               <list>
                  <head> The chief Palatin Nobility of <hi>Hungary.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>BAthory</hi> Princes of <hi>Tranſilvania,</hi> Counts of <hi>Schepuſe.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Bothlen Falva,</hi> Counts of <hi>Schepuſe.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Bubeck</hi> of <hi>Peſſevez.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Budiani,</hi> Counts.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Draskowich</hi> Counts of <hi>Tracoſthian.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Drugeth</hi> of <hi>Homonay.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Eſdrin</hi> Counts of <hi>Serini.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Eſterhazi,</hi> of <hi>Galanta,</hi> Counts of <hi>Frack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no</hi> and <hi>Sopronia.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Fergatz,</hi> Counts of <hi>Nograd, Saros</hi> and <hi>Sabol.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Gara.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Gareb,</hi> Counts of <hi>Windgradt.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Hedervara.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Illeſhazi,</hi> Counts of <hi>Lipton,</hi> and <hi>Trin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chin.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ilſua,</hi> Counts of <hi>Alba.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Kaonth.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Nadaſti,</hi> Counts of <hi>Pochenedioz.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Orſag</hi> of <hi>Guth.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Palfy,</hi> Counts of <hi>Erdend.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:34980:45"/>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Paſman,</hi> Counts of <hi>Paves.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Paſzta.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Poloch.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Poth,</hi> Barons of <hi>Hederwara,</hi> Counts of <hi>Simigin.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Privi,</hi> Counts of <hi>Viwar.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Revay,</hi> Counts of <hi>Turocz.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Rothal,</hi> Counts.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Schaſgotz,</hi> Counts.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Seech,</hi> Counts of <hi>Seech.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Teckely,</hi> Counts.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Weſſeleny</hi> of <hi>Hadad</hi> Counts of <hi>Muran, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mora, Peſt,</hi> and <hi>Pilis.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Zapolya,</hi> Counts of <hi>Scepuſe.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Zacky,</hi> Counts.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>The Counts and Barons who were at the Diet of <hi>1660.</hi> at Presbourg, were of the following Families.</head>
                  <item>Baſtian.</item>
                  <item>Balaſſa.</item>
                  <item>Berchery.</item>
                  <item>Boſſangi.</item>
                  <item>Boſckai.</item>
                  <item>Beirber.</item>
                  <item>Beringi.</item>
                  <item>Chaki.</item>
                  <item>Czobor.</item>
                  <item>Caroli.</item>
                  <item>Cikani.</item>
                  <item>Druget.</item>
                  <item>Dhomonaia.</item>
                  <item>Draſcowitz.</item>
                  <item>Eſterhaſi.</item>
                  <item>Erdoeidi.</item>
                  <item>Forgach.</item>
                  <item>Frangipani.</item>
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:34980:46"/>
                  <item>Franczi.</item>
                  <item>Herdewara.</item>
                  <item>Horwaths.</item>
                  <item>Horeski.</item>
                  <item>Jakwich.</item>
                  <item>Illeshaſi.</item>
                  <item>Keri.</item>
                  <item>Klegowits.</item>
                  <item>Kemeni.</item>
                  <item>Kara.</item>
                  <item>Kapi.</item>
                  <item>Koloniſch.</item>
                  <item>Konski.</item>
                  <item>Kokarch.</item>
                  <item>Liſtius.</item>
                  <item>Lippa.</item>
                  <item>Melith.</item>
                  <item>Meggeri.</item>
                  <item>Maitingi.</item>
                  <item>Megiſai.</item>
                  <item>Malakoſi.</item>
                  <item>Nadaſti.</item>
                  <item>Niari.</item>
                  <item>Nodani.</item>
                  <item>Ozacki.</item>
                  <item>Orchoci.</item>
                  <item>Oſtronſien.</item>
                  <item>Palfi.</item>
                  <item>Paſmani.</item>
                  <item>Prengi.</item>
                  <item>Pafkay.</item>
                  <item>Petroci.</item>
                  <item>Poloczi.</item>
                  <item>Pongrato.</item>
                  <item>Pongrangi.</item>
                  <item>Petreo.</item>
                  <item>Ragotski.</item>
                  <item>Revai.</item>
                  <item>Rothal.</item>
                  <item>Schezi.</item>
                  <item>Sekengi.</item>
                  <item>Scengici.</item>
                  <item>Szaniogh.</item>
                  <item>Telegki.</item>
                  <item>Weſeleni.</item>
                  <item>Wicay.</item>
                  <item>Zichi.</item>
                  <item>Zrin.</item>
                  <item>Zahi.</item>
                  <item>Zengchi.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Some of theſe Families are extinct ſince the late Wars.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:34980:46"/>
               <head>CHAP. XII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p> Of the State of the Palatin of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Hungary,</hi> his Quality, Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and Preheminence, with a Liſt of thoſe who in this laſt Age have been Elected to that Office.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE chief Dignity of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom next to the King, is that of <hi>Palatin,</hi> who calls the Eſtates during an Inter-reigne, and who hath the firſt and moſt powerful voice in the Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the King. He alſo decides the controverſies that happen betwixt the King and his Subjects, ſince the Kings there are ſubject to the Laws, and muſt not Tranſgreſs them. He hath abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Power in the Armies, ſo that he can puniſh and reward all, as he thinks good, and beſtow aſmuch Land as Twenty or Thirty men are able to Labour. He hath great Revenues, not only from the Salt-pits, but from other things alſo; and heretofore he had the Rents of the two Iſles on the Coaſt
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:34980:47"/> of <hi>Dalmatia,</hi> which now are poſſeſſed by the <hi>Venetians.</hi> In ſhort, ſo great is his Authority, that right or wrong the <hi>Hungarians</hi> obey his Will, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low his Reſolutions; and it is a Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that cannot be given to Strangers, but belongs only to the <hi>Hungarians,</hi> who many times oppoſe their King by means of that Magiſtrate. It is not an Hereditary but Elective Office. Here I ſhall mention thoſe who in this laſt Age have been Choſen to that Dignity.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Stephen Illiſhazi</hi> Count of <hi>Trenſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chin,</hi> Palatine of <hi>Hungary,</hi> choſen in the year 1601. died at <hi>Vienna</hi> the 26. of <hi>May</hi> 1609.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>George Turſo</hi> Palatine of <hi>Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> choſen the Seventh of <hi>December,</hi> 1609.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Sigiſmond Forgatz,</hi> of <hi>Guymes,</hi> 1619.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Nicholas</hi> Count of <hi>Eſterhazi</hi> of <hi>Galantha</hi> and <hi>Frakno,</hi> Palatine of the Kingdom of <hi>Hungary,</hi> made Knight of the Golden Fleece, in the year 1628. Deceaſed in the year 1645.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Nicholas Draskowich</hi> Count of <hi>Trakoſtyan,</hi> and of the County of <hi>Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſovia,</hi> Gentleman of the Bed Chamber
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:34980:47"/> to his Imperial Majeſty, in his Royal Court of <hi>Hungary,</hi> choſen Palatine in 1646. he died the Ninth of <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1648.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Paul Palfi</hi> Count of <hi>Erbent,</hi> and <hi>Plaffenſtein,</hi> Palatine of the Kingdom of <hi>Hungary,</hi> was made Knight of the Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Fleece in the year 1650. he died in 1654.</p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>Francis</hi> Count <hi>Weſſelini</hi> of <hi>Hadad,</hi> Hereditary of <hi>Muran,</hi> Palatine of <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary,</hi> made Knight of the Order of the Golden Fleece in the year 1662. he died in 1667.</p>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>Paul</hi> Count of <hi>Eſterhazi, Galan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha, Frackno,</hi> and <hi>Sopronica,</hi> Palatine of <hi>Hungary,</hi> made Knight of the Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Fleece, in the year 1682. Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellor and Chamberlain to the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror in his Royal Court of <hi>Hungary,</hi> at preſent Palatine of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:34980:48"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p> Of the Arms of the Kingdom of <hi>Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> and in what manner the Kings have born them.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE Kingdom of <hi>Hungary</hi> bears Barry of eight pieces <hi>Argent</hi> and <hi>Gules.</hi> Prince <hi>Sigiſmond</hi> King of <hi>Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia</hi> having Married <hi>Mary</hi> Daughter and Heireſs of <hi>Loüis</hi> of <hi>Hungary,</hi> was in right of her King of <hi>Hungary,</hi> and afterwards Emperor. He joyned the Arms of <hi>Hungary</hi> and <hi>Bohemia,</hi> which he bore upon the Eagle of the Empire, empaling thoſe of <hi>Hungary,</hi> with a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Croſs of St. <hi>Stephen,</hi> which is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved with his Coat of Arms and Sword, uſed in the Ceremony of the Coronation of theſe Kings. In his Coyn of Gold there is a Reverſe of the Globe of the Earth, Crowned with an Imperial Crown, which the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours at preſent place over their Arms.</p>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:34980:48"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>John</hi> and <hi>Matthias Corvinus,</hi> who were Kings after him, bore quarterly the Arms of <hi>Hungary,</hi> the Croſs of St. <hi>Stephen;</hi> thoſe of <hi>Dalmatia,</hi> and <hi>Bohemia,</hi> and upon all thoſe, the Arms of <hi>Corvin.</hi> In this manner they have been found upon a Prayer Book in Velom, which belonged to <hi>Matthias Corvinus,</hi> and is kept in the <hi>Bibliotheke</hi> of the <hi>Vatican.</hi> On the firſt page they are diſpoſed in this manner, quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly. 1. <hi>Hungary,</hi> Barry <hi>Argent</hi> and <hi>Gules.</hi> 2. <hi>Gules</hi> a Croſs double <hi>Argent</hi> placed upon a Tuff of Earth <hi>vert,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of three little Hills. 3. <hi>Dalma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia, Azure</hi> three Leopards Heads cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped and Crowned <hi>Or.</hi> 4. <hi>Bohemia, Gules,</hi> a Lion <hi>Argent</hi> his tail forked, nowed, and paſſed in <hi>Saltier,</hi> Crown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed langued and Armed <hi>Or,</hi> upon all the Arms of <hi>Corvin,</hi> which is <hi>Or,</hi> a Crow conturned Sable, the head re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning back to the right-hand, in his Beak a double long Croſs placed in Bend. <hi>Loüis</hi> King of <hi>Hungary</hi> Knight of the Golden Fleece, Son of <hi>Ladi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlaus</hi> King of <hi>Hungary</hi> and <hi>Bohemia,</hi> bore quarterly the 1. and 4. <hi>Hungary,</hi> the 2. and 3. <hi>Bohemia, Gules</hi> a Lion
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:34980:49"/> 
                  <hi>Argent,</hi> with a double tail, langued, and Armed <hi>Or,</hi> upon theſe the Arms of <hi>Poland.</hi> The Helmet Crowned <hi>Or,</hi> and the creſt an Eagle naſcent.</p>
               <p>After them, this Kingdom entered into the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> which joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Arms of both together. The Arch-Dukes, who have born ſo many Quarterings in their Eſcutcheons, have born a chief empaling <hi>Hungary</hi> and <hi>Bohemia. Ferdinand</hi> the Brother of <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth, King of the <hi>Romans,</hi> and afterwards Emperor, bore a great Eſcutcheon quartered of <hi>Hungary</hi> and <hi>Bohemia;</hi> upon which he placed ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther leſs Eſcutcheon, quarterly upon the 1. <hi>Auſtria</hi> and Ancient <hi>Burgun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy</hi> empaled. 2. Quarterly of <hi>Caſtille</hi> and <hi>Leon:</hi> Upon the 3. <hi>Arragon</hi> em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paled with <hi>Sicily:</hi> Upon the 4. <hi>partie per feſs, Lorrain</hi> upon <hi>Brabant.</hi> Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all another little Eſcutcheon em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paling <hi>Guelders</hi> and <hi>Juliers,</hi> two Lions confronting one another, the Eagle of the Empire was diſplayed behind the great Eſcutcheon encompaſſed with a Collar of the Order of the Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Fleece.</p>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:34980:49"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rodolph,</hi> II. during the Diet of <hi>Auſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourg,</hi> coyned a piece of Silver or Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal, in the Middle whereof was the Eagle of the Empire Crowned with an <hi>Imperial</hi> Crown, and collered with an open Crown ſupporting an Eſcutche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on quarterly of <hi>Hungary</hi> and <hi>Bohemia,</hi> with another over all, empaleing <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria</hi> and Ancient <hi>Burgundy:</hi> About this Medal or Coin, inſtead of an Inſcription, were Four and Twenty little Eſcutcheons of the Arms of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtillo, Leon, Arragon, Sicily, Granada, Carniola, Carinthia, Swabia, Cellem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourgh, Braganza,</hi> the Mark of <hi>Scla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vonia, Portuan, Habſbourg, Tyrol, Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant, Flanders, Nybourg, Alſatia, Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> the Mark of the Holy Empire, or <hi>Antwerp, Croatia, Sclavonia,</hi> and <hi>Dal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>One may judge how much in the progreſs of time, the Kings of <hi>Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> enlarged their Country, not ſo much by what may be found in Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, as by what is to be ſeen at their Coronation. For there are Twelve of the Chief of the Kingdom, who carry each of them a Banner, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in are repreſented the Arms of
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:34980:50"/> Ten Provinces of that Kingdom, which are,
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Hungary.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Dalmatia, Vert.</hi> Three Leopards Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: <hi>Or.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Croatia,</hi> Chequey <hi>Argent</hi> and <hi>Gules</hi> of Eight Ranges.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Sclavonia: Or,</hi> a Cardinals Cap <hi>Sable,</hi> bordered <hi>Gules,</hi> the Strings Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant of the ſame.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Galicia.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ruſſia:</hi> Sables, a Portal open, with an Aſcent of two Steps, <hi>Or.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Servia.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Bulgaria.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Boſnia: Azure,</hi> an Arm armed <hi>Or,</hi> holding in the hand a Sword <hi>Argent,</hi> the point upwards.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ludormiria.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:34980:50"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p> Of the Memorable Battels that have been fought in <hi>Hungary.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>ROMAN BATTLES.</head>
                  <p>THE Inhabitants of <hi>Hungary</hi> have had in Ages paſt many Bruſhes with the <hi>Romans,</hi> and fought ſeveral Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles with them: that which was given in the Neighbourhood of <hi>Adom,</hi> a Town of the Lower <hi>Hungary,</hi> upon the Bank of the <hi>Danube,</hi> was one of the Bloodieſt. The occaſion of it was, that at that time the <hi>Romans</hi> came to Seize the Country under the Conduct of <hi>Mocrinus</hi> and <hi>Tetricus,</hi> but there they received an utter overthrow.</p>
                  <p>Some time after the Inhabitants of <hi>Hungary</hi> having recollected their For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, gave the <hi>Romans</hi> a Second Battle in the precincts of <hi>Solna,</hi> wherein they again obtained the Victory, and drove out the <hi>Romans,</hi> though they loſt on their ſide above Forty thouſand of their own Souldiers.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="98" facs="tcp:34980:51"/>
                  <head>THE BATTLE OF MOHACZ.</head>
                  <p>THAT unhappy Battle, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <hi>Loüis</hi> King of <hi>Hungary</hi> loſt his Life, was fought the 30th. of <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1526. in the plain of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hacz,</hi> a little Town of the Lower <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary</hi> upon the River called <hi>Caraſſe,</hi> cloſe by the <hi>Danube,</hi> betwixt <hi>Boteſk</hi> and <hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeck. Solyman,</hi> Emperor of the <hi>Turks,</hi> being come into <hi>Hungary,</hi> with a pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful Army; the Chief Commanders of the <hi>Hungarian</hi> Army perſwaded the young King, who being hardly Twenty years of Age, was much wanting in Conduct, and had not For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſufficient to make head againſt the <hi>Turks,</hi> to give them Battle, without ſtaying for the Succors that were to come to him from <hi>Tranſilvania:</hi>
                     <pb n="99" facs="tcp:34980:51"/> They were puffed up with their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Victories, and ſo ſwollen with a good Conceit of themſelves, that they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hought none were able to ſtand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, and that their Reſerved<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs might make the <hi>Hungarians</hi> enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ain a bad opinion of the reſolution of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>heir Army. The Event anſwered <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he raſhneſs of that Counſel; for that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ovely Army of the <hi>Hungarians,</hi> conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ng of the beſt part of the Nobility, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd chief Forces of the Kingdom, was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>outed and cut in pieces: The King was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ot killed in the Fight; but his Horſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hrew him into a Mire, where he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tuck, and died, after he had for a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ong time fought Valiantly with the <hi>Barbarians</hi> on the other ſide of the Town. His Body was found two Months after the Battle, in the River <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f <hi>Czelepatuka,</hi> and was interred in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he Burying-place of the Kings, in the City of <hi>Alba Regalis.</hi> That unhappy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>efeat of the Chriſtians, and that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ictory of the <hi>Turks,</hi> occaſioned in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>equel the loſs of the chief part of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ingdom of <hi>Hungary:</hi> The Biſhops <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hemſelves aſwell as the reſt of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he Clergy, made it apparent
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:34980:52"/> in that Battle, that they were very good Soldiers for the common Cauſe of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom;</hi> for no fewer than ſix Biſhops were killed in that fatal Overthrow, and amongſt them <hi>Paul Tomorie</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Colocza,</hi> one of the chief who had adviſed the King to engage in that Battle: His Head was carried to <hi>Soly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> who called it a fooliſh Head, and incapable of giving its Maſter good Council. This is the Inſcription that was made in memory of that fatal day.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ludovicus</hi> ſolo nomine ſecundus,</l>
                     <l>Ad coronas natus, non formatus</l>
                     <l>Diadema Hungaricum ſecundo, quarto aetatis Bohemicum,</l>
                     <l>Ut Immaturus acquiſivit.</l>
                     <l>Ita maturè ſecum utrumque perdidit;</l>
                     <l>Foelicior, ſi ſolus perire potuiſſet.</l>
                     <l>Eandem tamen cum Rege fatalis urna ſortem</l>
                     <l>Experire coacta Hungaria,</l>
                     <l>Ducenta ſuorum millia eodem luctu deplora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit:</l>
                     <l>Luctuoſum praeviſorum malorum initium,</l>
                     <l>Lachrymabile futurorum dolorum argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum.</l>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:34980:52"/>
                  <head>THE BATTLE OF S. GODARD.</head>
                  <p>THis Battle was fought the firſt of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> in the year, 1664. at St. <hi>Godard,</hi> betwixt <hi>Kermin</hi> and <hi>Caniſa,</hi> in the Lower <hi>Hungary.</hi> In this place, one half of the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Army paſſed the River of <hi>Raab,</hi> to attack the <hi>Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rialiſts;</hi> but hardly were theſe Troops got over the River, when, without gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them time to entrench themſelves, the <hi>Imperial</hi> Forces under the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of General <hi>Montecuculi,</hi> being drawn up to receive them, forced them to fight, and utterly defeated the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt part of the <hi>Turks;</hi> the reſt betook themſelves ſhamefully to flight, who crowding in great haſte to re-paſs the River, threw themſelves head-long in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Water, and were carried away by the Stream; ſo that the Rapidity of
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:34980:53"/> the River, forcing along with it Men and Horſes, they were drowned in the deepeſt places; it being certain that more periſhed in the Water, than by the Sword: And the <hi>Turks</hi> themſelves acknowledged, that they loſt many more Men, than the <hi>Gazets</hi> of <hi>Europe</hi> mentioned. To which they added, that their Hiſtories did not ſpeak of ſo great and ſo ſhameful a Diſgrace happened to the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Empire, ſince it had attained to ſo high a degree of Power, as that Diſaſter was. The <hi>Turks</hi> left above Eight Thouſand Men upon the place, and the Glory of the day to the <hi>Imperialiſts,</hi> which was imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately followed by a Peace, that the <hi>Turks</hi> propoſed, and greedily embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced; of which theſe were the Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. That <hi>Tranſilvania</hi> ſhould conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue within its ancient Limits, and with its ancient Priviledges, under the Command of Prince <hi>Michael Abaffi.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. That the Emperour of <hi>Germany</hi> ſhould have Liberty to fortifie <hi>Gutta</hi> and <hi>Nitra.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <pb n="103" facs="tcp:34980:53"/>
                     <item>3. That the <hi>Turks</hi> ſhould make no In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novation in the Regulation made for the Frontiers, as well of <hi>Hungary,</hi> as of the other Territories of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour.</item>
                     <item>4. That <hi>Abaffi</hi> ſhould pay ſix hundred Thouſand Crowns to the Port, for the Charges of the War.</item>
                     <item>5. That all Acts of Hoſtility, betwixt the Emperour and <hi>Grand Signior,</hi> and their Subjects, ſhould for ever ceaſe.</item>
                     <item>6. That the two Provinces of <hi>Zatmar,</hi> and <hi>Zaboli,</hi> given to <hi>Ragotzi</hi> for Life, ſhould again return to his Imperial Majeſty, and neither the Prince of <hi>Tranſilvania,</hi> nor the <hi>Grand Signior</hi> pretend any Right to them.</item>
                     <item>7. That the ſtrong Caſtle of <hi>Zechel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hyd</hi> which revolted from the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, ſhould be demoliſhed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe neither Party would renounce their Pretentions to ſo important a place.</item>
                     <pb n="104" facs="tcp:34980:54"/>
                     <item>8. That <hi>Waradin</hi> and <hi>Newheuſel</hi> ſhould remain in the Poſſeſſion of the <hi>Turks,</hi> who had carried them by their Arms.</item>
                     <item>9. That for Confirmation of the Peace, the two Emperours ſhould ſend Ambaſſadours to one another, with reciprocal Preſents of equal value.</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:34980:54"/>
                  <head>THE BATTLE AND RELIEF OF VIENNA. The 12th. of <hi>September,</hi> 1683.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>Inſtead of a Deſcription of that happy day; I ſhall here publiſh the Letter of the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> written in Latin, the Day after the Battle, to the <hi>Marqueſs</hi> of <hi>Grana,</hi> then Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> with the Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof; nothing being more Authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick than the Contents of it.</p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>JOHN III. <hi>By the Grace of God, King of</hi> Poland, <hi>Great Duke of</hi> Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuania, Ruſſia, Pruſſia, Maſſovia, Samogitia, Livonia, Kiovia, Vol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinia, Podolia, Poldachia, Smalen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcia, Severia, <hi>and</hi> Czernihovia.</p>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div type="parallel_text">
                              <p>ILluſt<hi rend="sup">me.</hi> grate nobis dilecte.
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:34980:55"/> Vocati in ſubſidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um periclitantis Viennae, lectis con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtim militari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Copiis quam anguſti temporis ſpatio priùs via<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum incommoda, diſtantiam loci, &amp; ripas Danubij, demum cacumina montium &amp; ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus ſylvarum Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ennenſium ſupera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verimus, famam diſtuliſſe non du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitamus. Nobis vel id Illuſtritati Veſtrae referre pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet, quòd ſine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juria communis Chriſtianorum ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latij reticere non poſſumus. Deo auſpice, Comite Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reniſſimorum
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:34980:55"/> Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipum, Ducum, &amp; Electorum Fortunâ, Chriſtiani Exercitus, quorum nobis cuncti detulerant Imperium, die heſternâ in Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pis praeſentibus inſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem &amp; ſaeculis memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randam de Turcis, &amp; Tartaris reportarunt Victoriam. Magnus quippe Turcarum Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirus integris Orientis &amp; Hanni Crimenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um ſuperbus viribus, jam non Viennae dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taxat intra triduum (ni ſubventum fuiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet) periturae, ſed uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſae Chriſtianitatis ſpem deglutiens, acie, &amp; praelio unius diei coeſus, atque fugatus eſt. Peditatus vulgò
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:34980:56"/> Janiſſeri, utpote tardior militia, ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qualique cum Eque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribus fugae inſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciens, in Caſtris de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerta, &amp; Victorum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licta diſcretioni. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra ipſa longitudinem &amp; latitudinem duo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ferè milliarium exaequantia, capta, Tormenta atque inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gra res tormentaria cum opimis ſpoliis in praemium victricium ceſſêre armorum. Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enna gravi obſidione, &amp; extremis liberata periculis, ſuaque ſedes reddita Caeſari. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>l<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriori Victoriae mox metam poſuit, ac turpi fugâ ſeſe recipienti hoſte terrore panico in Pannoniam mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrante
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:34980:56"/> viam, um<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bra fuit beneficium. Inſidet nihilominus tergo illius levior noſtra militia; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficienteſque in viâ partim caedit; par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim in captivitatem abducit. Porrò &amp; ipſi in Dei nomine eidem inſiſtimus vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctoriae, non priùs de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituri, donec, ſi ita propitiis viſum fue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit Superis, hoſtili in terra armis Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianis ſtativa pate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant hyberna. Tali itaque rerum Otto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manicarum ſub-ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tâ confuſione, ſi quid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piam aliquando Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ropae vires ubique promptis accinctae ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis dignum Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ano
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:34980:57"/> nomine auder<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap> contendant, nunquam opportuniora rerum momenta praeſentibus nanciſci poterunt; Si namque ad clangorem memoratae Victoriae, vel levis armorum ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>râ marique ſuccedat oſtentatio, proculdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bio gemens ſub tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nide Graecia, ac ipſa Conſtantinopolis per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fido recalcitraret Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mino, ad ſuaſque reſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceret origines. Idem de Epiro, Macedoniâ, Boſniâ, Bulgariâ, Dal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiâ, Valachiâ, Mol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daviâ, aliiſque Regnis &amp; Provinciis raptis credendum, prout non levia praemiſſorum ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bemus indicia: fortè jam &amp; illam conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuam
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:34980:57"/> rerum huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narum Mahometano Imperio ſupereſſe vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſſitudinem, ut poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam ab exiguis pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectum initiis eò cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verit, ut magnitudine ſuâ laboret, rurſus vertente fato &amp; vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lubilis fortunae rotâ aliò inclinante, ad ſua devolvatur prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipia &amp; ubi ſatis in altum ſurrexerit, lap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu graviori ru at: Sed his omnibus ſupremo Imperiorum Regno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rumque Arbitrio reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis. De Illuſtritate Veſtrâ omnino perſuaſi ſumus, habere illam tantum pietatis &amp; ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neroſiſſimae mentis in res Chriſtianas, ut non ſolùm felicibus hiſce
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:34980:58"/> congaudeat ſucceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, ſed eos communes ſibi aliquando faciat, nullaſque ad mutua Chriſtianitatis incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moda intermittat oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſiones. Quod dum profundiſſimis inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minamus deſideriis, optimam Illuſtritati Veſtrae cum proſpero re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſucceſſu precamur valetudinem. Daba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur in Caſtris Turcicis in Tentoriis Viſiriis ad Viennam die <hi>13.</hi> menſis Septemb. anno Dom. <hi>1683.</hi> Regni noſtri <hi>X.</hi> Anno.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div type="parallel_text">
                              <p>MOST Illuſtrious Lord, and moſt dear to us. Being
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:34980:55"/> called to the relief of <hi>Vienna,</hi> which was in danger of being loſt, we make no doubt, but that you have been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Report, in how ſhort a time, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties and length of the way, we came to the Banks of the <hi>Danube,</hi> ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounted the tops of Mountains, and croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Forreſts of <hi>Vienna,</hi> with Forces that we raiſed in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence; but with Pleaſure now we ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint your Illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Lordſhip with that which we cannot conceal without pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Conſolation of Chriſtendom. Know then that Yeſterday the Chriſtian Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, the command whereof was by all given to us, fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing under the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of God; and
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:34980:55"/> aſſiſted by the good Fortune of the Princes, ann Dukes and Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, obtained in the Camp where we are, a ſignal Victory and Memorable to all poſterity, over the <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Tartars.</hi> For the <hi>Grand Viſier</hi> of the <hi>Turks</hi> proud with the Forces of all the Eaſt and of the <hi>Crim Tartars,</hi> and think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of nothing leſs than ſwallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up not only <hi>Vienna,</hi> which in three days ſpace muſt have periſhed (had it not been reliev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) but alſo all Chriſtendom, is in one days fight overthrown and put to flight. The Infantry, whom they call <hi>Jani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries,</hi> not being able to fly ſo
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:34980:56"/> nimbly as the Horſe, ſeeing they are ſlower and more peſtered, were left in the Camp, and aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion of the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorious. Their Camp, which took up near two <hi>German</hi> miles in <hi>length,</hi> and as much in breadth, was taken, their Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non, Ammuniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, with rich ſpoils became the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of the victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Armies. <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enna</hi> is relieved from a dreadful Siege, and immi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent dangers, and the Emperour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain reſtored to the place of his Reſidence. The Night put a ſtop to the courſe of the Victory, and Darkneſs favoured the Ignominious flight of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy, who ſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:34980:56"/> with a Panick Fear is retreated towards <hi>Hungary.</hi> Our Light Horſe, nevertheleſs pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue them at the Heels, and kill or make Priſoners all whom they over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take in the way. We, moreover, in the name of God purſue the ſame Victory, being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt, untill (if kind Heaven ſo think fit) we have opened for the Chriſtian Armies Winter quarters in the Enemies Country. And ſuch at preſent is the Confuſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>on of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, that if the Princes of Europe, will ſpeedily Arm and undertake ſomewhat worthy of the Chriſtian Name, a more favourable Jun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture than this
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:34980:57"/> can never be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered unto them; for if the News of this Victory were ſeconded by ſome ſhew of arm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by Land and by Sea, there is no doubt but <hi>Greece,</hi> that groans under the Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny of an U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurper, and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople</hi> it ſelf would revolt from their perfidious Maſter, and endea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vor to reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver their priſtine-Liberty. Upon no ſlight grounds we may aſſert the ſame thing of <hi>Epyrus, Macedonia, Boſnia, Bulgaria, Dalma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia, Valachia, Mol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>davia,</hi> and other Kingdoms and Provinces that have been ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued by the <hi>Turks.</hi> Perhaps, alſo the <hi>Mahometan</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, may now have a tryal of
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:34980:57"/> the viciſſitude of Humane Affairs, and from ſmall Beginnings being grown ſo great, that it labours under its own weight, by a change of Fate and a turn of the Wheel of fickle Fortune, it may relapſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to its Original, and from ſo high an Elevation have a greater fall. But all theſe things are to be left to the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Will and Pleaſure of Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pires and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms. As for your Illuſtrious Lordſhip, we are fully perſwaded that you have ſo great Piety and ſuch Generous In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations towards the concerns of Chriſtianity, that you will not on<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly congratulate
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:34980:58"/> theſe happy ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes; but one day alſo contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moting of the ſame, and omit no Occaſion of furthering the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom.</hi> This we deſire from the bottom of our Heart, praying God to give your Illuſtrious Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip perfect health and all ſort of Proſperity. From the Tent of the <hi>Grand Viſier,</hi> in the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Camp before <hi>Vienna</hi> the 13. <hi>Septemb.</hi> 1683. and the Tenth Year of our Reign.</p>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <p>Upon occaſion of this great Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, the following Chronogram was publiſhed.</p>
                  <q>aVſtrIaCo aVXILIVM DeVS.</q>
                  <p>And it was the Subject of a Medal, which was made repreſenting a double
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:34980:58"/> ſpread Eagle upon the Globe of the World looking to the Sun, with this Inſcription, <hi>Colliget Auxilii radios,</hi> and having in its Tallons a Sword and Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: About the Globe was this Mot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, <hi>Sub umbrâ alarum tuarum,</hi> and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneath this, the Creſcent reverſed, with this Hemiſtich, <hi>Victamque rede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>git in umbras.</hi> And in the circumfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of the Medal, this Verſe:
<q>Imperii murum Auſtriaco interponit inorbe.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>On the Reverſe theſe Words were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graven.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>1683.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Die <hi>14.</hi> Julii</l>
                     <l>Vienna Auſtriae</l>
                     <l>A Turcis obſeſſa,</l>
                     <l>Sed Protectore altiſſimo,</l>
                     <l>Leopoldi Imperatoris induſtriae conſilio,</l>
                     <l>Regis Poloniae Joannis <hi>III.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Preſentis valido Auxilio.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>On the one ſide was Written.
<q>
                        <l>In Perſo. Seren. Electoris Bavari, Saxon:</l>
                        <l>Et Imperi ſubſidio Comit. Caplieres Deput. Praeſidente.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="114" facs="tcp:34980:59"/>
                  <p>And on the other:
<q>Duce Lotharingio Caeſaris locum tenente Generali, Comite Starembergio Viennae.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>And underneath all theſe Writings was what follows:
<q>
                        <l>Viennenſium denique Univerſitatis Senatus,</l>
                        <l>Officialium, Civium ac incolarum concordi obſequio, ab obſidione</l>
                        <l>Profligato hoſte eodem Anno</l>
                        <l>Die <hi>12.</hi> Septembris liberata.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>There were many Sonnets made upon the ſame Subject in Vulgar Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages to the Honour of the King of <hi>Poland;</hi> but that which was made on him in Latin, very well deſerves a place here.</p>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div type="poem">
                              <head>JOANNI SOBIESCO.</head>
                              <lg>
                                 <l>DOminatione Polonico, Lutuanico;</l>
                                 <l>Liberatione Auſtriaco, Pannonico;</l>
                                 <l>Profligatione Ottomanico, Turcico;</l>
                                 <l>Religione Chriſtianiſſimo;</l>
                                 <pb n="115" facs="tcp:34980:59"/>
                                 <l>Pietate Catholico;</l>
                                 <l>Zelo, &amp; obſequio Apoſtolico.</l>
                                 <l>Inter Reges ſapientiſſimo,</l>
                                 <l>Inter Duces praeſtantiſſimo,</l>
                                 <l>Inter Imperatores, citra fabulas,</l>
                                 <l>Solo nomine tremebundo,</l>
                                 <l>Solo nomine Hoſtes profliganti.</l>
                              </lg>
                              <lg>
                                 <head>CUI</head>
                                 <l>Gloria militaris Regnum peperit,</l>
                                 <l>Clementia firmavit,</l>
                                 <l>Meritum perenabit.</l>
                              </lg>
                              <lg>
                                 <head>QUI</head>
                                 <l>Raro probitatis &amp; conſtantiae exemplo,</l>
                                 <l>Propria deſerens, aliena defendens,</l>
                                 <l>Docuit quo pacto ſancta Jura foederum</l>
                                 <l>Ineantur, excolantur, perficiantur.</l>
                                 <l>Ottomanicam lunam fulgentiſſimo</l>
                                 <l>Crucis vexillo</l>
                                 <l>Aeternam eclypſim minitant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap>m,</l>
                                 <l>Ita properè fortiterque à Chriſtianorum finibus eliminavit,</l>
                                 <l>Ut unum, idemque fuerit</l>
                                 <l>Veniſſe, vidiſſe &amp; viciſſe.</l>
                                 <l>Inter innumeros igitur Chriſtiani orbis plauſus,</l>
                                 <pb n="116" facs="tcp:34980:60"/>
                                 <l>Inter vindicatae Religionis &amp; Imperii Laetitiam,</l>
                                 <l>Inter cruentatae lunae extrema deliquia,</l>
                                 <l>Agnoſcant praeſentes, fateantur poſteri,</l>
                                 <l>Non tantum enaſcenti Evangelio quo promulgaretur,</l>
                                 <l>Sed etiam promulgato ne profligaretur,</l>
                                 <l>Utrobique fuiſſe hominem à Deo miſſum</l>
                                 <l>
                                    <hi>Cui nomen erat</hi> Joannes.</l>
                              </lg>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <p>Now this happy Victory and Relief of <hi>Vienna,</hi> is ſo much the more to be pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, that it is certain, according to the Liſt which was afterwards found in the Grand Viziers Tent, that the Army of the <hi>Turks</hi> which Beſieged it, conſiſted of 191800. men, and the Chriſtian Army only of 81600. The great Standard, the Horſes Tail, and the Grand Viziers own Horſe were taken by the <hi>Poles,</hi> who obſtinatly purſued them in their Retreat, and there was much booty found in the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Camp, which was wholly plundered even to the Tent of the Grand Vizier, where they found great Riches in Gold, Silver, and other pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious things: All their Artillery, which conſiſted of above an hundred pieces
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:34980:60"/> of Cannon, was alſo gained with ſtore of Ammunition.</p>
                  <p>The great Standard we mentioned before, was carried before the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> when he made his entry into <hi>Vienna,</hi> immediately after it was Relieved, and was ſent preſently by that King to the Pope. On the one ſide of it was this Inſcription,
<q>We prophecy to you proſperity and good Succeſs, God Pardon your Sins, and grant you all his grace.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>And on the other ſide.
<q>God Aſſiſt and Bleſs you, and dwell in the Hearts of Believers, that the purity of the Faith may encreaſe therein. Beſides him there is no other God, and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homet</hi> is his Prophet.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>It will not be amiſs here to inſert the Liſt of the great Lords, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the <hi>Imperialiſts,</hi> were preſent at that Battle; of whom the Names follow,
<list>
                        <pb n="118" facs="tcp:34980:61"/>
                        <item>The King of <hi>Poland.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Prince <hi>Alexander</hi> his Son.</item>
                        <item>The Elector of <hi>Bavaria.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>The Elector of <hi>Saxony.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>The Duke of <hi>Lorrain.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Prince <hi>Waldeck.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Two Marqueſſes of <hi>Baden.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Four Dukes of <hi>Saxony.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Three Dukes of <hi>Wittenberg.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>The Prince of <hi>Anhalt.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>The Duke of <hi>Croy.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>The Prince of <hi>Salms.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Two Dukes of <hi>Neubourgh.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>The Marqueſs of <hi>Barreit.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>The Prince of <hi>Hannover.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>The Prince <hi>Lubomirski.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>The Prince of <hi>Savoy.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>The Prince of <hi>Hogen Zoller.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>And ſince the King of <hi>Poland</hi> had ſo great a Hand in this Victory, I hope the Curious will not be diſſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to ſee the League offenſive and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive, which was happily made and concluded in the Month of <hi>April,</hi> 1683. betwixt their <hi>Imperial</hi> and <hi>Polo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian</hi> Majeſties, of which the ſubſtance follows:</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <pb n="119" facs="tcp:34980:61"/>1. There ſhall be only an Alliance defenſive betwixt the two high Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractors; but againſt the <hi>Turks</hi> there ſhall be alſo an Alliance offenſive, which ſhall laſt untill both Parties find themſelves in Reſt and good Security.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. This Alliance ſhall be Sworn and Sacredly confirmed by Oath, in preſence of the Pope, by the two Cardinals <hi>Pio</hi> and <hi>Barberino,</hi> aſwell in name of his <hi>Imperial</hi> Majeſty, as of his Majeſty of <hi>Poland,</hi> and of his States.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. His <hi>Imperial</hi> Majeſty renounces all pretentions for the Charges he hath been at, for the good of the Republick of <hi>Poland,</hi> during the late War of <hi>Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> and the <hi>Diploma de Electione Regis</hi> ſhall be given back and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nulled.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. On the other hand the Crown and Republick of <hi>Poland</hi> renounces all pretentions it can have againſt the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5. The one ſhall not make a ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Peace, without the conſent of the other.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <pb n="120" facs="tcp:34980:62"/>6. The Heirs of the two parties and Succeſſors in the Government, ſhall be obliged to obſerve this Alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. This only is to be underſtood of a War againſt the <hi>Turks,</hi> and not of any other.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. His <hi>Imperial</hi> Majeſty declares, that he will entertain 60000. men, whereof he will ſend 40000. into the Fields, and keep the other 20000. in Garriſons.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. His <hi>Polonian</hi> Majeſty offers to bring 40000. men into the Fields un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his own command.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. To the end the Preparations of War may be the ſooner in readineſs, His <hi>Imperial</hi> Majeſty promiſes by Antici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation to remit 200000. Crowns to the Crown of <hi>Poland,</hi> on condition that that ſum be raiſed out of the Tenth of the Pope in the Kingdom of <hi>Poland,</hi> which he hath granted for that effect.</p>
                  <p n="11">11. His <hi>Imperial</hi> Majeſty ſhall be obliged to recover the places that he hath loſt in <hi>Hungary.</hi> The <hi>Poles</hi> in like manner ſhall be obliged to regain theirs in <hi>Podolia, Walachia,</hi> and the <hi>Vkrain,</hi> and to act againſt <hi>Teckely</hi> with 6000. men.</p>
                  <p n="12">
                     <pb n="121" facs="tcp:34980:62"/>12. Other Chriſtian Kings and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentats may be alſo received into this Alliance; but not without the mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al conſent of both Parties, and above all the two <hi>Czars</hi> of <hi>Muſcovy</hi> ſhall be earneſtly entreated to enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it.</p>
                  <p>I cannot conclude this Chapter, without calling to mind a pretty Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleme made upon occaſion of this Victory, by a young Prince, who reckons Emperors amongſt his Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors: The Emblem repreſents a <hi>Turk</hi> pitching a Net to ſurpriſe and catch the Eagle; but who wandering and engaging too far in his own Toile, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came himſelf therein the prey of the Eagle, with this Inſcription: <q>
                        <hi>Qui captat, capitur,</hi> or <hi>Turca à capiendis captus.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Turca parans Aquilae inſidias ac retia tendens</l>
                     <l>In ſomnis nuper viſus adeſſe mihi.</l>
                     <l>O miſeram! mecum tacitus, te funera, dixi,</l>
                     <l>Quae maneant, neſcis, quo malè cauta volas?</l>
                     <l>Interea in caſſes tendebat rectà volatu,</l>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:34980:63"/>
                     <l>Tollere jam praedam, praedo parabat ovans.</l>
                     <l>Unguibus at contrà volucris (mirabile viſu)</l>
                     <l>Tendentem inſidias inſidiaſque tulit.</l>
                     <l>Sic raptus raptor, factus ſic latro, rapina,</l>
                     <l>Praedonemque putans ſe fore, praeda fuit,</l>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="123" facs="tcp:34980:63"/>
                  <head>THE BATTLE OR DEFEAT OF THE TURKS NEAR <hi>PRESBO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RG.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THE <hi>Turks</hi> who were before <hi>Vienna,</hi> in the year 1683. find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it difficult to bring their Proviſions and Ammunition from the City of <hi>Buda,</hi> to the place where they were on the ſide of the <hi>Danube;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Garriſons of <hi>Raab</hi> and <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mora</hi> way laid all their Convoys, and much annoyed them; the <hi>Grand Viſier</hi> ſent orders to <hi>Baſha Huſani,</hi> to join
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:34980:64"/> Count <hi>Teckely</hi> with ſome Troops, who was on the other ſide of the <hi>Danube,</hi> near the River of <hi>Waag,</hi> and to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to make himſelf Maſter of the City of <hi>Presbourg,</hi> to the end they might have the paſſage of the <hi>Danube</hi> free, make a Bridge of Boats over it, and be provided of all things on that ſide. The thing was well undertaken; for Twenty thouſand of their Men marched towards that Town: But the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> who at that time reſolved to encreaſe his Army with the Regiments of <hi>Gran</hi> and <hi>Baden,</hi> which were in <hi>Raab,</hi> and were not ſo neceſſary there, ſeeing the <hi>Turks</hi> had Beſieged <hi>Vienna,</hi> and who therefore had drawn near to <hi>Preſbourg,</hi> to ſecure that Town from the attempts of the <hi>Turks;</hi> having had notice of it, ſent immediately againſt them Prince <hi>Louis</hi> of <hi>Baden</hi> (who that day commanded the Van-Guard) with ſome Squadrons of Prince <hi>Lubomirski</hi>'s men, and the Two Regiments of <hi>Palfi</hi> and <hi>Styrum,</hi> who at firſt charged <hi>Teckely</hi>'s men in ſuch a manner, that preſently they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took themſelves to flight. The <hi>Turks</hi> made a little longer Reſiſtance; but at
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:34980:64"/> length alſo they were forced to give ground with the loſs of Eight hundred of their Men, and a conſiderable <hi>Aga.</hi> The <hi>Imperialiſts</hi> gained there a Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Wagons with Baggage; and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly it was a lucky Hit for them to have beat the Enemy at that time, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe if they had delayed but one day longer, <hi>Preſbourg</hi> had been loſt, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe within had promiſed to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der next day to <hi>Teckely,</hi> and to furniſh him with all that was neceſſary for the Bridge of Boats: whereas the <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perialiſts</hi> thereby not only preſerved that Town, whither ſoon after they ſent Six hundred men to re-inforce the Garriſon; but alſo hindred the paſſage of the <hi>Danube,</hi> and the means of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding the Army before <hi>Vienna</hi> with neceſſaries; beſides that they alſo ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ined the Boats which Count <hi>Teckely</hi> and the <hi>Turks</hi> had gathered together for making a Bridge: Theſe laſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated towards the River of <hi>Waag,</hi> from whence Count <hi>Teckely</hi> wrote a Letter, to Juſtifie himſelf to the <hi>Grand Viſier,</hi> which was intercepted by the <hi>Imperialiſts.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="126" facs="tcp:34980:65"/>
                  <head>THE BATTLE OF BARKAN.</head>
                  <p>THE Generals of the Chriſtian Armies, on the 10th. of <hi>Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> 1683. advanced towards <hi>Barkan</hi> (the <hi>Poles</hi> on that occaſion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the left Wing;) the <hi>Turks</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them approach, fell upon them with a dreadful Shout, and chiefly up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the left Wing, commanded by the Lord High Marſhal of <hi>Poland Jabla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowisky,</hi> who having the former Vict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ory in his thoughts, charged the <hi>Turks</hi> ſo furiouſly, that he conſtrained them to give ground; but the Duke of <hi>Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain</hi> with the Cavalry of the right Wing, broke in upon them, with ſo great Impetuoſity, that he put them entirely to the Flight. Afterwards ſome Regiments were commanded out to purſue the <hi>Turks,</hi> who fled, and by
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:34980:65"/> them were driven partly in a Mariſh, and partly into the <hi>Danube;</hi> becauſe the Bridge, betwixt <hi>Barkan</hi> and <hi>Gran,</hi> broke in the middle, ſo that moſt of them fell into the River, and were drowned, and the reſt who ſaved themſelves in the Mariſh were killed, ſeeing in the firſt heat they gave the <hi>Turks</hi> no Quarters; and it was not till towards the end that they took a Thouſand Priſoners, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt whom was the Baſha of <hi>Siliſtria.</hi> Prince <hi>Loüis</hi> of <hi>Baden</hi> ſignalized him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf on this occaſion, and was by his Conduct the chief cauſe of the Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, becauſe the <hi>Imperial</hi> Cavalry act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all along without the Foot. The Chriſtians gained all the Colours, Tents, Cannon, Baggage, and in a word, all that was in the Camp of the <hi>Turks,</hi> beſides a Thouſand Horſes that they made booty of. There are various Relations of the loſs that the <hi>Turks</hi> ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered in this Fight; ſome will have it that being Thirteen thouſand ſtrong before the Defeat, they ſaved but Three or Four Thouſand at moſt, and amongſt thoſe the <hi>Baſha</hi> of <hi>Meſopotamia</hi> who Commanded them; all the reſt,
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:34980:66"/> who were the Choice of the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Army, being either killed or taken. However it be, the Waters of the <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nube</hi> were died with their Blood; this Fight laſted about five hours.</p>
                  <p>From thence the <hi>Imperaliſts</hi> advanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed towards <hi>Barkan,</hi> and Battered that place ſo violently with great and ſmall Shot, that preſently they in the Town beat a Parley, which being granted them, the <hi>Imperialiſts</hi> enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the place; but ſhortly after a Fire happening in it, this little Hold was burnt down, and no body could tell how the Fire happened. This Victory was followed by the taking of <hi>Gran,</hi> which ſurrendered the 27th. of <hi>Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> after four days Siege: Theſe were the Articles of Capitulation;</p>
                  <p n="1">1. All the Cannon, Mortars, Ammu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition, Magazines, and other Arms ſhall remain in the Fort, except what is hereafter ſpecified.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The Garriſon ſhall have leave to provide themſelves of Bread and Meat for two days, and to carry with them all their Coffee, Sharbet, Cloaths and other Moveables.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb n="129" facs="tcp:34980:66"/>3 His Highneſs of <hi>Lorrain</hi> ſhall fur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niſh the Garriſon a certain Number of Waggons, to carry their Goods to the Water, to be Tranſported down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Some Boats ſhall alſo be given to the ſaid Garriſon, to be made uſe of for tranſporting their Effects; and if they cannot carry them off all at once, they may ſend for them at ſeveral times.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. That if the afore ſaid Baggage can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be Tranſported all at once, the Garriſon may put what is left behind into ſome Houſes of the Lower Town, which ſhall be kept by ſome of their Men, that all the reſt may honeſtly and without Let or Moleſtation follow after.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Since the Boat-men cannot be ſpared at preſent, the Garriſon ſhall be obliged to make uſe of their own men, to go down and up the River with the Boats.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. The afore-mentioned Articles being granted to the Garriſon, the Gate of the Caſtle ſhall immediately be opened to the <hi>Imperial</hi> Troops, that they may take their Poſt there,
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:34980:67"/> and ſo ſoon as the aforeſaid Waggons and Boats ſhall be ready, the Garriſon of the Fort of <hi>Gran,</hi> that is to ſay, they who are capable to bear Arms, ſhall march out all at once.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. All the Chriſtian Priſoners in the Caſtle ſhall be releaſed.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. Laſtly, the Garriſon may freely march out, as hath been ſaid, with their Wives and Children, Arms and Baggage, Horſes and Camels, obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Conditions above-mentioned, in the manner as they are expreſſed.</p>
                  <p>In conſequence of this Capitulation, the Prince of <hi>Alepah</hi> of <hi>Syria,</hi> Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in <hi>Gran,</hi> and <hi>Baſha</hi> of <hi>Nicopolis,</hi> and <hi>Samſon Baſha</hi> Colonel of the <hi>Janiſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> marched out of the place with Five hundred Men carrying Arms to go to <hi>Offen;</hi> whereupon the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> made Governor of <hi>Gran</hi> Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel <hi>Calowith</hi> Governor of the Caſtle of <hi>Presbourg,</hi> with a Garriſon of 1000. <hi>Imperial</hi> Souldiers, and ſome Hundreds of <hi>Huſſars.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="131" facs="tcp:34980:67"/>
                  <head>THE BATTLE OF GRAN.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>AUguſt</hi> the 16. 1685. The Dukes of <hi>Lorrain</hi> and <hi>Bavaria</hi> raiſed the Siege that the <hi>Turks</hi> had laid down before <hi>Gran,</hi> and then engaged the <hi>Barbarians,</hi> to the number of Fifty or Sixty Thouſand men, gave them a total Rout, and obliged them to aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don their Camp and Baggage; which Victory Three days after was fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed with the taking of <hi>Newheu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It will not be improper, I think, in this place to inſert the Letter which about that time, the <hi>Seraſquier Ibrahim Baſha</hi> wrote to his Highneſs the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> which he ſent by the <hi>Defte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dar</hi> of the <hi>Timmariot</hi>'s <hi>Achmet Deſquelebi</hi> by the Advice of the <hi>Grand Signior,</hi> the Contents whereof are word for word as follows.</p>
                  <div type="letter">
                     <pb n="132" facs="tcp:34980:68"/>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>To our good Friend the Duke of <hi>Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain,</hi> Generaliſſimo of the Armies of the Emperour of the <hi>Germans,</hi> Greeting: </salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>We let you know as a good Friend, that <hi>Ach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met Deſquelebi Deftedar,</hi> or Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary of <hi>Newheuſel,</hi> hath reported that we your Friend, ought to ſend you Letters, to which you might give Credit, if we deſire to ſee a Negotiation for Peace: It is for that Cauſe that the preſent are Writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and ſent to you; and ſeeing we your Friends deſire for the ſervice of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of God, that means of Tranquillity might be found out for the Subjects of both Parties, what we ſay to you and beſeech, as well as what we ſhall do (in purſuance of our Word) hath been approved (for ſo is the Will of God) by the Majeſty of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſplendent, Omnipotent, and formidable Emperor and King of the Superfice of the Earth; wherefore we ſend you this Man, to whom we have entruſted ſome things to be told you by word of Mouth, to the end you may be pleaſed to ſend us a truſty Man on your part, to endeavour a Peace, it is hoped we may come to a Conference; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon Farewel. Given in the Camp at <hi>Peſt:</hi> 
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Signed, <hi>IBRAHIM.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <pb n="133" facs="tcp:34980:68"/>
               <head>CHAP. XV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p> Of the Ceremonies obſerved in the Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of the Kings and Queens of <hi>Hungary.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>AFter all neceſſary Preparations have been made for the Solem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of the Coronation, the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of it are performed in this manner: In the firſt place, an Election is made of thoſe who are to go and fetch the Crown, Scepter, Globe, repreſenting the World, Sword, Coat of Arms, the Royal Habits, and Croſs, in the City of <hi>Presbourg,</hi> where they are kept, with the Standards of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. They diſcharge this Duty, and carry them to the Church. The Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latin takes the Crown, and places it on the right ſide of the Altar, where the Arch-biſhop of <hi>Strigonium</hi> ſays Maſs; the Prelates ſit about the Steps of the Altar, and ſome of them lead the King from the Throne to the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, or from the Altar to his Seat; the
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:34980:69"/> reſt ſerve for ſome other Action of the Coronation. The Kings Throne dec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked with Cloth of Gold, is pretty near the Altar, and oppoſite to the middle of it, having over it a Cloth of State, of the ſame Stuff as that of the Seat. The King kneels firſt upon the Steps of the Altar, and Kiſſes the Croſs, which the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Stri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonium</hi> preſents to him; then takes the Oath contained in the <hi>Roman</hi> Pontifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, ſaying the Words after the Arch-biſhop, and laying his Right hand on the Goſpel, with Eyes lifted up to Heaven, as if he called God to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. After the Oath, he is anointed by the Arch-biſhop on the right Arm near the Elbow, and betwixt the two Shoulders: Then being cloathed with the Coat of Arms of King St. <hi>Stephen,</hi> he receives from the ſame Arch-Biſhop, the naked <hi>Cuttelas</hi> of the ſame Saint, then gives it back to the Arch-biſhop, who returns it into the Scabbard, and then girds it to his ſide. That being done, the King turned towards the Altar, as Defender of the Altars, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and the Church, draws the Sword out of the Scabbard,
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:34980:69"/> and brandiſhing it three ways in the Air gives ſo many blows; then the Arch-Biſhop taking the Crown, gives it to the Palatin, who holding it up on high with both his Hands, and being upon the Steps of the Altar, asks aloud all that are preſent, if they would have him Crown'd for their King, and having three times put the ſame que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion unto them, upon their anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Affirmative, he is crowned, and receives from the Arch-Biſhop the Scepter in the right hand, the Globe in the left, and all the marks of Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Dignity: After that he ſits down on the Throne, as taking Poſſeſſion of the Kingdom. Then all the <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garians</hi> make loud Shouts and Accla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations, wiſhing the King a long and proſperous Reign, and at the ſame time, the Vocal and Inſtrumental Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, the Trumpets, Drums, and Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non, mingle their noiſe with the confuſed Voices. Maſs being ſaid, and the Streets, through which the King is to go, being Boarded and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered with White, Green, and Red Cloth, the King walks from the Church, where he was, to another,
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:34980:70"/> wearing the Crown and Coat of Arms, ſome carrying before him the Royal Ornaments and Standards, and a great many others walking before and after him. At the ſame time pieces of Gold and Silver are ſcattered a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the People, in all the Streets through which the King paſſes, who coming to the other Church, ſits down on the Royal Throne erected there, and makes ſome Knights, ſtriking them thrice on the Back with the naked Sword of St. <hi>Stephen,</hi> as they are knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling before him. This being done, he comes out of the Church, and mount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on Horſe back, with the Crown and Coat of Arms, having the ſame per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons on Horſe-back, who walked be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore or followed him on foot, as he came in the ſame Order he goes out of the Town, and alighting, with the Arch-biſhop of <hi>Strigonium</hi> mounts up upon a Theater, where lifting up the Right hand he takes an Oath to the <hi>Hungarians</hi> to maintain the Priviledges of the Nobility, do Juſtice to all, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Laws of the Kingdom, and procure the good of the Publick.</p>
               <p>In the mean time all are uncovered, and when he hath taken the Oath, all
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:34980:70"/> again ſhout, and amidſt the noiſe of great Guns wiſh him all ſort of Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. Afterwards he mounts a ſtately and well-managed Horſe, and ſpurs him towards an adjoyning ground, where putting him upon the Carrier, and drawing the Sword of St. <hi>Stephen,</hi> he makes in form of a Croſs, four ſtroaks in the Air, turning his Horſe very nimbly, as threatning the four Corners of the World, and then there is nothing to be heard but Volleys of great Guns. After this the new King putting his Horſe to a Walk, draws near the Lords who are Spectators, and with them goes to his Pallace, where he feaſts them, ſitting at Table with his Crown and Coat of Arms, and being ſerved by ſome Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons and Grandees of the Kingdom, appointed for that Office; and when Dinner is over, they who have the charge of the Crown, and Royal Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments carry them back to their place.</p>
               <p>Now to ſhew you the Ceremonies of the Coronation of the Queens of <hi>Hungary,</hi> I'll give you here an Abridg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of what paſt when the preſent Empereſs <hi>Anna Maria of Bavaria</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latineſs
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:34980:71"/> of <hi>Newbourg</hi> was Crowned Queen of <hi>Hungary</hi> in the Town of <hi>Edimbourg</hi> in the year 1681. The Emperor in his <hi>Imperial</hi> Habits, and the Domeſtick Crown of the Empire on his Head, went with his Attendants to the Church of the <hi>Recollets,</hi> where he was received and ſprinkled with Holy Water by the Clergy of <hi>Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Train of the Empreſs came after, before whom Count <hi>John Draſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kowich</hi> walked with the Scepter, in place of Count <hi>Draſkowich,</hi> the Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of the Kingdom went before. The Counts <hi>Stephen Zichy</hi> and <hi>Chriſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher Erdedy,</hi> both Keepers of the Crown, came next, with the Lords who carried the Royal Jewels upon Cuſhions of Crimſon Velvet. Count <hi>Illiſhazi</hi> carried the Silver Croſs, Count <hi>Nicholas Erdedy</hi> the Scepter, the Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin of <hi>Hungary</hi> the Crown, and Count <hi>Nicholas Draſkowich</hi> the Globe of the Empire. The <hi>Empreſs</hi> came after theſe, led by the Duke of <hi>Diederichſtein</hi> Maſter of the Palace. The Counteſs of <hi>Rapach</hi> chief Governante carried up her Train, which was embroidered
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:34980:71"/> with Gold, Diamonds and Pearls, and after her came the Palatineſs and other Ladies of Court. The Empereſs was received at the Entry into the Church, by the Arch-Biſhops of <hi>Colocza</hi> and <hi>Neutra,</hi> who led her to the Throne. In the mean time the Emperour ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving taken his place on the ſide of the Goſpel, went alſo to his Throne in the middle of the Quire over againſt the great Altar, behind the Throne ſate the Palatineſs with the chief Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernante and other Ladies of Court, in Chaires prepared for them. On the left hand of the Empreſſes Throne were the Lords of <hi>Hungary,</hi> who carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Jewels of the Kingdom, which were taken from them by the Arch-Biſhop who put them upon the Altar. Before the Throne there was a Silver Stool, where the Domeſtick Crown, which was brought to the Church un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a Cover, was placed. That being done the Goſpel was read, at the end whereof the Emperour went to the Altar with the Crown on his Head, the Scepter in his Right Hand, and the Globe in the Left, and preſented the Empreſs to the
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:34980:72"/> Arch-biſhops to be crowned. When his Imperial Majeſty had taken his place, the Empreſs advanced towards the Altar, aſſiſted by the Arch-biſhops, and kneeled upon the firſt Step, whilſt the Arch-biſhop of <hi>Gran</hi> kiſſed the end of the Croſs, and preſented her the Scepter and Globe of the Empire, which ſhe took, the Scepter in her right hand, and the Globe in the left, the Prelate all the while ſaying ſome Prayers. That Ceremony being over, the Empreſs was led back to the Throne, where the Arch-biſhop hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing again ſaid ſome Prayers, <hi>Te Deum</hi> was ſung during a Volly of 480. Musket<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhot, and a diſcharge of the Artillery upon the Rampart. Then Count <hi>John Draskowich</hi> took the Scepter and Globe of the Empire out of the hands of the Empreſs, in place of the Steward of <hi>Hungary,</hi> and gave them back to thoſe who had carried them before. That being done, the Empreſs was led to the Offering by the Arch-biſhops, and put a rare piece of Gold of Gold-Smiths work into a Silver Baſon that was up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Altar, and then returned to her Throne. The Domeſtick Crown was
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:34980:72"/> taken off of the Head of the Empreſs by the Biſhop of <hi>Neutra,</hi> during the Offering and Communion, and given to be held by the Duke of <hi>Diederickſteyn,</hi> who after the Communion gave it back to the ſaid Prelate, to be put up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Head of the Empreſs again. The aforeſaid Biſhop led her to the Communion, which being given her by the hand of the Arch-biſhop of <hi>Gran,</hi> the Crown was put upon her Majeſties head. The Ceremonies thus performed, they returned in the ſame Order as they came, with the noiſe of Cannon, and the Ladies were ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to kiſs her Hand. When they were at Table, his Imperial Majeſty ordered the Artillery once more to play, which concluded the Solemnity.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <pb n="142" facs="tcp:34980:73"/>
               <head>CHAP. XVI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p> Of the Deſcription of <hi>Tranſilvania,</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently united to <hi>Hungary,</hi> and the Princes who have Reigned in it, ſince the beginning of this Age, to the preſent time.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>TRanſilvania,</hi> a Principality of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope,</hi> is part of the Ancient <hi>Dacia,</hi> to the Weſt of <hi>Hungary,</hi> and to the Eaſt of <hi>Moravia,</hi> having the <hi>Carpathian</hi> Mountains to the North, and <hi>Walachia</hi> to the South. It is four days journey in length, and as much in breadth: That Name was given it by the <hi>Romans,</hi> becauſe it is incompaſſed with Forreſts as well as Mountains. The <hi>Hungari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> call it <hi>Erdely,</hi> and the <hi>Germans Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ben bergen;</hi> becauſe of Seven Towns which the fugitive <hi>Saxons</hi> built there. Several other People ſettled there; but the <hi>Saxons</hi> I ſpeak of cultivated the Country beſt. The <hi>Romans</hi> after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards became Maſters of it under <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jan:</hi>
                  <pb n="143" facs="tcp:34980:73"/> In proceſs of time it was united to <hi>Hungary,</hi> from which it was diſmem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred in the year 1541. At preſent the Princes of it are Elective &amp; Tributary to the <hi>Turk.</hi> The Town of <hi>Tranſilva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia</hi> are <hi>Hermenſtadt, Clauſenbourg, Wei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenbourg,</hi> or <hi>Alba-Julia,</hi> &amp;c. It is a fertile Country, and hath ſeveral Mines and Medicinal Plants. Moſt of the Inhabitants are <hi>Greeks, Schiſmaticks;</hi> there are in it alſo a great many <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks,</hi> and ſome <hi>Mahometans.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Princes of <hi>Tranſilvania,</hi> who have reigned ſince the beginning of this Age, are theſe that follow.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Sigiſmond Bathori,</hi> Knight of the Golden Fleece, Son to <hi>Chriſtopher</hi> Prince of <hi>Tranſilvania,</hi> who died in the year 1581. ſucceeded to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in that Principality, and died at <hi>Prague</hi> the 17. of <hi>March</hi> 1603.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Stephen Bodtskey</hi> introduced himſelf by force into that Principality, and his Uſurpation was approved by the <hi>Turk,</hi> and at length by the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror upon certain Conditions; he died of Poyſon in the year 1606. and named for his Succeſſor <hi>Valen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine Homonay;</hi> but the States of the
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:34980:74"/> Country preferred <hi>Sigiſmond Ragot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ski</hi> before him.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Sigiſmond Ragotski</hi> was elected Prince of <hi>Tranſilvania</hi> in the year 1606. but having reigned a year, he reſigned that Dignity to <hi>Gabriel Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thory</hi> Nephew to Prince <hi>Sigiſmond</hi> in 1608. <hi>Sultan Achmet</hi> confirmed that choice, and the King of <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary,</hi> the Arch-Duke <hi>Matthias</hi> did not oppoſe it.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Gabriel Bathory</hi> was elected Prince of <hi>Tranſilvania</hi> in the year 1608. and was aſſaſſinated at <hi>Valencze</hi> in the year 1613.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Bethlen Gabor</hi> who had had a great Hand in that Death, being ſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the <hi>Turks,</hi> ſeized the State and cauſed himſelf to be proclaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Prince of <hi>Tranſilvania</hi> in the year 1613. and by a Treaty made with the Emperor in 1622. he continued Prince of <hi>Tranſilvania.</hi> He died the 15. of <hi>November</hi> 1629.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>George Ragotski</hi> Prince of <hi>Tranſilva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia</hi> ſucceeded to him; he died of his Wounds at <hi>Waradin</hi> in the Month of <hi>June</hi> 1660.</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <pb n="145" facs="tcp:34980:74"/>7. <hi>Achatius Barchay</hi> by the <hi>Turks</hi> intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced into that Principality in place of <hi>Ragotski,</hi> reſigned it ſome time after, and was beheaded about the end of the ſaid year 1660,</p>
               <p n="8">8. When <hi>John Kemeni</hi> was choſen Prince, who was killed in the year. 1661.</p>
               <p n="9">9. <hi>Michael Abafti</hi> Count of <hi>Sicules,</hi> Prince of <hi>Tranſilvania</hi> who Reigns at preſent, was choſen in the year 1661. by the Aſſiſtance of the <hi>Turks.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <pb n="146" facs="tcp:34980:75"/>
               <head>CHAP. XVII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p> Of the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Emperors, who in Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs of time have invaded, ſubdued, and uſurped the greateſt part of <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>SOlyman,</hi> called the Magnificent, Son of <hi>Sultan Selim,</hi> immediately af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the death of his Father, whom he had poyſoned, took <hi>Belgrade,</hi> and the Iſle of <hi>Rhodes,</hi> was the firſt that inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Kingdom of <hi>Hungary,</hi> and with his Armies paſſed the Rivers of <hi>Save</hi> and <hi>Drave,</hi> in the year 1526. He was Victorious in the Famous Battle of <hi>Mohacz,</hi> which I mentioned before, wherein <hi>Loüis</hi> II. King of <hi>Hungary</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunately periſhed. At <hi>Bagdet</hi> he was crowned King of <hi>Perſia,</hi> and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> and <hi>Meſopotamia:</hi> He made ſix Expeditions into <hi>Hungary,</hi> and took the ſtrong Towns of <hi>Strigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium</hi> and <hi>Alba-Regalis:</hi> He alſo ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected <hi>Aladulia,</hi> and the Kingdom of <hi>Aden;</hi> beſides many other Towns up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:34980:75"/> the <hi>Red-Sea:</hi> He made <hi>Algiers</hi> Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>utary, took <hi>Pialli, Tripoli,</hi> and the <hi>Gerbes,</hi> and after all theſe Victories whilſt he beſieged the ſtrong Town of <hi>Siget</hi> in the lower <hi>Hungary,</hi> he died <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n <hi>Five-Churches,</hi> as hath been menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned before.</p>
               <p>This Emperour took to himſelf the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ollowing Titles, in the Credential Letters of the Ambaſſador, whom <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſent to the Emperour <hi>Ferdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>and.</hi>
               </p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>
                        <hi>I the Lord of all Lords, the Ruler of the Eaſt and Weſt, who am able to do, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ot to do whatſoever I pleaſe. Lord of all</hi> Grecia, Perſia, <hi>and</hi> Arabia, <hi>Ruler over <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ll things that can be Subject to a King <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>nd Lord; the Great</hi> Hero <hi>of theſe Times, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>nd mighty Giant of this vaſt univerſe; Lord of the White and Black Seas, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>he Holy City of</hi> Mecha, <hi>ſhining with the Brightneſs of God, of the City of</hi> Medina, <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>nd the Holy and Chaſte City of</hi> Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>em; <hi>King of the moſt Noble Kingdom of</hi> Egypt; <hi>Lord of the Country of</hi> Ionia, <hi>and Cities of</hi> Athens <hi>and</hi> Sena, <hi>of the Holy Temple of God</hi> Zabilon <hi>and</hi> Baſſio, Ret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>aam <hi>and</hi> Magadim, <hi>the Seat and Throne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>f the Great King</hi> Naſhin Rettham, <hi>and
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:34980:76"/> Lord of the Iſland of</hi> Algiers, <hi>and Prince of the Kingdom of</hi> Tartary, Meſopota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia, <hi>the</hi> Medes, Georgians, <hi>and of all</hi> Greece, Morea <hi>and</hi> Anatolia, Aſia, Armenia, Walachia, Moldavia, <hi>and all</hi> Hungary, <hi>with a great many other Kingdoms and Dominions, whereof I am Emperour, that thrice great</hi> Caeſar, Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan Solyman, <hi>the Son of the great Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror</hi> Sultan Selim, <hi>who have Authority from God to Rule all People in a bit of Iron, and power to open the Gates and Doors of all Cities and ſtrong Holds, all the ends of the Earth, none excepted are delivered into my Hands; I the Lord of the Eaſt from the Land of</hi> Tſcin <hi>to the utmoſt bounds of</hi> Africa, <hi>whom God hath made a valiant Warriour in the edge of the Sword, amongſt whoſe moſt potent King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms the impregnable Caſtle of</hi> Ceſarea, <hi>is reckoned the leaſt, and the Empire or Dominion of</hi> Alexander <hi>the Great the meaneſt of my Hereditary Dominions; with me is the Strength of the whole World, and Virtue of the Firmament.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>
                  <hi>Zelim</hi> II. Emperor of the <hi>Turks,</hi> Son of <hi>Sultan Solyman</hi> II. called the Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificent, ſucceeded to him in the year 1566. being about Fourty two years
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:34980:76"/> of Age; this Emperor having ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted <hi>Nicoſia</hi> and <hi>Famaguſta,</hi> ſeized the Iſland of <hi>Cyprus,</hi> a Kingdom belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the <hi>Venetians</hi> in the year 1521. but after that loſs the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> gained the Famous Battle of <hi>Lepanto,</hi> the 7th. of <hi>October</hi> the ſame year. <hi>Haly Baſha</hi> was killed there, and it is not doubted, but that it was the greateſt Blow that the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Empire had for a long time received; and, indeed, if the <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> had known how to make the beſt Advantage of that Victory, they might without doubt have taken <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople,</hi> where all were in a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Conſternation: And to ſee how great a Victory that of the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Princes was, we may only read the Triumphal Inſcription expoſed by the <hi>Romans</hi> in the Capitol, in memory of it, and of <hi>Marco Antonio Colonna</hi> Duke of <hi>Paliano,</hi> Knight of the Golden Fleece, Great Conſtable of <hi>Naples,</hi> whom Pope <hi>Pius</hi> V. made General of the Eccleſiaſtical Forces, who ſolemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly received the Standard in St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Church at <hi>Rome,</hi> and who in that memorable Battle commanded as Lieutenant General, being upon his
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:34980:77"/> return received in Triumph in the City of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Marcus Antonius</hi> Aſcanij Filius, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bricij nepos, Columnae Marſorum, &amp; Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicorum Dux, initâ inter Pium V. Pont. Max. Phillippum Hiſpaniarum Regem Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicum, &amp; Rempublicam Venetam So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietate, Claſſis Pontificiae Praefectus,</p>
                  <p>De Turcis Non. Octobris ad Echinadas,</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Navali praelio victis,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>DC.</hi> Navigiis in poteſtatem redactis,</l>
                     <l>Demerſis &amp; fugatis.</l>
                     <l>Chriſtianos <hi>XV.</hi> mill. in libertatem aſſertis,</l>
                     <l>Hoſtium <hi>XXX.</hi> mill. caeſis,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>X.</hi> mill. captis,</l>
                     <l>Re optimè geſtâ</l>
                     <l>Ut Victoriâ omnium maxima in mari partâ.</l>
                     <l>Ex S. C. &amp; Pij V. S. P. authoritate</l>
                     <l>More Majorum</l>
                     <l>Prid. Non. Decembris anno à Chriſto nato <hi>M.D.LXXI.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Triumphavit,</l>
                     <l>Ad ejus rei memoriam ſempiternam,</l>
                     <l>Diem hunc antiquis Triumphalibus faſtis adſcribendum,</l>
                     <l>Et monumentum hoc in Capitolio ponendum,</l>
                     <l>Cenſuit S. P. Q. R. ut ſuperiorum aemu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lationi,</l>
                     <pb n="151" facs="tcp:34980:77"/>
                     <l>Praeſentis aevi gloriae, poſterorum incita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento,</l>
                     <l>Teſtaretur, in promerendis honoribus, ac tribuendis,</l>
                     <l>Neque virtutem, neque benignitatem priſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam</l>
                     <l>Adhuc deeſse Romanis,</l>
                     <l>Coſſ. Rom. decreverunt, curaverunt.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Selim</hi> the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Emperor, died of an Apoplexy the Thirteenth of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember</hi> 1574.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Amurath</hi> III. Son of <hi>Selim</hi> II. began to Reign about the end of the year 1574. He preſently put to death five of his Brothers, according to the Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el cuſtom of the <hi>Ottomans,</hi> and refuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to prolong with the Emperor <hi>Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milian</hi> II. the Truce which he had concluded with <hi>Selim</hi> II. He took <hi>Tauris</hi> which he Plundered, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feated the <hi>Marovites</hi> and <hi>Drus</hi> of Mount <hi>Libanus:</hi> After that he made a powerful Invaſion into the Country of the <hi>Croats,</hi> who were worſted at firſt, but they afterwards killed Ten thouſand <hi>Turks,</hi> and obliged the reſt to let them live in quiet. <hi>Amurath</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> the 18th. of <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuary,</hi>
                  <pb n="152" facs="tcp:34980:78"/> 1595. at the Age of Forty eight.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mahomet</hi> III. Son of <hi>Amurath</hi> III. began his Reign in the year 1595. by the death of One and Twenty of his Brothers, and Ten of his Fathers Wives whom he left with Child, and whom he cauſed to be thrown into the Sea. He never was at the Head of his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my but once. The Chriſtians under the Conduct of Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> took <hi>Strigonium, Alba-Regalis</hi> under the Command of the Duke of <hi>Mercaur</hi> in the year 1601. and the Lower Town of <hi>Buda,</hi> under the Arch-Duke of <hi>Auſtria.</hi> He loſt the Forts of <hi>Vice grad, Balbocz, Petrinia, Haduan, Palota</hi> and <hi>Veſprin;</hi> and on the other ſide the Knights of <hi>Malta</hi> ſeized <hi>Lepanto.</hi> The Armies of <hi>Mahomet</hi> were beaten by the Vaivod of <hi>Walachia,</hi> and by the Prince of <hi>Tranſilvania,</hi> who defeated <hi>Sinan Baſha,</hi> and ſo <hi>Moldavia, Wala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ohia</hi> and <hi>Tranſilvania</hi> ſhook off the <hi>Ottoman</hi> yoke. The <hi>Turks</hi> on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hand had ſome advantages, and re-took two or three Towns, as <hi>Peſt Caniſa</hi> and <hi>Alba-Regalis,</hi> but that was not comparable to their loſſes. <hi>Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met</hi>
                  <pb n="153" facs="tcp:34980:78"/> demanded Peace of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, who refuſed it. He was an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famous Man, ſo plunged into Debau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery, that neither domeſtick Diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, nor Forreign Wars could ever make him forſake it; that made the <hi>Janiſaries</hi> mutiny; to pacifie whom <hi>Mahomet</hi> was forced to deliver up his greateſt Friends to their Rage, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to baniſh his Mother, who was thought to be the cauſe of all the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities of the State. He cauſed his eldeſt Son to be Strangled, and the <hi>Sultana</hi> the Mother of him to be drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, having ſuſpected her to be Guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of ſome Treaſon againſt his Perſon. He died of the Plague at <hi>Conſtantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> in the year 1603. the Thirty ninth year of his Age, and Eighth year of his Reign.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Achmet</hi> I. of that name, Emperor, of the <hi>Turks,</hi> Succeeded to his Father, <hi>Mahomot</hi> III. at the Age of Fifteen years, in the year 1603. His Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration was admired upon his coming to the Throne, in that having but one only Brother, he did not put him to death according to the Cuſtom of the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Princes; but ſhut him up in
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:34980:79"/> a Cloyſter of <hi>Mahometans.</hi> The <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy</hi> of <hi>Perſia</hi> taking the advantage of his Minority, re-took <hi>Tauris</hi> and <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zerum. Achmet</hi> ſent thither the <hi>Baſha Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gale,</hi> who not having acquitted himſelf well of his Commiſſion, was upon his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn Strangled by 50. <hi>Capigis</hi> who met him at <hi>Burſa. Achmet</hi> regained <hi>Tranſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vania, Walachia</hi> and <hi>Moldavia</hi> by the means of <hi>Botskay,</hi> who revolted from the Emperor, and ſided with <hi>Bethlem Gabor</hi> againſt <hi>Sigiſmond Bathory</hi> Prince of <hi>Tranſilvania.</hi> Afterwards finding himſelf Attacked on all hands, he put Four Armies into the Field; one againſt the <hi>Perſians,</hi> another againſt the <hi>Poloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> one to oppoſe the <hi>Coſſacks,</hi> and the laſt to guard the Tribute of <hi>Egypt;</hi> but all of them having been unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, as he was preparing for greater deſigns, he died the 15th. of <hi>November</hi> 1617. in the Thirtieth year of his Age and Fourteenth of his Reign.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Muſtapha,</hi> Emperor of the <hi>Turks</hi> was Son to <hi>Mahomet</hi> III. and Brother to <hi>Achmet</hi> I. he ſucceeded to him though he had a Son <hi>Oſman</hi> Twelve years old in the year 1617. <hi>Muſtapha</hi> being Twenty five years of Age was placed
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:34980:79"/> upon the Throne by the <hi>Janiſaries,</hi> who two Months after degraded him, being diſpleaſed at his reſerved way of living. <hi>Oſman</hi> his Nephew Succeeded to him, and <hi>Muſtapha,</hi> as ſome ſay, led a recluſe and ſolitary Life: But the truth is he was in Priſon; howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver being brought out by the <hi>Janiſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> he was again ſet upon the Throne the 19. of <hi>May</hi> 1622. Next day after he cauſed his Nephew <hi>Oſman</hi> to be put to death, and having Reigned ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen Months, the People being diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatisfied with his Conduct, he was again confined to perpetual Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the Month of <hi>September</hi> 1623. and <hi>Amurath</hi> Brother to <hi>Oſman</hi> was put in his place.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Oſman,</hi> Emperor of the <hi>Turks,</hi> was the Son of <hi>Achmet</hi> I. and ſucceeded to him at Twelve years of Age about the end of <hi>January</hi> 1621. He led an Army of almoſt Four hundred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand men againſt the <hi>Poles;</hi> but that Expedition was not proſperous; he loſt above an Hundred thouſand men, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempting to force the Camp of Three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore thouſand <hi>Poles</hi> and <hi>Coſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ks,</hi>
                  <pb n="156" facs="tcp:34980:80"/> Commanded by Prince <hi>Ladiſlaus. Oſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> was obliged to make a Peace on diſadvantageous Conditions. He thought that the <hi>Janiſaries</hi> had much contributed to that unhappy Succeſs, which made him have a mind to ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhier them, and he was accuſed of having a deſign to remove the ſeat of the Empire unto <hi>Damaſcus</hi> in <hi>Syria.</hi> That inſolent Militia revolted and the Unfortunate Prince was Strang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the 20. of <hi>May,</hi> 1622. dy Order of <hi>Muſtapha</hi> his Uncle, whom the ſame <hi>Janiſaries</hi> had raiſed to the Throne, as I ſaid before. <hi>Oſman's</hi> Reign laſted but Four years, and about four Months. Sultan <hi>Oſman</hi> took the following Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles, in a Letter which he wrote at the deſire of the moſt Chriſtian King to Baſha <hi>Ferrovi</hi> and to <hi>Mula Cadi</hi> of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> to reſtore the <hi>Cordeliers</hi> to the poſſeſſion of <hi>Bethlehem</hi> and of the Holy Sepulchre in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> which places had been poſſeſſed by the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menians</hi> in the year 1625.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The Emperor</hi> Oſman, <hi>Son of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror</hi> Achmet, <hi>always Victorious; I who am by the infinite Graces of the Almighty Creator, and by the abundant Miracles of
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:34980:80"/> the chief of the Prophets, Emperour of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorious Emperours, Diſtributor of Crowns to the greateſt Princes of the Earth, Kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the two ſacred and moſt auguſt Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, the faireſt amongſt all thoſe of the World</hi> Mecha <hi>and</hi> Medina, <hi>Protector of the Holy</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>Lord of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt part of</hi> Europe, Aſia, <hi>and</hi> Africa, <hi>conquered with our Victorious Sword, to wit, of the Countries and Kingdoms of</hi> Greece, Themeſwar, Boſne, Seget, Natolia, Caramania, Egypt, <hi>and of all the Countries of the</hi> Parthians, Curdes <hi>and</hi> Georgians, <hi>of the</hi> Iron-Gate, <hi>of the Countries of the Prince of the little</hi> Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars, Cyprus, Diarbeck, Aleppo, Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zerum, Damaſcus, Babylon, <hi>the</hi> Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zaradick, Arabians, Abechy, Thunis, Tripoli, Barbary, <hi>and of ſo many other Countries, Iſles, Streights, Paſſages, Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, Families, Generations and of ſo many Thouſand millions of valiant Soldiers, who reſt under the Obedience and Juſtice of me, who am Emperor</hi> Oſman, <hi>Son of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror</hi> Achmet, <hi>of the Emperor</hi> Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met, <hi>of the Emperor</hi> Amurath, <hi>of the Emperor</hi> Selim, <hi>of the Emperor</hi> Solyman, <hi>by the Grace of God, the Retreat of the greateſt Princes of the
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:34980:81"/> World, and Refuge of the moſt honorable Emperors.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>
                  <hi>Amurath</hi> IV. was the Son of <hi>Achmet,</hi> and Brother of <hi>Oſman;</hi> after the Death of <hi>Achmet,</hi> the <hi>Janiſaries</hi> as we have ſaid, put <hi>Muſtapha</hi> his Brother upon the Throne, and afterwards having ſent him back again to Priſon, they crowned <hi>Oſman.</hi> But in the ſequel the ſame Inſolent Militia re-called <hi>Muſtapha,</hi> who cauſed <hi>Oſman</hi> to be ſtrangled, and the Government of that Prince, being diſagreeable unto them, they remanded him to Priſon. <hi>Amurath</hi> at the Age of fifteen years was ſaluted Emperor in the Month of <hi>Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember</hi> 1623. and in the year 1626. he beſieged <hi>Bagdet;</hi> but the <hi>Perſians</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended themſelves ſo vigorouſly, that in the year 1630. the <hi>Turks</hi> were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to withdraw. <hi>Amurath</hi> had the Trouble of loſing <hi>Hali Baſha,</hi> and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers places, which the <hi>Perſians</hi> and <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bians</hi> took from him. Beſides that, the <hi>Poles</hi> and <hi>Coſſacks,</hi> gave him the allarm ſo hot, that the <hi>Viziers</hi> were reſolved to dethrone him, if the Peace, which he made with theſe People, had not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered their minds. <hi>Amurath</hi> concerned
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:34980:81"/> himſelf indirectly in the Affairs of the Proteſtants of <hi>Germany,</hi> at the Sollicita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and under the Conduct of <hi>Ragot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ski;</hi> but it happened to the Confuſion of both. He had at length the Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to be revenged on the <hi>Perſians.</hi> In the year 1638. He ſet out into the Field, as it is thought, one of the moſt numerous Armies that ever the <hi>Otto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> had on foot, and making uſe of the favourable juncture of the War betwixt the <hi>Perſians</hi> and <hi>Mogols,</hi> he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged <hi>Bagdet,</hi> and took it in fourty days time. <hi>Amurath</hi> enjoyed not that Victory long, for his Debauches brought him to his Grave the 8th of <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruary</hi> 1640. in the Two and thirtieth year of his Age.</p>
               <p>This <hi>Amurath</hi> IV. in a Letter which he wrote to the King of <hi>Hungary</hi> in the year 1640. took the following Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>
                        <hi>By the Grace of the Almighty God in Heaven, we</hi> Soly-Mahomet <hi>only God upon Earth, full of invincible Graces, and Omnipotent Emperour of</hi> Babylon in Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea, <hi>from the Sun-riſing to its Setting, King of all the Kings of the Earth, King of all</hi> Arabia <hi>and</hi> Media, <hi>Duke ſprung
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:34980:82"/> from the Noble Stem of</hi> Greece <hi>and</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menia, <hi>born Triumphant King of</hi> Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, <hi>Lord and Protector of the Holy Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulcher of Chriſt Crucified.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ibrahim,</hi> Emperor of the <hi>Turks,</hi> was the Son of <hi>Achmet,</hi> and ſucceeded to his Brother <hi>Amurath</hi> IV. in the year 1640. When this laſt died the Officers of the Port had a great deal ado, to make him come out of the place where he had been in a manner Priſoner for three or four years, ſuſpecting it to be only a pretext to render him Criminal. The <hi>Sultana</hi> his Mother perſuaded him of the truth, having ſhown him the dead Body of his Brother, he came out, and having been crown'd, he gave himſelf wholly over to Voluptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, which was fatal unto him. The loſs of one of his <hi>Sultana</hi>'s, whom the Knights of <hi>Malta</hi> took in the year 1644. betwixt <hi>Rhodes</hi> and <hi>Alexandria,</hi> made him undertake to be revenged on <hi>Malta.</hi> But he turned his Arms a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Candie,</hi> and took the <hi>Canea</hi> in 1645. In the mean time he grew cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el, his Pleaſures made him abandon all care of the Affairs of the Empire, and he became inſupportable to all Men.
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:34980:82"/> The Militia and Officers conſpired a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, and ſent for the <hi>Mufti</hi> and other conſiderable Perſons of the Law, on deſign at firſt to put to Death the <hi>Grand Viſier:</hi> Then they reſolved to depoſe <hi>Ibrahim,</hi> who expreſſing a great Contempt, and much Haughtineſs, did ſo incenſe thoſe mutinous Spirits, that they ſtrangled him the 18th. of <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1649. and placed <hi>Mahomet</hi> his Son up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Throne.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mahomet</hi> IV. was Born the ſecond of <hi>January</hi> 1642. and was raiſed to the Throne ten days after the Death of <hi>Sultan Ibrahim</hi> his Father, who was ſtrangled by the <hi>Janiſaries.</hi> In the years 1663. and 1664. He took in <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary</hi> the Towns of <hi>Newheuſel, Fort-Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rin</hi> or <hi>Serin-wart,</hi> afterwards demoliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ſome other places. The loſs he ſuſtained at the Battle of <hi>Raab</hi> or <hi>St. Godard</hi> made him reſolve to make Peace, which he did the 17th. of <hi>Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember</hi> 1664. He hath been more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate in the preſent War, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he hath loſt <hi>Gran, Newheuſel</hi> and a great many other ſtrong Places and Battles mentioned before. He took the City of <hi>Candie</hi> in the year 1669.
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:34980:83"/> after a very long and tough Siege. The <hi>Venetians</hi> have taken many impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant Places from him in this War, both in the <hi>Morea</hi> and elſewhere. His great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt delight is in Hunting, wherein he ſpends moſt part of the year. For that reaſon it is that he reſides commonly at <hi>Adrianople,</hi> that he may be near the places where there is moſt Game. He goes often to <hi>Lariſſa,</hi> and ſpends ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times Eight or Ten Days together un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der magnificent Tents, pitched half a League from that Town upon the Banks of the <hi>Peneus.</hi> The <hi>Turks</hi> in his time have made many Conqueſts from the <hi>Poles,</hi> from whom they have taken <hi>Caminiec,</hi> and ſome other places. <hi>Sobieski</hi> great Mareſhal of the Crown, and at preſent King of <hi>Poland,</hi> was at that time General of the <hi>Polonian</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, who defeated the <hi>Turks</hi> at the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Battle of <hi>Gotzchin</hi> in the year 1673. He eluded their Projects the two years following, and at length re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced them to deſire a Peace. Since that, the <hi>Turks</hi> undertook a War a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Moſcovites,</hi> and got ſome ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages over them in the year 1678. and the <hi>Poles</hi> having confederated with
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:34980:83"/> the Emperor and Republick of <hi>Venice</hi> in the year 1683. continue to Haraſs and make head againſt them in <hi>Podolia, Ruſſia,</hi> and the neighbouring Territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. Theſe are the Titles that <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homet</hi> IV. takes to himſelf.</p>
               <p>Mahomet Sultan, <hi>by the Infinite Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Almighty Creator, and by the abundant Miracles of the chief of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, Glorious, Great, Invincible, and always Victorious, Emperor of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors of</hi> Conſtantinople <hi>and</hi> Trebizon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, <hi>King of Kings, Diſtributer of Crowns to the greateſt Princes of the Earth, Kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the two ſacred and moſt auguſt Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> Mecha <hi>and</hi> Medina, <hi>Protector of the Holy</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>Maſter of the great Sea, Lord of the greateſt part of</hi> Europe, Aſia <hi>and</hi> Africa, <hi>conquered with our Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorious Sword, Lord of the Eaſt and Weſt, of the great</hi> Anatolia, Bithinia, <hi>of the great City of</hi> Nice, Nichomedia, <hi>the great</hi> Chalcedonia, Phrygia, Lycia, Pamphylia, Tarſis, Paphlagonia, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramania, Capadocia, Ceſarea, <hi>of the great and little</hi> Armenia, Iberia, Geor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gia, Mingrelia, <hi>the</hi> Iron-Gate, Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comania, <hi>of the</hi> Curdes, Parthians, Medes, Perſians, <hi>of</hi> Tauris, Aſſyria,
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:34980:84"/> Meſopotamia, Diarbeck, <hi>of great</hi> Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon, Balzara, Chaldaea, <hi>of the</hi> Holy Land, Syria, Judaea, Canaan, Galilee, Jeruſalem, Samaria, Phenicia, Pale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine, Aleppo, Erzerum, Damaſcus, <hi>of the great</hi> Antioch, <hi>of the</hi> Tyberiade <hi>and</hi> Caſpian Seas, <hi>of the three</hi> Arabias, <hi>the Stony Deſart, and Happy, the</hi> Indian, <hi>and Red Seas, of</hi> Aleppo, Ethiopia, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt, Alexandria <hi>and</hi> Grand Caire, <hi>of</hi> Barbary, Thunis, Tripoli, Fez, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rocco, Cyprus, <hi>of</hi> Rhodes, <hi>all</hi> Greece, Peloponeſus, Thrace, <hi>Great</hi> Romani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a, Macedonia, Theſſaly, Corinthia, Cherſoneſus, Albania, Boſnia, Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>via, Bulgaria, Slavonia, Moldavia, <hi>of</hi> Themeſwar, Dacia, Hungary, Wallachia, Scythia, <hi>the greater and leſſer</hi> Tartary; <hi>and of an infinite num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of other Countries, Kingdoms, and Empires, Iſles, Streights, People, Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, Generations, and of ſo many Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Millions of Valiant Soldiers, who reſt under the obedience and Juſtice of me, who am Emperor</hi> Mahomet, <hi>ſon of the Emperor</hi> Ibrahim, <hi>by the Grace of God, the Retreat of the greateſt Princes of the World, and the Refuge of honourable Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="165" facs="tcp:34980:84"/>
               <p>This Prince <hi>Mahomet</hi> IV. has Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren: the <hi>Sultana</hi> Queen, who is his chief Wife, brought him his firſt Son, ſhe is called <hi>Eumenia,</hi> a Greek by Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; he hath a Brother called <hi>Solyman</hi> and his eldeſt Brother named <hi>Oſman,</hi> is a Dominican Monk, called <hi>Father Dominick of St.</hi> Thomas, who was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with his Mother by the Galleys of <hi>Malta</hi> ſayling to <hi>Alexandria</hi> upon a Pilgrimage to <hi>Mecha.</hi> This Emperor is the greateſt Enemy of Chriſtendom: May Heavens grant, that the projects of that Infidel Prince againſt the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion, may be diſapointed, and that the proud Empire of the Creſcent may one day be ſubject to the glorious Standard of the Croſs, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Auſpices of that great <hi>Caeſar,</hi> who under the lovely name of <hi>Leopold</hi> hath merited to be the firſt, and XIV. Emperor of the moſt <hi>Auguſt</hi> Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> who by his great Prudence and exemplary Piety, by his Conſtant and indefatigable Pains, and by the Grace of the Great God of Armies, hath happily procured to Chriſtendom, all theſe great Victories to the ſhame and confuſion of that fierce and barbarous common
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:34980:85"/> Enemy, and under the Conduct of the Valiant <hi>Charles</hi> IV. Duke of <hi>Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain,</hi> that brave <hi>Hero,</hi> to whom Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom is obliged, that it had time to Relieve <hi>Vienna,</hi> when with unparal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Speed he marched thither, and in view of the Enemy ſupplied the place with Proviſions, Ammunition and 12000 of the beſt men in the Army, who defeated the <hi>Turks</hi> and Rebels before <hi>Presbourg;</hi> that having taken that Town, had a deſign, to make a Bridge there over the <hi>Danube,</hi> thereby to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilitate the paſſage of the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voys to their Camp before <hi>Vienna,</hi> who flew like lightening to ſave the King of <hi>Poland</hi> from the extream Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger wherein he was, being engaged with the Body of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Army near <hi>Barkan,</hi> and who after gained the Battle of <hi>Barkan</hi> that we mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before. This is that Prince who conſidering that his Glorious Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors have Reigned in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> when they had driven the <hi>Mahometans</hi> out of it, hath on that occaſion given ſo many Proofs of his Courage, that it may be ſaid he there revived the <hi>Lorrain</hi> Princes, who heretofore Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:34980:85"/> the Eaſt. He hath ſpared nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Body nor Heart in following their Footſteps, that he might Crown him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with Glory in the Bloody Battle of <hi>Gran,</hi> which he gained. He is the very ſame who hath ſo often repulſed the Fury of the <hi>Turks,</hi> when they were moſt formidable: It is he, in ſhort, who re-took from the Infidels the ſtrong place of <hi>Newheuſel,</hi> which ſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them for a Key to open them a paſſage farther into the Countries of the Chriſtians, and who after the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of the Glorious <hi>Godfrey,</hi> who filled <hi>Europe</hi> with admiration in the year 1096. hath ſo ſignalized himſelf that if he Reign not in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> as his Anceſtors have done, he Reigns, at leaſt, in the hearts of thoſe, who have been the Spectators of his Fortitude and Proweſs.</p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Sic fidei ductus Zelo Bullonius Heros,</l>
                     <l>Ille Ambivaritae <hi>Gothofredus</hi> Marchio Terrae,</l>
                     <l>Moenia dum Solymae, templumque Arcem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que Sionis,</l>
                     <l>Non ſibi, ſed Coelo vincit, Diadema ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perbum</l>
                     <pb n="168" facs="tcp:34980:86"/>
                     <l>Sprevit, &amp; oblatae gemmantia dona Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronae.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Huc <hi>Leopoldorum</hi> virtus animoſa te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendit</l>
                     <l>Auſtriadum, quorum hic celſa <hi>Ptolemai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dos</hi> arce,</l>
                     <l>Viciniſque procul <hi>Salidinum</hi> exegit ab oris,</l>
                     <l>Barbarico referens ſaga candida merſa cruore,</l>
                     <l>Quo gentilitii rubuere inſignia ſcuti:</l>
                     <l>Alter Damiatae muros, Nilotica Clauſtra</l>
                     <l>Diruit, &amp; Phariis tentoria fixit arenis:</l>
                     <l>Ambo, triumphati ſpoliis Orientis onuſti.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Horum magnanimus modò per veſtigia tendit</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Auſtriades,</hi> Caeſar <hi>Leopoldus</hi> Gloria Saecli:</l>
                     <l>Cui victrix Pietas famulantia dirigit Arma,</l>
                     <l>Et Comites ſecum deducit in agmina Divos.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="index">
            <pb facs="tcp:34980:86"/>
            <head>A TABLE OF MATTERS.</head>
            <list>
               <item ana="#role_LABEL">A
<list>
                     <item>AChmet. <hi>Pag.</hi> 153</item>
                     <item>Agria. <hi>Pag.</hi> 17</item>
                     <item>Alba Regalis. <hi>Pag.</hi> 44</item>
                     <item>Altenbourg. <hi>Pag.</hi> 60</item>
                     <item>Altſol. <hi>Pag.</hi> 32</item>
                     <item>Amurath III. <hi>Pag.</hi> 151</item>
                     <item>Amurath IV. <hi>Pag.</hi> 158</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Arms of</hi> Hungary. <hi>Pag.</hi> 92</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item ana="#role_LABEL">B.
<list>
                     <item>BArkan. <hi>Pag.</hi> 53</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Battles of the</hi> Romans. <hi>Pag.</hi> 97</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Of</hi> Mohacz. <hi>Pag.</hi> 98</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Of</hi> St. Godard. <hi>Pag.</hi> 101</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Of</hi> Vienna. <hi>Pag.</hi> 105</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Of</hi> Presbourg. <hi>Pag.</hi> 123</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Of</hi> Barkan. <hi>Pag.</hi> 126</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Of</hi> Gran. <hi>Pag.</hi> 131</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Of</hi> Lepanto. <hi>Pag.</hi> 149</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Of</hi> Candie. <hi>Pag.</hi> 161</item>
                     <item>Bedrac. <hi>Pag.</hi> 76</item>
                     <item>Borſneth. <hi>Pag.</hi> 80</item>
                     <item>Buda. <hi>Pag.</hi> 38</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item ana="#role_LABEL">C.
<list>
                     <item>CAniſa. <hi>Pag.</hi> 45</item>
                     <item>Caſſovia. <hi>Pag.</hi> 16</item>
                     <item>Charles <hi>Duke of</hi> Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain, <hi>his Elegy.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chronogram on the day of the Relief of</hi> Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enna. <hi>Pag.</hi> 112</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ceremonies obſerved at the Coronation of the Kings and Queen of</hi> Hungary. <hi>Pag.</hi> 133</item>
                     <item>Five Churches. <hi>Pag.</hi> 64</item>
                     <item>Cirmium. <hi>Pag.</hi> 71</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Clergy of</hi> Hungary. <hi>Pag.</hi> 84</item>
                     <item>Colzoca. <hi>Pag.</hi> 21</item>
                     <item>Comorra. <hi>Pag.</hi> 58</item>
                     <item>Count <hi>of</hi> Bouquoy, <hi>his Elegy. Pag.</hi> 31</item>
                     <item>Counts <hi>of</hi> Serini, <hi>their Elegy, Death of</hi> Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholas, I. <hi>Pag.</hi> 62, 63</item>
                     <item>Counts <hi>of</hi> Hungary. <hi>Pag.</hi> 81</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:34980:87"/>
                     <item>Cremnitz. <hi>Pag.</hi> 34</item>
                     <item>Marco Antonio Colon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na. <hi>Pag.</hi> 150</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item ana="#role_LABEL">D.
<list>
                     <item>DAnube. <hi>Pag.</hi> 73</item>
                     <item>Debrechim. <hi>Pag.</hi> 21</item>
                     <item>Dotis. <hi>Pag.</hi> 48</item>
                     <item>Drave. <hi>Pag.</hi> 78</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item ana="#role_LABEL">E.
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>EMblem upon the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of</hi> Vienna. <hi>Pag.</hi> 121</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Emperors of the</hi> Turks. <hi>Pag.</hi> 146</item>
                     <item>Eſperies. <hi>Pag.</hi> 71</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Epitaph of the Emperor</hi> Probus. <hi>Pag.</hi> 72</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Of</hi> Ovid. <hi>Pag.</hi> 50</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Of</hi> Louis II. <hi>King of</hi> Hungary. <hi>Pag.</hi> 100</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Of</hi> Count Serini. <hi>Pag.</hi> 67</item>
                     <item>Eſſeck <hi>its</hi> Bridge. <hi>Pag.</hi> 61</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Eſtates of</hi> Hungary. <hi>Pag.</hi> 84</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item ana="#role_LABEL">F.
<list>
                     <item>FIleck. <hi>Pag.</hi> 16</item>
                     <item>Freiſtadt. <hi>Pag.</hi> 28</item>
                     <item>Funs-kirchen. <hi>Pag.</hi> 86</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item ana="#role_LABEL">G.
<list>
                     <item>GIula. <hi>Pag.</hi> 22</item>
                     <item>Gran. <hi>Pag.</hi> 51. 79</item>
                     <item>Gutta. <hi>Pag.</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item ana="#role_LABEL">H.
<list>
                     <item>HAdwan. <hi>Pag.</hi> 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </item>
                     <item>Hern-grundt. <hi>Pag.</hi> 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </item>
                     <item>Hungary. <hi>Pag.</hi> 1. 3</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item ana="#role_LABEL">J.
<list>
                     <item>JAvarin. <hi>Pag.</hi> 5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </item>
                     <item>Ibrahim. <hi>Pag.</hi> 160</item>
                     <item>John III. <hi>King of</hi> Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land. <hi>Pag.</hi> 105</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>His Elegy. Pag.</hi> 114</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>His Letter upon the Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance of</hi> Vienna. <hi>Pag.</hi> 10<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item ana="#role_LABEL">K.
<list>
                     <item>KIngs, look their pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Names. Pag. <hi>8</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item ana="#role_LABEL">L.
<list>
                     <item>LEopold a Town <hi>Pag.</hi> 28</item>
                     <item>Leopold, <hi>the Emperor and his Elegy. Pag.</hi> 167</item>
                     <item>Lepanto. <hi>Pag.</hi> 149</item>
                     <item>Louis, II. <hi>King of</hi> Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary <hi>his Death. Pag.</hi> 98</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item ana="#role_LABEL">M.
<list>
                     <item>MAhomet III. <hi>Pag.</hi> 152</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:34980:87"/>
                     <item>Mahomet IV. <hi>Pag.</hi> 161</item>
                     <item>Maros. <hi>Pag.</hi> 35</item>
                     <item>Matthias Corvin <hi>King of</hi> Hungary. <hi>Pag.</hi> 93</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Medal of the Deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of</hi> Vienna. <hi>Pag.</hi> 113</item>
                     <item>Metroviza. <hi>Pag.</hi> 71</item>
                     <item>Mongatz. <hi>Pag.</hi> 24</item>
                     <item>Muſtapha Sultan. <hi>Pag.</hi> 154</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item ana="#role_LABEL">N.
<list>
                     <item>NEwheuſel. <hi>Pag.</hi> 15</item>
                     <item>Newſol. <hi>Pag.</hi> 29</item>
                     <item>Nitria. <hi>Pag.</hi> 14</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Nobility of</hi> Hungary <hi>vid.</hi> Palatine.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Nobility</hi> Palatine <hi>of</hi> Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary. <hi>Pag.</hi> 62</item>
                     <item>Novigrad. <hi>Pag.</hi> 15</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item ana="#role_LABEL">O.
<list>
                     <item>ONoth. <hi>Pag.</hi> 21</item>
                     <item>Oſman. <hi>Pag.</hi> 155</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item ana="#role_LABEL">P.
<list>
                     <item>PApa. <hi>Pag.</hi> 49</item>
                     <item>Palatines <hi>of</hi> Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. <hi>Pag.</hi> 62, 89</item>
                     <item>Peſt, <hi>Pag.</hi> 35.</item>
                     <item>Petronel. <hi>Pag.</hi> 60</item>
                     <item>Presbourg. <hi>Pag.</hi> 12</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Princes that aſſiſted at the Relief of</hi> Vien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na. <hi>Pag.</hi> 118</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item ana="#role_LABEL">Q.
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alities and Titles <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurped by the</hi> Turkiſh <hi>Emperours. Pag.</hi> 146</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item ana="#role_LABEL">R.
<list>
                     <item>RAab. <hi>Pag.</hi> 55. 77</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Rivers of</hi> Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. <hi>Pag.</hi> 73</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item ana="#role_LABEL">S.
<list>
                     <item>SAbaria. <hi>Pag.</hi> 79</item>
                     <item>Satwar. <hi>Pag.</hi> 49</item>
                     <item>Satmar, <hi>ſee</hi> Zarmar.</item>
                     <item>Save. <hi>Pag.</hi> 78</item>
                     <item>Sarnowitz. <hi>Pag.</hi> 29</item>
                     <item>Servizza. <hi>Pag.</hi> 80</item>
                     <item>Schemnitz. <hi>Pag.</hi> 33</item>
                     <item>Schinta, <hi>Pag.</hi> 27</item>
                     <item>Schut, <hi>an Iſle. Pag.</hi> 54</item>
                     <item>Siget. <hi>Pag.</hi> 61</item>
                     <item>Sirmium, <hi>ſee</hi> Cirmium.</item>
                     <item>Solyman. <hi>Pag.</hi> 146</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>St.</hi> Martins-bourg. <hi>Pag.</hi> 48</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Standard of the</hi> Turks. <hi>Pag.</hi> 117</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item ana="#role_LABEL">T.
<list>
                     <item>TAta. <hi>Pag.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Temeſwar <hi>Pag.</hi> 24</item>
                     <item>Teckely, <hi>Count, his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feat near</hi> Presbourg.</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:34980:88"/>
                     <item>
                        <hi>His Impriſonment at</hi> Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radin. <hi>Pag.</hi> 26</item>
                     <item>Tibiſcus. <hi>Pag.</hi> 76</item>
                     <item>Tirnau. <hi>Pag.</hi> 21</item>
                     <item>Tranſilvania <hi>and its Princes.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Tokay. <hi>Pag.</hi> 20</item>
                     <item>Topolchan. <hi>Pag.</hi> 28</item>
                     <item>Tortoiſe. <hi>Pag.</hi> 59</item>
                     <item>Trenſchin. <hi>Pag.</hi> 29</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Treaty of Alliance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Emperour and King of</hi> Poland. <hi>Pag.</hi> 118</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item ana="#role_LABEL">V.
<list>
                     <item>VAccia. <hi>Pag.</hi> 15</item>
                     <item>Veſprim. <hi>Pag.</hi> 48</item>
                     <item>Vice-grad. <hi>Pag.</hi> 46</item>
                     <item>Vienna <hi>Succoured and Relieved. Pag.</hi> 105</item>
                     <item>Vizovichitz. <hi>Pag.</hi> 34</item>
                     <item>Ungwar. <hi>Pag.</hi> 20</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item ana="#role_LABEL">W.
<list>
                     <item>WAlpo. <hi>Pag.</hi> 70. 80</item>
                     <item>Waradin. <hi>Pag.</hi> 25</item>
                     <item>Waag. <hi>Pag.</hi> 79</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item ana="#role_LABEL">Z.
<list>
                     <item>Zaravas. <hi>Pag.</hi> 23</item>
                     <item>Zatmar. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Zelim. <hi>Pag.</hi> 148</item>
                     <item>Zolnock. <hi>Pag.</hi> 22</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:34980:88"/>
            <head>There is lately Printed for <hi>Hen. Rhodes,</hi> next door to the <hi>Swan Tavern,</hi> near <hi>Brides-Lane</hi> in <hi>Fleet-Street;</hi> the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Books.</head>
            <p>THe Comical Hiſtory of the States and Empires of the Worlds of the Moon and Sun: Writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in <hi>French,</hi> by <hi>Cyrano Bergerac,</hi> newly done into <hi>Engliſh</hi> in <hi>Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Hiſtory of Monaſtical Conventions, and Military Inſtitutions with a Survey of the Court of <hi>Rome.</hi> Or a deſcription of the Religions and Military Orders in <hi>Europe, Aſia</hi> and <hi>Africa,</hi> for above twelve hundred years, being a brief Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of their Inſtitution, Confirmation, Rules, Habits, and manner of Living, the Qualification of their Inſtitutors, and the time of their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Inſtitutions, extending to either Sex, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Together with a Survey of the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> &amp;c. in all the Great Offices, and Officers Eccleſiaſtical and Civil dependant thereon: As alſo the Ceremonies of the Conſiſtories, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clave and thoſe that have been uſed in the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of Cardinals; Election of the High-Biſhop or Pope, and his Triumphant Coronation, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, and that of his taking Poſſeſſion of the <hi>Lateran</hi> Church in <hi>Rome;</hi> with what is obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in his Sickneſs, and the manner of Solem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizing his Funeral Obſequies; with many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things worthy of Note, according to what has been recorded by Candid Authors of divers Nations, and faithfully Collected by <hi>J. S.</hi> price bound one ſhilling.</p>
            <p>The Strange and Prodigious Relations, Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms, and Manners of divers Nations. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining;
<pb facs="tcp:34980:89"/> 
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> the Ridiculous Rites, and Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of the Heathens, in the Worſhip of their ſeveral Deities. <hi>Secondly,</hi> the various Changes of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Religion, and the State it is now in: With a full Relation of the Apparitions, that foretold the fall of <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> as alſo of the dreadful Famine, wherein a Woman Roaſted and Eat her own Child; with the Circumſtances of the Final Deſtruction of that Famous City, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Titus. Thirdly,</hi> The Riſe and Growth of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hometaniſm,</hi> giving an Account of the Doctrine of the <hi>Turkiſh Alcoran. viz.</hi> Their Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and Strange Pilgrimage to <hi>Mecca,</hi> &amp;c. With the Life of that Grand Impoſtor, <hi>Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met;</hi> as alſo Remarks on the Life of <hi>Scanderbeg,</hi> with the many Victories he gain'd over the <hi>Turks. Fourthly,</hi> the Schiſms, and Hereſies in the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Church: Being an Account of thoſe Grand Hereticks, the <hi>Adamites, Mugletonians,</hi> &amp;c. and all intermingled with Pleaſant Relations of the Fantaſtical Rites, both of the Antients and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derns, in the Celebration of their Marriages, and Solemnization of their Funerals: Faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Collected from Ancient and Modern Authors, and adorned with divers Pictures, of ſeveral re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable Paſſages therein; by <hi>R. D.</hi> price bound one Shilling.</p>
            <p>Hiſtorical, and Political Obſervations on the Preſent State of <hi>Turky;</hi> deſcribing the Policy, Religion, Manners, and Military Diſcipline of the <hi>Turks;</hi> with an Account of all the Battles, Seiges, and other Remarkable Tranſactions and Revolutions which have happened, from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Empire, to this Preſent Grand <hi>Seignior.</hi> To which is added his Life, containing all the material Occurrences, that happened during his Reign; together with the
<pb facs="tcp:34980:89"/> Preſent State of <hi>Hungary,</hi> and Hiſtory of the Wars, Price bound 1. <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Converſations on ſeveral Subjects, written in <hi>French</hi> by <hi>M. de Scudery,</hi> and done into <hi>Engliſh,</hi> by <hi>Ferrand Spence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>London</hi> Jilt, or the Politick Whore, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is ſhewed all the Artifices and Stratagems, which the Ladies of Pleaſure make uſe of, for the Intriguing and Decoying of Men: Interwo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven with ſeveral pleaſant Stories of the Miſſes ingenious Performances, in two Parts.</p>
            <p>The School of Recreation; or the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man's Tutor, to thoſe moſt Ingenious Exerciſes, of Hunting, Racing, Hawking, Riding, Cock-Fighting, Fowling, Fiſhing, Shooting, Bowling, Tennis, Ringing, Billiards, price bound one Shilling.</p>
            <p>Coffee-Houſe Jeſts, Refined and Enlarged, by the Author of the <hi>Oxford</hi> Jeſts, the Fourth Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, with large Additions, price bound one Shilling.</p>
            <p>Wit's Cabinet, or a Campanion for Young<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and Ladies: Containing the whole Art of Wooing, and making Love; with the beſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plemental Letters, Elegant Epiſtles, Amorous Addreſſes, and Anſwers, in a moſt Pleaſant and Ingenious ſtrain, with the neweſt Songs, Sung at Court, and both Theatres. The School of <hi>Bac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus,</hi> or the whole Art of Drinking, taught by a New, and moſt Learned Method. The Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of all ſorts of Dreams. The Art of Chiromancy, and Palmiſtry. The ſeveral ſorts of Coſmeticks, for Clearing, and Beautifying the Face, and taking away all Freckles, Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phews, Tetters, Ring-worms, and preſerving the Complexion; together with the way of making all ſorts of Perfumes and Sweet-Waters.
<pb facs="tcp:34980:90"/> The uſe of Mettals, and Precious Stones, and the way to Counterfeit them. Several of the choiceſt Secrets of Art and Nature. Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Rules for Gentile Behaviour of Young<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and Ladies, in all Companies. Several ſorts of News, from divers Parts, very Jocoſe and Pleaſant, price bound one Shilling.</p>
            <p>The Chriſtian's Guide to Devotion, with Rules and Directions for a Holy Life; as alſo Meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Prayers, by <hi>S. Smith,</hi> the Second Editi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, price bound 1 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The whole Duty of a Communicant; being Rules and Directions, for the Worthy Receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the moſt Holy Sacrament of the Lord's Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, by the Reverend Father in God <hi>John Gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> late Lord Biſhop of <hi>Exeter:</hi> The Second Edition, with Additions out of that Reverend Prelate's Original Copies, price bound 1 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Hiſtory of <hi>Kara Muſtapha,</hi> the late Grand <hi>Viſier,</hi> being a faithful Account of the Riſe, and ſeveral Degrees of his Fortune; his Amours in the <hi>Seraglio,</hi> his Exploits, the true Cauſe of his undertaking the Siege of <hi>Vienna,</hi> together with the Particulars of his Death. Originally Written in <hi>French,</hi> and Faithfully Tranſlated into <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> by <hi>F. Philo,</hi> price bound 1 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Seraſquier Baſſa,</hi> or an Hiſtorical Novel of the times, containing all that paſſed at the Siege of <hi>Buda,</hi> out of <hi>French,</hi> price bound one ſhilling.</p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:34980:90"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
